In this session, we will look at
statistical models that can be used to
combine and compare the results of
several studies. More specifically, we
will look at how you can investigate and
model heterogeneity.
In a typical meta analysis, the
following steps can be distinguished. We
formulate our research question.
We plan our study. We start looking for
studies that possibly could be relevant
for our meta analysis.
We make a selection of the relevant
studies based on inclusion and exclusion
criteria.
We start extracting data that are
relevant for a met analysis. This is we
look at outcome variables. We look at
the study characteristics that possibly
are related to the outcomes and we look
at the quality of the studies.
We convert all the data to a common
effect size measure
and then we combine and compare the
effect sizes. We look for moderator
variables and finally we discuss and
report the results. In this session we
will look especially to um step seven
and eight the combination and comparison
of effect sizes and looking for
moderator variables.
First the fixed effects model.
In the fixed effects model,
we say that an observed effect size and
here I use the symbol t to refer to
whatever uh type of effect size we have
at hand. So that can be standardized
mean differences but that can also be
correlation coefficients or loss ratios
or any other type of effect size.
So in this model we say well an observed
effect size is equal to the population
effect size plus a random deviation.
And very often in a meta analysis we use
an effect size from which we know that
the sampling distribution is a normal
distribution. In other words, in this
model R is assumed to follow a normal
distribution with mean equal to zero and
with a specific variance.
Moreover, for commonly used effect size
measures, the sampling variance, so the
variance of R is known. For instance,
for the standardized mean difference, we
have seen that the sampling variance is
more or less equal to 4 divided by n.
So, uh four divided by the total sample
size.
So, we can
estimate the sampling variance before we
start our meta analysis. So, therefore,
sampling variances are assumed or are
considered as known in our meta
analysis.
So the observed effect size is equal
equal to the population effect size plus
a random deviation. We assume that that
random deviation is normally distributed
with variance equal to uh sigma squar r
which is equal to the standard error
squared
which is equal to the sampling variance.
In a fixed effects model that can be
used for meta analysis, we say that if
we have a set of observed effect sizes,
then we say that each observed effect
size is equal to a population effect
size plus random deviation.
And moreover, we say that all the
population effect sizes for all the
studies are exactly the same. So theta_1
is equal to theta 2 is equal to theta in
general.
Therefore this model is also called a
fixed effects model. So we assume that
the population effect is
the same for all studies. It's fixed.
It's not random.
So if we have m multiple uh study
studies then the effect sizes are
assumed to follow a normal distribution
around a population effect size theta
and this variation is only due to
sampling variance because in a specific
study
we take a sample rather than study the
whole population and therefore there is
that random uh deviation R. And so in
another study we take another sample and
therefore we have another residual R.
And so all these residuals are assumed
to follow a normal distribution.
If we would have samples that are
infinitely large then these residuals
would be equal to zero. Then our
observed effect size is equal to the
population effect size. And because all
the population effect sizes are the same
for all studies, all observed effect
sizes would be exactly the same.
How can we estimate uh the common
population effect size? Well, we can
calculate an average of all the observed
effect sizes. So we sum all the observed
effect sizes and we divide this sum by
the number of effect sizes or the number
of studies um g
the sampling variance
of this uh average effect size is equal
to the sampling variance of an
individual effect size divided by k. So
what does it mean? So the more studies
we combine, so the more effect sizes we
combine, the smaller the sampling
variance of the estimate will become. So
the more we are sure that our estimate
is close to the population effect size
theta.
Of course, even if you use a fixed
effects model, uh very often population
um studies are not of exactly the same
size. So you may have small studies, you
may have larger studies and therefore
the sampling variance is probably not
the same for all these studies. For a
large study, the sampling variance is
small
and so we have a small sampling
distribution.
For a small study, the sampling variance
is large. So we have a large sampling
distribution. But in a fixed effects
model, we assume that all means of these
sampling distributions are equal to each
other, they're equal to the common
population effect size.
So if in such a situation where the
sample sizes of the studies can vary,
it's not a good idea to use a simple
mean, a simple average of the of the
observed effect sizes in order to
estimate uh the common population effect
size. It's more efficient if we use
precision weighted mean.
This is a mean of the observed effect
sizes with weights equal to the
precision of the observed effect size
and the precision of an observed effect
size is defined as one over the sampling
variance of that uh individual effect
size.
So for a small study
the sampling variance will be large and
therefore the weight so the precision
will be small. So the weight that will
be given to that small study will be
small.
The sampling variance of this estimate
now is equal to one over the sum of the
precisions of the individual estimates.
What does this mean? It means that if we
have very precise estimates of the
population effect size from our
individual studies.
So this is in case we have large
individual studies then the precision
will be large for these individual
studies. So if we sum all these
precisions we will get a large value.
If we take one over the sum of the
precisions,
we get a small value. So if you combine
the results of very precise estimates,
then the sampling variance will become
the sampling variance of the average
observed effect size will become small.
which means that the observed
that the mean of the observed effect
sizes uh will be a precise estimate of
um the common population effect size.
Note also that the more studies we
combine,
the more terms we add.
So the sum of the precisions will become
larger
the more effect sizes we have because we
sum more precisions and all these
precisions are positive. So the more
studies the more effect sizes we combine
the larger the sum of the precisions and
therefore one over the sum of the
precisions will become smaller and so
the sampling variance of our new
estimate will become smaller. So we will
get a more precise estimate of the
population effect. The more studies we
combine and the more precise each of
these individual studies are,
it can be shown that the sampling
variance of our estimate is indeed
smallest if we combine the observed
effect sizes by using a precision
weighted mean.
If the observed effect sizes follow a
normal distribution
with mean the population effect size and
with a specific variance
then the mean of the observed effect
sizes will also follow a normal
distribution with the same mean so with
the same uh population effect size as
the mean and with a variance which is
equal to uh one over the sum of the
precisions.
So therefore
a standardized
estimate will follow a standard normal
distribution. And why is this
interesting? Well, we can use it in two
ways.
First to test a null hypothesis.
Suppose that you your null hypothesis is
that theta so the population effect size
is equal to a specific value theta 0. In
that case if that would be true. So
under the assumption that the null
hypothesis is true. This would mean that
the estimate minus the theta under the
null hypothesis divided by the sampling
uh by the standard deviation of the
sampling distribution follows a standard
normal distribution.
Note that theta 0 is defined or is um
specified under the null hypothesis. And
we also know the standard deviation of
our estimate. The standard deviation of
our estimate is the square root of one
over the sum of the precisions of the
individual effect sizes. And we know how
precise each of the individual effect
sizes are. For instance, for the
standardized mean difference,
the precision of one standardized mean
difference is one over the sampling
variance. It's 1 over 4 / n. So it's n /
4. So we know in advance what the
precision is of individual effect sizes
and therefore we can also derive what
the precision is of um our mean
estimate.
And so we can calculate that test
statistic. If our test statistic
um has a very large value or a very
small value then we will reject the null
hypothesis that theta is equal to theta
0.
We can also use the fact that uh our
standardized
um estimate follows a normal
distribution or a standard normal
distribution, we can also use this
property or this feature to construct a
95% confidence interval. So if we take
our estimate and we subtract and we add
1.96
times the standard deviation of the
sampling distribution then we obtain the
under and upper limit of a 95%
confidence interval
assessing heterogeneity.
We discussed a fixed effects model.
fixed effects model that assumes that
the population effect size is the same
for all studies so that we have one
common theta.
If this is not the case
then the way we estimated
that theta and the way we test that
theta is not valid
and very often that assumption is a very
strong assumption which probably is
violated often in practice. For
instance, there can be a lot of
differences between studies. For
instance, in the kind of participants in
study context in the outcome variable
and how the outcome variable is measured
in the independent variable or the
treatment and how this treatment is
operationalized in the study design and
so on.
So there can be many differences
differences between studies and it's
unlikely that none of these differences
so none of these stud characteristics
affect the size of the population
effect.
So therefore
using a fixed effects model may not be a
good idea.
You can say well maybe sometimes it is
not as uh such a bad idea to assume that
the population effect size is the same
in all studies but look for instance at
the many labs projects. So in this
projects the idea was let's try to
replicate
um some studies in several laboratories
around the world. So different research
groups are trying to replicate exactly
the findings that were found in in
specific studies.
And it was found that in in many of
these replications,
the effect sizes that were found were
not the same. But not only not the same,
there were varying more than you would
expect based on samp sampling variance
alone.
So we cannot explain the variation in
effect sizes that was found um over all
these research groups by thinking about
sampling variance alone. Probably there
were systematic differences between
these studies.
So even if you try to replicate
perfectly studies then still it seems
that there still are some small uh
systematic differences between studies
that affect um the effect that is
studied.
So maybe the use of a fixed effects
model is not very often or maybe hardly
maybe never a good idea.
But how can you know whether the
assumption that the population effect
size is the same for all studies? How
can you know this assumption makes
sense? Well, one possibility is to do a
homogeneity test. The null hypothesis is
that all population effect sizes are
exactly the same. The alternative
hypothesis
is not that all population effect sizes
are different, but the alternative
hypothesis is that they're not all the
same. So it could mean that at least
that that one uh population effect size
differs from the others. But it's also
possible that two differ from each other
or defer from the others or they're very
um there are many uh alternative
scenarios.
But in general the alternative
hypothesis says they're not all the
same. So at least one effect size
differs from uh another.
How can we test this assumption of
homogeneity?
Well, we can use the Q statistic. And if
you look at the Q statistic, then you
see that it is a kind it looks like a
kind of variance. So you look at a
deviation between observed effect sizes
and the mean effect size.
And these deviations of course these can
be positive these can be negative but
you square these deviations
so that all deviations become positive.
Then you sum these squared deviations
and note that you also weight the
squared deviations. So you will
especially look at um studies from uh
effect sizes from large studies.
So if for a large study
there is a deviation of the observed
effect size from the population effect
size, well this deviation will count
much more than the deviation for a small
study.
And so by summing all these weighted
square deviations, you get of course a
positive value. And the more variation
there is in observed effect sizes, the
larger that Q statistic.
It can be shown that under the null
hypothesis that all population effect
sizes are the same, the Q statistic will
follow a k square distribution. A k
square distribution
with k minus one degrees of freedom.
Note that k refers here to the number of
studies or the number of effect sizes.
we will reject the null hypothesis if we
obtain a very large Q statistic. So if
our Q statistic is really in the right
tail of that K square distribution.
So for instance in the 5% largest uh or
more extreme values of that k square
distribution
random effects models.
So we have seen that often a fixed
effects model
is or using a fixed effects model is not
a good idea because very often the
assumption that population effect sizes
are the same
is likely to be violated. You can test
whether this uh assumption is violated
but
yeah a problem with that homogeneity
test is that the power is not very high.
So it is possible that you do not reject
the null hypothesis that all population
effect sizes are the same but still that
there are differences between population
effect sizes. So in that case it's it's
still not a good idea to use a fixed
effects model although the null
hypothesis that population effect sizes
are the same is not rejected.
Maybe it's a better idea to say from the
beginning that maybe population effect
sizes can vary over studies.
This is what is done is in a random
effects model.
The observed effect size TJ
is assumed to be equal to the population
effect size for that study J plus a
random deviation.
And again the random deviation RJ is
assumed to follow a a normal
distribution
and for most common effect sizes uh like
standardized mean differences locals
ratios and so on we can already estimate
the variance of R.
But now there is a second equation. A
second equation that says the population
effect size in study J is assumed to be
equal to
a mean effect size theta plus a random
deviation that is typical for that study
that is specific for that study. So the
UJ
so the UJ is a difference or the
deviation
of the population effect size in study J
from the mean effect size over all
studies
and also this residual UJ is assumed to
follow a normal distribution.
So in this model we assume that each uh
study can have its own population effect
size. Of course it's possible that in
some of the studies population effect
size is exactly the same.
And moreover we assume that these
population effect sizes follow a normal
distribution.
So a normal distribution with mean equal
to theta and with variance equal to the
variance of u.
Of course this does not mean that
um in a specific study the observed
effect size is equal to the population
effect size. So on top of the variation
between population effect sizes, we have
also variation of observed effect sizes
around population effect sizes. So for
instance, in study five, the mean or the
population effect size is equal to theta
5, but the observed effect size T5 can
be somewhat smaller or somewhat larger
than theta 5.
comparing the fixed effects model and
the random effects model.
So here you can see again the fixed
effects model. The observed effect size
is equal to a common population effect
size plus random deviation due to the
fact that within that study only a
sample is taken.
In the random effects model, we say the
observed effect size is equal to a
population effect size that is typical
to that study J plus a random deviation
due to sampling variance.
And the population effect size of that
study is equal to a mean population
effect size plus a deviation
specific for that study. Or we can write
the two equations in one equation. So
the observed effect size in study J is
equal to an overall mean effect size
over all studies
plus the deviation of the population
effect size from study J from the mean
population effect size and plus a random
deviation of the observed effect size
from the population effect size from
that study J.
So note that in two in the two models so
both in the fixed effects model and
random effects model we have uh our
theta but the theta now has a different
interpretation in both models. In a
fixed effects model, the theta refers to
the overall no sorry to the common
population effect size common population
effect size for all studies. Whereas in
the random effects model, the theta
refers to the mean population effect
size. So the mean of that normal
distribution of population effect sizes.
Note that in a fixed effects model,
there is only one parameter to be
estimated, more specifically theta. We
want to estimate the common population
effect size. We do not have to estimate
the variance of R because we already
know this variance before we start our
meta analysis. Again for uh an observed
uh standardized mean difference the
sampling variance is about 4 divided by
n. So we do not have to estimate this
parameter. It's not an unknown
parameter. In the random effects model
there are two unknown parameters.
We have to estimate the mean population
effect size theta. But on top of that we
also will estimate the variance between
studies in the population effect sizes.
So we also want to estimate the variance
of the use.
Again the variance in the Rs uh does not
have to be estimated anymore. We already
know them before starting our meta
analysis.
Meta analysis sometimes has been have
been criticized because and especially
random effects model uh meta analysis
because you are estimating a mean
uh a mean effect
the mean population effect sizes overall
population effect sizes. And the idea is
well
if the population effect size can vary
over studies because studies differ in a
lot of aspects. So does it make sense
to combine all these effect sizes? Are
we not mixing apples and oranges?
And I think the answer of Jean Claus who
started um or who invented um the idea
of meta analysis
the answer of Jean Claus was well
it's not interesting uh to combine
apples with apples or oranges with
oranges. It's much more interesting to
combine apples and oranges because in
that way you can compare apples and
oranges.
So to explain this somewhat further,
the advantage of combining the results
of studies that are not done in exactly
the same way and for which the
population effect sizes may be not
exactly the same. Well, what is
interesting about such meta analysis is
that we can test whether there is
hetrogenity, whether there is
homogeneity and suppose that we see that
population effect sizes are very similar
despite the fact that um uh that the
studies were set up in in various ways
or that the treatments were done
operationalized in different ways or
that population studied were not exactly
the same in all studies. So despite
these differences between studies, if
despite these differences between
studies, we still find the same
population effect then this is an
interesting finding then this means that
we can generalize this effect to a
variety of situations.
If on the contrary we find that there is
heterogeneity so that population effect
sizes are not the same. Well then an an
additional interesting question is why
are there differences? Can we study in
what situations for what types of
studies the effect is larger than for
what other types of studies. So in this
way we can study much more questions and
can be answered by individual studies.
So for instance, we can study whether
the effect is larger in the United
States compared to Europe
and so on. An additional advantage of
combining the results of studies even if
these studies um do not exactly do
exactly the same things is that in this
way we can increase the size of our
metalic data set. And so by increasing
the size of our metal analytic data set,
so by increasing the number of effect
sizes in our meta analysis, we can
increase the accuracy or we can increase
the precision of our mean estimate and
at the same time we can increase the
statistical power in doing statistical
tests. So there are several advantages
of uh combining
even heterogeneous study results. Of
course, it does not make sense to
combine whatever numbers.
So if you want to combine the results of
several studies, you have to look at or
you have to evaluate whether there is a
common ground in these studies. Do these
studies uh study more or less the same
research question?
So to give an example of a of meta
analysis that was done by glass. So
class did a huge meta analysis uh
studying the effect of psychological
treatments
but there are different types of
psychological treatments.
And so he has been criticized because he
was combining effects of a variety of
types of psychological treatments. And
based on the meta analysis, he was
saying something about the average
effect of a psychological treatment.
But people were saying, well, there is
not such a typical psychological
treatment. So what is the meaning of
this mean population effect size for
psychological treatments?
But what was interesting in the meta
analysis of of class is that in this way
he could compare different types of
treatments. He could study whether for
instance psychotherapy gave better or
worse results compared to um client
center therapy and so on
comparing the fixed effects model and
random effects model.
So in a random effects model,
if we want to estimate um
uh the mean population effect size using
the results of several studies, so using
multiple observed effect sizes, we can
again calculate
uh a mean of these observed effect sizes
uh precision weighted mean. So you can
see that formula here is exactly the
same as for the fixed effects model.
But there is a difference. The
difference is that the precision is now
different. Precision is one over the
variance of the observed effect size.
But the difference is in a fixed effects
model the variance of observed effect
sizes is simply the sampling variance.
So it's the variance of the R. Whereas
in a random effects model we say no
there are two residuals there are two
deviations two types of deviations. An
observed effect size can be smaller than
other observed effect sizes because
by coincidence we have taken a sample
and in that sample the observed effect
size is smaller than the population
effect size. But it's also possible that
the population effect size in that study
was smaller than the population effect
size than the mean population effect
size.
So in fact the variation in observed
effect sizes is now due to these two
sources of uh deviations.
So it's equal to the sampling variance
plus the variance in the use and in the
metalic literature. Very often the
symbol toao squared is used to refer to
this variance in population effect
sizes.
What is a consequence for a mean effect?
Well, it can go in a two directions. So
in general, the fixed effects model and
the random effects model estimate of
theta is somewhat similar.
But if you look at the weights that are
given, the weights in the random effects
model will be more similar to each
other.
So the weights are equal to one over the
precision and the precision
depends in a random effects model both
on the to squared which is the same for
all studies and on the sampling variance
which is different for different
studies. In a fixed effects model, um
the precision only depends on the
sampling variance which is different for
each study.
So in a fixed effects model, the weights
can differ a lot over studies.
In the random effects model, the rates
are more similar.
And I think this makes sense. This makes
sense in because
in if we uh assume that population
effect sizes may not be exactly the same
in all studies. So that there is a
distribution of population effect sizes
and we want to say something about the
mean of that distribution. We are going
to give enough weight also to smaller
studies. Okay. In smaller studies there
is a lot of sampling variance. So we we
give less weight to that study compared
to a large study. But still we want to
give enough weight to that effect size
from that study because in that study an
other population effect size is
estimated compared to other studies and
therefore we also want to give enough
weight to that individual study.
What about the precision? So again the
precision of our estimate when using a
random effects model is equal to one
over the sampling variance. So it's
equal to the sum of the precisions of um
all observed effect sizes. So it's again
exactly the same formula as for a fixed
effects model but again the difference
is in that variance of t. In fixed
effects model, it's the s the sampling
variance only. In the random effects
model, this variance of t is equal to
the sum of two uh types of variance
sampling variance and the uh the true
variance or the variance in population
effect sizes
to squar.
So this means
that in a random effects model,
the precision of an individual effect
size of an individual observed effect
size is smaller
and therefore the precision of our
weight of sorry the precision of our
mean is also smaller.
And again I think this makes sense. Um
now we take into account the additional
uncertainty. We say well each study
has its own population effect size and
we want to say something about the mean
of the population of effect sizes but we
only have a sample of studies. And so if
we had observed an effect size in an
additional study, maybe in that
additional study another population
effect size would have been estimated.
And so because now we have an additional
uncertainty
because we do not have information on
many
possible um yeah about many population
effect sizes of studies that could have
been performed.
um our estimate is less precise
an example.
So here we can see the results of a
small meta analysis done by uh
Borenstein
HS and Rostein.
So a meta analysis of about uh six
studies look at the mean effect size.
The mean effect size is equal to 0.397.
Standard error is equal to 0062
when using a fixed effects model.
Also look at the size of the dots in the
confidence intervals. The size of the
dots
is pre uh proportional
to the weight that is given to that
effect size.
So you can see that the study of dunuts
so the fourth study has a very large
dot. This means that a lot of weight is
given to that individual study probably
because this is a large study. So the
sample size is large. Therefore you can
also see that the confidence interval is
uh smaller. So it's a more precise
estimate and so more weight is given to
that study.
Now look at the results of the random
effects model.
You can see that the mean effect now is
so much similar but standard error is
much larger. It used to be 0
062. Now it's 0
107. So it's almost twice as large. So
the standard error is larger. So the the
sampling variance is larger. The
precision is smaller.
The confidence interval is also larger.
So this indicates that we take into
account the additional uncertainty.
Also look at the size of the dots.
Before the study of donut had a much
larger dot than the other studies.
Whereas now this dot is still somewhat
larger than for the other studies. But
the size of the dots are uh more
similar. This is because we are using
more similar weights in our random
effects model because in our weights we
also take into account the to squared
and the to squar is the same for all
studies. So it's a constant.
How can we test and uh
and calculate interval estimates for
theta? Well, again the same slide as
before.
The only difference now is that the
standard deviation of theta hat. So the
standard the sample yeah the standard
deviation of the sampling distribution
of our estimate of the mean population
effect size now is the sum or is equal
to the square root of the sum of two
variances rather than the square root of
one
uh variance.
So I said the precision
or the accuracy is smaller when using a
random effects model. So our confidence
interval will be larger. It also means
that the power is smaller. If our
confidence is larger then the
probability that for instance a value of
zero is included in a confidence
interval will be larger. So the
probability that we will reject the null
hypothesis that an effect is equal to
zero will become smaller. So when we use
a random effects model the power is
smaller and we have a smaller accuracy.
You may wonder
this is not what we want. So why not
using a fixed effects model?
So the reason is simple. The fixed
effects model is only appropriate if
population effect sizes are exactly the
same. So if population effect sizes are
not the same in all studies then the
results of the fixed effects model is
simply wrong are simply wrong.
And so indeed we have more power and the
confidence interval indeed are smaller
when using a fixed effects model. But
this is because we do not take into
account the additional uncertainty we
have about the mean effect size when
population effect sizes are not exactly
the same.
So the power and the accuracy is
artificially
higher when using a fixed effects model.
The next question is well we have seen
in our weights we have to use to squar
um we have to use to squar as well to
calculate the precision of our estimate
and so to do significance tests and to
calculate confidence intervals. But how
can you obtain to squar
before we do the meta analysis? We can
already estimate or calculate the
sampling variance but to squar cannot be
calculated before our meta analysis. We
have to estimate this in our meta
analysis. And how can we estimate to
squ? Because in the random effects model
we have seen the observed effect size in
study J is equal to a mean population
effect size plus a residual and plus
another residual. So we have two
residuals. For each observed effect size
we have two residuals. So how can we
disentangle these two sources of
variance?
Well, the reason is simple
because we already know the variance of
R.
So the variance in the observed effect
sizes is the sum of the variance of
U. So to squar plus the sampling
variance because we know the sampling
variance. So we know the variance of R.
we can calculate and then we also see
how much variation there is in the
observed effect sizes. We can um
subtract
um the variance in observed we can take
the variance in the observed effect
sizes and subtract the sampling variance
to get an uh an estimate of the variance
of the use or to squared.
Of course, the sampling variance or the
variance of R is not the same for all
studies. So for larger studies, the
sampling variance will be smaller than
for smaller studies. So a solution could
be that we can that we calculate the
mean of these sampling variances. So we
sum we sum all the sampling variances
and we divide it by the number of
studies. So this is what was proposed by
hatches and 1985.
So the estimate of to squar is the
variance in or the observed variance in
the observed effect sizes minus the mean
estimated sampling variance.
Note that sometimes a conditional random
effects model approach is used which
means well one starts from a fixed
effects model one performs a homogeneity
test and if the homogeneity test shows
that the null hypothesis of homogeneity
can be rejected. So if there is evidence
for heterogeneity
then one says okay fix using a fixed
effects model was not a good idea let's
continue with a random effects model.
I want to mention very clearly that this
conditional random effects model is not
a good approach.
The problem is that the power of the
homogeneity test is not very good.
So it is possible that the assumption
that all population effect sizes are the
same that this assumption is simply
wrong. But still that this assumption is
not rejected in our homogeneity test.
And in that case in a conditional random
effects model approach one would
continue using a fixed effects model
whereas a random effects model would be
more appropriate.
So my suggestion is to use always random
effects model.
So a random effects model does not
assume that uh population effect sizes
are the same for all studies. But
it is allowed that population effect
sizes are the same for all studies. In
that situation the variance that we
estimate the variance in population
effect sizes will be probably um very
small. So our estimate of the variance
between population effect sizes. So the
variance of u so the to squar probably
will be very small or even equal to
zero.
There is still some discussion about
whether it is a good idea to use a
random effects model.
So a first issue is
yeah does it make sense to consider our
sample
of studies or the sample of
effect sizes as a random sample of a
population of effect sizes. So our
thetas
from our set of studies, we consider
these thetas as a random sample from
that normal distribution of thetas.
But does it make sense to consider
studies as a random sample?
Another issue is
well are we interested in that
population of
population effect sizes? Maybe we are
only interested in these specific
treatments that were studied in the
studies we have. So maybe we do not want
to generalize to other population effect
sizes than the population effect sizes
that were studied in our set of studies.
Another question is does it make sense
to assume that population effect sizes
are normally distributed?
Maybe this does not make sense. Of
course, we can test whether
these effect sizes are normally
distributed.
But the problem is very often in a meta
analysis we do not have a lot of effect
sizes. We do not have a lot of studies.
Say um suppose that we only have 10 or
20 or even 30 studies. That's not enough
to test with enough power the null
hypothesis that our uh effect sizes stem
from a normal distribution.
And then a final issue
is if we use random effects model
then we are giving more or less the same
weight to all studies. So we give uh
relatively a lot of weight to small
studies as well.
In a fixed effects model we give we do
not give a lot of weight to small
studies. And we have seen in the first
session
that publication bias is especially
apparent for small studies. In small
studies, there is a lot of variation in
effect sizes. So probably only the
largest effect sizes for small studies
will be published or reported because
only the largest effect sizes will be
statistically significant.
So therefore the problem of publication
bias
will be will have a larger effect on the
results of a meta analysis if we are
giving uh relatively large weights to
the small studies which is done in the
random effects model.
In a fixed effects model small studies
are downweighted much more.
So for if there is publication bias,
this will most be most apparent when
using a random effects model, which is
another argument against the use of
random effects model. So there are still
some questions that are asked um or
still some critiques that are given on
the use of random effects model.
Understanding differences in
So suppose
that you find that there is indeed
heterogeneity that population effect
sizes are not the same for all studies.
Of course this is not a very interesting
finding.
It's or or it raises another question.
Why is there variation between studies?
Can we
explain why in some studies the effect
size is larger than in other studies?
And one possibility is to uh use a model
with a categorical
um predictor, a categorical variable, a
categorical study characteristic.
So that's a characteristic that divides
studies in categories. For instance,
maybe you say
or you think that there can be
differences in the effects um of studies
done in the United States uh compared to
um effects of studies done in Europe. So
then we have two categories of studies
and in the simplest model we say well
within these categories population
effect sizes are the same but it is
possible that population effect sizes
differ over categories.
Of course this does not mean that within
categories observed effect sizes will be
exactly the same because again you have
that sampling variance. So a population
effect size or an observed effect size
in a specific study can still be
somewhat smaller or somewhat larger than
the population effect size from that
study. But in this model,
we say well the observed effect size
from study J in category I is equal to
the population effect size for that
category I plus random deviation.
Random deviation due to sampling
variance and again sampling variance can
be estimated. So what uh population
parameters we have to estimate here are
the population effect sizes for all
these categories. So the theta I
look at the Q statistic that we have
seen before. we can calculate exactly
the same Q statistic but now I used uh
two summation marks because yeah we have
um effect sizes from multiple studies
from multiple categories.
What we can do is so I said before the Q
can be considered as a kind of variance
or a statistic that expresses how much
variation there is um of the observed
effect sizes around the overall mean
effect size.
We can do a kind of analysis of variance
by splitting this total variability in
observed effect sizes in two parts. We
can say well observed effect sizes can
vary around the overall mean because of
two
um there are two explanations or there
can be two explanations. The first
explanation is that there are
differences between the population means
of different categories
and a second explanation is well within
categories the observed effect sizes can
vary.
So we can split
um the the Q statistic that we have seen
before in two separate Q statistics and
I will give uh the formulas in on the
next slide but note that we that each of
these Q statistics follow a kiquare
distribution.
So the Q total
is in fact um if we use this Q total and
compare this Q statistic to a K square
distribution then we are performing a
homogeneated test the same test as the
one that we have done before. The Q
between
tests whether there is variability
between categories. So it's a kind of
moderator test. So it tests whether the
size of the effect
depends on the category. If the size of
the effect depends on the category, then
the category or the categorical variable
is called a moderator variable. The
category moderates the effect of the
intervention.
Within categories,
there still can be variability. So it's
again a kind of homogeneity test but
it's testing the homogeneity within
categories.
So because now we are splitting the
total variance in two parts. Um this is
a kind of analysis of variance. But note
a difference with an ordinary analysis
of variance is that now we are going to
give weights. We are going to look
especially um at larger studies. they
are going to give more weight to larger
studies. So this is a weighted analysis.
How does the formulas look like? Well, Q
total, we have already seen this Q
total. This Q total is split in two Q's.
The Q between
expresses the size of variation between
category uh population effect sizes or
category means.
So we look at the mean population effect
size estimate within each category I
and we calculate the deviation with the
overall estimate or the overall mean
estimate. We square this um deviation.
We wait this deviation this squared
deviation and we sum this overall
categories. Note that the weight that is
given to each category is equal to the
sum of the weights um of all these
studies within that category.
The Q within is calculated by
calculating the Q within for each
category separately and then summing all
these Q withins. And how is the Q within
for a specific category I calculated?
Well, we look at the squared deviations
of the observed effect sizes from the
mean effect size from this category.
We multiply it by the weight um and we
sum everything um overall observed
effect sizes within that category.
Note that if we found that the
categorical variable has a moderating
effect so that there are differences
between categories of studies then uh an
interesting question is between which
two or between what pairs of categories
there are differences. I'm not going to
discuss this but you can look at the
paper of hatches and pickot um to look
at um how you can test contrasts in much
the same way as in ordinary analysis of
variance you can calculate or test
contrasts
between pairs of categories
an example let's go back to the example
of Steve Stefan Renbush about the
teacher expectancy effects
So we have our 19 observed effect sizes
together with their standard error. So
the square of the sampling variances and
we have different categories of studies.
In some studies there was no prior
contact between uh students and
teachers. In other studies there was one
week of prior contact other studies two
weeks or in still other studies three or
more than three weeks.
I've done a met meta analysis using a
fixed effects model and using a random
effects model. So on the right side of
this graph you can see the results of
the fixed effects model and the random
effects model analysis. Note that the
estimate of theta is somewhat similar
for the two approaches. But for the
random effects model, the confidence
interval is much larger than for the
fixed effects model because now we take
into account that there may be
systematic variation between studies. So
there may be variation between
population effect sizes.
Here I ordered the effect sizes
according to the number of weeks of
prior contact.
And what is interesting is that in the
first category, the first category of
studies in which there was no prior
contact,
observed effect sizes were relatively
large. If there was one week of prior
contact, on average, effect sizes were
somewhat smaller. After two weeks of
prior contact, effect sizes were still
smaller and after three weeks of prior
contact, effect sizes were around zero
or even on average somewhat negative.
So apparently
um there are differences between these
categories of studies. So we can use a
weighted analysis of variance to test
whether these differences that we see
here are statistically significant.
here the results. So if we use uh the
overall Q or the total Q statistic so to
test whether in general there is
homogeneity we see that this null
hypothesis is rejected.
So we have a Q statistic equal to 35.83
with 18 degrees of freedom. This gives
us a p value that is smaller than 0.05
even smaller than 0.01. So we can reject
the null hypothesis that all population
effect sizes are the same.
The second test, the Q between test
tests whether there are differences
between categories.
Again you can see that we obtain a very
small p value. So again we reject the
null hypothesis and we conclude yes
there are differences between categories
of studies.
And then the third test using the Q
within statistic
does not give a small p value. On the
contrary, the p value is relatively
large. It's equal to 42. So we do not
reject the null hypothesis. The null
hypothesis stating that all population
effect sizes within categories are the
same.
So we conclude
yes there are differences between
population effect sizes but these
differences can be explained completely
by the number of weeks of prior contact.
If we take into account that categorical
variable there is no heterogenity
anymore. So the Q within test shows that
the variation we still see within
categories can be explained completely
by random variation. So by sampling
variance
maybe you can have a look at the Excel
sheet that is on to called routenbush
example. In this Excel sheet I did all
these calculations. So I used uh fixed
effects model
to estimate and to test uh the theta so
the common population effect size. I
also used random effects model to test
and to estimate the mean population
effect size.
I also used a Q
uh statistic
and I also performed a weighted analysis
of variance. So the calculations that
were done to obtain Q total, Q between
and Q within are shown in that Excel
sheet. So I recommend you to have a look
at this Excel sheet and to try to
understand how these results were
obtained.
A note um simulation studies have shown
that maybe the Q statistic is not the
best statistic to use. The Hartung test
um brings better under control the type
one erate.
Another approach to take into account
differences between studies is by using
not a weighted analysis of variance but
a weighted regression analysis.
So the idea now is the observed effect
size in study J is equal to the
population effect size in study J plus a
residual due to sampling variance. But
the the population effect sizes of the
studies now are described using a
regression equation.
So it's equal to the population effect
size in study J is equal to a constant
an intercept plus a regression weight
times um yeah the value
on a specific stat characteristic for
this study and so on.
Note that in this regression equation
there is no residual. So we assume that
based on this regression equation we can
perfectly describe what the population
effect size is in a specific study. So
there is no random variation. It's
completely fixed. is completely the
population effect size is completely
determined by the characteristics of the
study. So therefore we still talk about
the fixed effects model but it's a fixed
effects model including
uh moderator variables in regression
model. So it's called fixed effects
regression model.
Note that this is not an ordinary
regression analysis. It's a weighted
regression analysis. Again, we are going
to give um or we are going to use the
precision as weights
and like in an ordinary regression
analysis. Um you get the estimates of uh
the regression weights, you get
estimates of um the standard errors of
these uh estimates. And so the estimates
divided by the standard errors follow a
normal distribution or standard normal
distribution. So if um the estimates are
at least twice as large as a standard
error, we know that we can reject
another hypothesis at the 5%
significance level.
Mixed effects models.
So we have seen random effects models.
We also have seen how if there is
variation in population effect sizes,
how we can include moderators, how we
can include a categorical moderator and
perform an analysis of variance or how
we can include um a moderator in a
regression model.
But in both models that we have seen
there was no residual no residual U. So
which means that we assumed in that
analysis of variance that there may be
differences between categories of
studies but within categories population
effect sizes are the same.
We can also define a model where we say
well maybe there are specific population
effect size or mean effect sizes for
each category. But on top of that maybe
a population effect size of a study can
defer from the mean in the category to
which that population effect size
belongs.
So we can include an additional uh
residual u.
So here we combine effects the random
effects model and uh the fixed effects
model with a categorical moderator
variable.
Also the regression model can be
extended by including an additional
residual U
to say that
maybe we can based on the
characteristics of the study we can
predict the population effect size from
that study but maybe the population
effect size from that study still
differs from what we predicted. So
that's the meaning of that residual U.
And so in uh analysis in meta analysis
using these models we are going to
estimate
well in the first model we are going to
estimate the theta I so the mean effects
for the different categories but on top
of that we are going to estimate the
variance of the use. So the variance
between studies within categories
in a regression model we are going to
estimate the regression coefficients. So
the betas and
uh as well as the variance in the use.
So which is the
variance between population effect sizes
after taking into account um the effects
of the study characteristics
to illustrate the random effects model
with a moderator um using that uh
analysis of variance model.
So here we assume that we have multiple
categories. Here we have for instance
two categories. But within these
categories population effect sizes can
still vary and we assume that this
variation is according to a normal
distribution.
Of course on top of that variation
um so yeah we we have to we still have
the sampling variation. So now we have
three sources of variation. We have
variation between categories in the
population in the mean population effect
sizes. We have variation within
categories
um between population effect sizes. And
on top of that we have the sampling
variation the variation of observed
effect sizes around the population
effect sizes.
So because in this model we have a
combination of random variation and
fixed variation or variation that can be
predicted uh using our moderator
variables. We also call this mix of
random and and fixed effects. We call it
a mixed effects model.
Note that this model is the least
restrictive model. It's a more general
model. Um,
if you use this model and it turns out
that the variance of U is equal to zero,
then this model automatically simplifies
to a fixed effects model with a
moderator. Or suppose that the moderator
variable is not having an effect. In
that situation, the the mixed effects
model um reduces or simplifies to random
effects model
or if
there is no effect of the moderator. And
if there is also no random variation in
population effect sizes, then the mixed
effects model automatically simplifies
to the first model we started from. The
fixed effects model without moderators.
So a final remark I want to make about
these analysis of variance models is
that very often it is assumed that
within categories the between study
variance so the variance of u is exactly
the same. So we are going to
estimate only one parameter the variance
of u or the to squared.
But some software
um packages also allow to assume that
possibly the variance of u depends on
the category.
In that situation of course you estimate
much more variance components.
For instance, in the software Refman or
in um this is done uh by default in the
software CMA, you have the choice.
A simulation study showed that if in
reality
all variances between population effect
sizes are the same for all categories,
then it's a better idea to uh yeah to
ask only or to use only one estimate of
this common uh between study variance.
So it's a good idea to use a pulled
estimate over categories.
If not, it's better to obtain or to ask
um uh for yeah for a separate uh
variance estimates one for each category
otherwise you will get flawed results.
So to summarize this session we have
seen six types of models. We started
from a fixed effects model without
moderator. Then we looked at random
effects model without moderators. We
said well if there is random variation
maybe it's a good idea to include a
moderator and we have seen um how we can
extend the fixed effects model as well
as the random effects model by including
a a categorical moderator. So resulting
in analysis of variance models or
including continuous moderators
resulting in fixed effects or random
effects regression models.