Thank you very much for the
introduction. Also, thank you for
inviting me. Um, it's a really exciting
conference. I'm sorry that I could not
attend yesterday and before yesterday. I
had to examine my poor students
yesterday. So, I can only attend today.
So I'm going to talk about the use of
multi-level models for performing meta
analysis.
And so my talk will consist of several
parts. First I will introduce uh
multi-level analysis. Afterwards I will
talk about how you can consider meta
analysis as a specific case of
multi-level analysis. Afterwards I will
talk about some opportunities um when
you use multi the multi-level modeling
framework for analyzing pro data over
studies or for analyzing uh effect
sizes.
Afterwards, I will say something about
when and how multi-level models are used
for performing meta analysis. And
finally, I want to give some ideas, some
reflections on how you can present the
results of multi-level meta analysis. So
first short introduction in multi-level
analysis and I will use an example
uh data collected in Flanders in Flemish
part of Belgium uh longitudinal study in
which uh more than 6,000 students were
measured
uh five measurement occasions during
their secondary education 6,000 more
than 6,000 students coming from 57
schools and so here for instance you can
see part of the data so on the xaxis You
can see the performance of the students
on an exam of mathematics in the
beginning of of secondary education. On
the y-axis you can see the performance
of the students on the mathematics exam
at the end of secondary at the end of
the second year of secondary education.
And of course you can see a positive
linear relationship that can be
described using an accretion equation
aggression equation that can also be
used to make predictions.
But there is a problem with this kind of
analysis in this kind of data sets. The
problem is that here students are nested
within schools. So you have several
students coming from the same school and
this can make that residuals are not
independent. Whereas this is an
assumption in ordinary regression
analysis. What does it mean? Well,
suppose there is a school that is
performing very good. So in the sense
that that teaching is very good and this
makes that uh students are performing
better than you would expect at the end
of the second year then you would expect
based on their score uh in the beginning
of secondary education or there may be a
school that is not doing such a good job
and then you can see that that the
scores of these students are lower than
you would expect. So you can see now
that the residuals are not independent.
If a new student is saying well I'm from
school too you can already expect that
for this student you also will have a
positive residual. So in other words
positive residuals of the students of
that school too will give information on
the residual uh of that new student. So
residuals are not independent.
Why is this a problem? Well, if
residuals or if students are nested
within schools and if there are
differences between schools, then this
means that there is some overlap of
information.
Um
there is well students are to a certain
extent copies of other students from the
same school. So there's overlap in
information and if we do not take this
into account then we are overestimating
the total amount of information we have.
And from a statistical point of view,
this is reflected in two small standard
errors. And if we use these standard
errors to perform statistical
significance tests, this will make that
the type one error rate is not under
control that we make too many type one
errors.
So if another hypothesis is correct, we
will too easily reject this null
hypothesis. What can be the solution?
Well, we could do separate regression
analysis for each school. But remember
in this data set we had 57 schools. So
this would mean that we have to do 57
separate meta analys um regression
analysis.
This could be a solution as you see in
this graph because now the residuals are
independent for each school. Now you
have positive residuals as well as
negative residuals. So residuals do not
give information anymore on the residual
of a new student. But this is not yeah
here you can see the separate regression
equations for each of the uh capital J
schools but this is not a very efficient
way. We have to do 57 analysis and maybe
for some schools we only have data from
a few students which means that yeah
parameter estimates will be not very
reliable.
Also in this way we cannot study to what
extent there are differences between
schools.
An alternative is that we use school
dummy variables in our regression
analysis. Then we can do one regression
analysis but you will have a lot of
coefficients. So here for instance we
have a dummy variable for school two
dummy variable for school three and
until school 57. So this would mean that
we have instead of one intercept we have
57 coefficients and instead of one uh
regression weight for our x variable we
will again have 57 uh coefficients. So
we have two times 57 regression
coefficients which is of course not very
efficient. How can we solve this? Well a
multi-level analysis can be a solution.
So the idea is well we start from an
equation the equation that I showed
before but now I added an index J
referring to the score
also the intercept and regression weight
of X gets an index J which means these
coefficients can vary over schools and
this variation is described with
additional equations equations. So the
first equation is describing the
variation within schools. These
equations are describing the variation
over schools. So what does it mean? So
the weight regression weight of X
depends on the school. And here we say
when it is equal to an overall slope
plus random residual residual that is
typical to the school. And so what is
nice about multi-level models is that we
do not have to estimate all these betas.
We do not have to estimate regression
coefficients for each school separately.
We simply estimate the mean intercept,
the mean slope as well as the variances
and the coariance.
I did this analysis for the example. You
get very similar
um uh regression coefficients here. But
now this analysis takes into account um
when testing these parameters that
students are nested within schools. So
standardize will be larger. You can also
uh you get also information about the
variation between schools in the
intercept and in the slope also
coariation. So positive coariation means
that if for a specific school the
intercept is higher you would also
expect that for that school the slope is
higher.
Afterwards if you want you can also
estimate the individual betas. And so
based on these estimates I I compose
this graph. So for each school you can
see a blue regression line and the red
line refers to the mean intercept and
the mean slope over all schools. Of
course if there is variation between
schools in intercept and in slope it can
be interesting
um to try to explain why there is
variation. So maybe we can include
characteristics school characteristics
in these equations at the second level.
For instance, in the example, I included
a dummy variable indicating whether this
school is a private school rather than a
public school. And these are the
results. So for public schools, the
intercept is 13.73.
For private schools, the intercept is
1.12
points lower. Yeah. So 13.73
minus 1.12.
The slope for private schools is
slightly higher than for public schools.
Okay, this is illustrated in this graph.
So we have an interaction effect. This
term in fact is an interaction term.
It's cross level interaction between um
yeah the mathematics zero and the type
of school.
So in this example we had a two-level
structure. So we have students nested
within schools. But of course this
structure it can also be recognized if
we have repeated measures. If we have
repeated measures
um then again we have two levels and at
both at both levels there can be
variation. So we have at the second
level subjects and within subjects we
have repeated measurements can be
variation between measurements within
subjects can be variation between
subjects and we can try to explain this
variation by including characteristics.
It can be more complicated for instance
well in the data set that I discussed uh
some analysis were done using four level
models. So we have schools but in some
of the schools more than one class was
uh was studied within classes you have
multiple students and students were
repeatedly measured. So we have a
fourlevel structure.
Um okay how does it look like such a
this is a four a three-level model. So
compared to the two-level model we have
an additional index K and so the
coefficients at the first level can vary
randomly
over the second level units possibly we
can uh we can explain part of the
variance by including characteristics
um and then these coefficients in turn
can vary over third level units.
So to summarize why would we use
multi-level models? First reason is a
statistical reason. We take into account
the nesting of units in higher level
units and so this makes sure that type
one rate will not be exceeded. But there
is also a conceptual reason of course in
this kind of data sets. It's interesting
to study to what extent are there
differences between schools or between
classes and why where do these
differences come from? Can we explain
these differences by including school or
class characteristics?
This was my short introduction in
multi-level analysis. Now meta analysis
as a specific situation or specific
um instance of a multi-level analysis.
So in our example we had two levels. We
had students nested within schools. In
fact in meta analysis we have a very
similar structure. We have
we have multiple studies and within
studies we typically have multiple
participants and there can be variation
between participants from the same study
but there can also be variation between
studies and it's interesting to study
why there is variation. We can include
stud characteristics. We can include
participant characteristics to try to
explain this variation at the two
levels.
How does this multilevel look
multi-level model look like? Well,
suppose you have a set of studies and in
each study you have control group and an
experimental group. Well, you could use
this model, this equation to describe
the variation within the study. So, it's
a simple model. Our dependent variable
is regressed on a treatment dummy
variable to indicate whether this person
is part of of the treatment group rather
than the control group. And so how do we
have to interpret this? Well, so the
beta zero intercept is the expected
value for somebody from the control
group. Yeah. So it's the expected value
or the the population mean of the
control condition in that study.
The effect of treatment is
what is added to this expected value if
somebody belongs to the treatment group
rather than to the control group. And so
this coefficient refers to the mean
difference
um the population mean difference
between these two conditions. So you see
it's it's a measure of effect the effect
of the treatment. So the effect of the
treatment is expressed by this
coefficient beta one and the variation
well it's possible that the intercept as
well as the effect the treatment effect
can vary over studies and this variation
can be described using additional
equations. So the intercept is equal to
a mean plus random deviation random
effect that is typical to that study.
Same for a treatment effect. So the mean
here you have the mean treatment effect
or the overall treatment effect and this
is a random residual specific to that
study.
Of course it's also interesting to study
the between study heterogeneity in
treatment effects.
This is expressed using this parameter.
So the variance between studies in the
treatment effect. So you can recognize
the parameters that we typically
estimate in a meta analysis.
To illustrate this, I simulated a small
data set using this population model. So
um
the mean intercept. So the overall
expected value in control condition is
equal to one. The overall treatment
effect is equal to one. But there is
some variation between studies in both
coefficients and at the first level
within studies uh you have residual
variation of one. I simulated
data from 30 studies with each two
groups of 30 units. I analyzed the data
using the level analysis and so here are
the parameter estimates. You can see
that well these parameters are quite
close to the population values. Um but
of course if I I would have thrown
another sample would have simulated
another data set these values would have
been slightly different and and maybe
now this value is slightly smaller.
Maybe
by simulating another data set that
value would be larger than one.
Yeah.
Of course you could say well this is not
a typical meta analysis. In a typical
meta analysis, yeah, you you have data
from several studies
and in these different studies typically
outcome variable is not measured on
exactly the same scale. So we have to
standardize the data. Okay, one way of
standardizing the data is by dividing
the dependent variable by the standard
deviation within the study. In fact, an
estimate of this parameter is the pulled
standard deviation which is also used
when we used when we uh when we
calculate a standardized mean
difference.
So in fact the coefficient now it was a
mean difference now it is a standardized
mean difference that you recognize from
that analysis.
uh I I put here primes because yeah the
parameters of course change or can
change
but otherwise it remains the same model
you can again use multi-level uh
modeling software
um so let's look again at a simulated
data set so now parameter estimates or
the population parameters remain exactly
the same because already in the first uh
uh data set the variance within studies
was one so standard izing doesn't make a
difference here.
But now in the simulated data set, I
analyze the data after standardizing the
data within each study with an estimate
of the um of the the within study
residual um standard deviation.
And so you get uh similar results as the
ones I've used before
in a real meta analysis. Of course again
this is not a realistic situation
because in a real meta analysis we
typically do not have the data of each
individual participant. Yeah. So such an
ordinary multi-level analysis is not
possible. So rather
instead of having the data from each
individual participant we have data we
have summary statistics about the sample
of participants within each study. We
might have uh test statistics, means,
standard deviations and so on or effect
sizes.
Um and yeah, we can do we can use these
effect sizes to perform a met analysis.
Typically for common uh effect sizes, we
also know or we we the sampling variance
or we can obtain good estimates of the
sampling variance. So the sampling
variance or the variance at this first
level does not have to be estimated
anymore. Sorry.
So we only have to estimate uh the
variance at the study level. But
otherwise we can use the same framework.
Let's look at at the model I've showed
before. So remember that this parameter
is a standardized mean difference. So
what if we have effect sizes? Well, a
standardized mean difference that is
estimated um in a specific study in fact
is an estimate of this beta y prime. So
it's an estimate of the population
effect size. Of course it's possible
that the effect that the estimate is
slightly too high or too low. So there
is a residual and uh the residual we
assume that these residuals from a
normal distribution with a variance that
we do not have to estimate anymore. We
already know that frequency
at the second level. So here
this equation remains the same equation.
Yeah. So the population effect size is
equal to a mean effect size plus random
residual typical to that study.
Let's look at the results of the
simulated data set. So in a simulated
data set I calculated uh observed effect
sizes or standardized mean differences
for each of the individual studies and I
analyzed them using such a multi-level
model for effect sizes and look at the
values you get exactly the same values
for the mean effect as well as for the
variance between studies in the effect.
So this is just to show that effect
sizes in this situation are sufficient.
We have we do not need more information
than information we have with these
effect sizes.
Now, why would we use a multi-level
model for analyzing or meta analyzing
data? Well, first I'm going to talk
about the meta analysis of raw data. You
can say well typically we do not have
raw data but sometime sometimes we do.
And to illustrate this, I will uh
discuss a reanalysis of a meta analysis
that was done by Terry Shan. She did a
meta analysis on several single case
studies. Single case studies that
studied the effect of choice making or
yeah she she looked at studies that
investigated whether problem behavior of
students in classes can be reduced by
giving these students a choice in the
activities or in the order of the
activities. And so she found several
studies, single case studies and single
case studies are experimental studies in
which uh individual participants are
measured repeatedly over time under
different conditions. So here without
having the choice and with having the
choice
here are the data for one single
participant from one of the studies. And
so for instance well this is a typical
way in which uh the data are presented
in single case studies. So they are
typically presented visually graphically
and they're typically also analyzed
visually so without statistical
analysis. But the nice thing about this
tradition is that from these graphs we
can retrieve raw data and so we can use
multi-level models to analyze these data
or to meta analyze the data over several
studies.
Um so what do you see here? Well first
that person was measured during eight
sessions without having the choice. You
can see that the problem behavior
um is relatively large. So this is
percentage of intervals in which there
was problem behavior. In the second
phase there were sessions in which the
students could choose um the activities
or the order of activities and then you
can see that the problem behavior was
reduced. It's much lower. Then in the
third phase again they did not have the
choice again problem behavior is larger.
Then in the fourth phase again there was
no choice or they could choose again and
so you can see that the problem behavior
was reduced again. So looking at this
graph you can see that at least for this
participant there seems to be an effect
of um giving choice
but we had uh data uh or Gary Shogun
collected data from several studies and
in some of these studies two three four
cases or participants were studied. So
we had a lot of these time series graphs
and so we have analyzed this data using
this model. So at the first level we say
well the score is equal to uh an
expected score
in the baseline phase. So without having
the choice but something is added and
here something negatively is added if uh
people are getting the choice. So
problem behavior here is reduced. So
beta one is the size of the effect for
this participant
um of having the choice
in the data set. uh we had 13 single
case studies in total data from 30
cases. So we used the tree level model
to study variation
between yeah measurement occasions
within cases and of course we took into
account whether at that moment they had
a choice or not. There can be variation
between cases. can be variation between
studies and we can try to explain this
variation by including case and study
characteristics. So we use this model
three level model
here are the results. So on average the
intercept after standardizing the data
for each study separately or for each
case separately. So on average the
um yeah the amount of problem behavior
in the control condition was 3
But you can see that the amount of
problem behavior was reduced. It was
yeah more than 50% reduced by uh giving
uh the students choice.
We can include characteristics of
studies, characteristics of cases as
moderator variables
um or as as predictors in the second and
the third level equations. So at the
second level we include included um the
gender of the person. At the third level
we included well there were two types of
studies. In some studies the students
could choose the activities. In other
studies the students could choose only
the order of activities. So we included
here uh a predictor a dummy variable
indicating whether they could choose the
order rather than the activities
themselves.
And so yeah here are the results. So if
you are talking about a female and if
they could choose the activities
themselves then the reduction of problem
behavior was minus 2.86
but if it was a male then the reduction
was somewhat smaller. If they only could
choose the order then the reduction was
even smaller. Okay so that's the meaning
of these coefficients.
What is nice about the use of
multi-level models is that multi-level
models are very flexible. So you can
extend this simple model in several
ways. For instance, you can include or
you can model autocorrelation. You can
model heterogeneity. So you do not have
to assume that the variance within the
baseline faces for instance is the same
as the variance within uh treatment
phases. You can also include additional
coariantss at the first level. For
instance, if you have two treatments,
you can use two dummy variables for two
treatments.
You can if you have count data, you can
uh use generalized multi-level model
rather than an ordinary multi-level
model. You can also include linear and
non nonlinear trends over time at the
first level and so on. So a lot of
extensions are possible. So for instance
here yeah this is a model that can be
used to model a time trend in the
baseline phase,
a time trend in the treatment phase and
and yeah in this model we have two
effect sizes. In fact, beta 2 here
refers to the immediate effect whereas
beta 3 refers to the interaction effect.
So the effect of the treatment on the
slope over time.
So you can see it's yeah very flexible
model. What about the multi-level meta
analysis of effect sizes? So this is a
typical structure for each this is the
structure that is assumed when using
traditional meta analytic techniques. So
we assume that for each study we have
one sample of participants and so for
each sample we only have one effect
size. So theta here refers to the
population effect size t to an observed
effect size and so these observed effect
sizes can be assumed independent but
sometimes well there can be various
reasons why effect sizes might be
dependent. For instance it's possible
that there that there are dependencies
over studies.
For instance, maybe some studies were
done in Belgium, some in Germany, some
in the United States and so on. Suppose
that that these are studies done in
education, but the educational system is
is completely different in the United
States compared to Germany. So, you can
expect that the results of studies done
within the United States are more
similar than uh results of studies done
in Germany. So again there is overlap in
information and it's important to take
that overlap into account otherwise your
type one error rate will be too high. So
we could use a three-level model. We can
extend the two-level model that I showed
before by including an additional higher
level model.
It's also possible that you have
dependencies within studies. So for
instance sometimes you you have studies
and within studies several experiments
are done
and so again it's it can be interesting
to study to what extent there are
differences between studies but also to
study to what extent there are
differences within studies between these
sub studies or experiments within
studies.
And in the next step we can try to
explain this variation by including
study characteristics or by including
characteristics of these sub studies.
For instance, what sub population was
studied in this sub study or what
variation of treatment was evaluated and
so on. This is a model we again we can
use a tree level model. So we have at
the first level we have our sample
level. So the with the sampling variance
at the second level we have uh the level
of sub studies with variation between
possibly variation between sub studies
and at the third level we have the
studies. This is the model we used um
for a meta analysis on priming effect
studies and we found that in a lot of
studies several experiments were done.
Typically these experiments were
replicated in different groups but with
a slight variation in in the way uh the
treatment was operationalized.
Yeah.
And so by by calculating a simple
average within each study you would lose
that information. Yeah. Whereas when
using a tree level analysis, you still
keep that variation between substudies
within studies and you can try to
explain this variation by looking at uh
for instance the time that the prime was
offered. Does it make uh does it have an
influence on the size of the effect? So
in the first step we did random effects
model analysis at the tree level random
effects model. So we found that yeah at
the tree levels we had more or less um
the same amount of variation
and then we did moderator analysis and
we found that with only one moderator
variable one study characteristic and
one um moderator variable at the second
level. So one characteristic of the
experiments within studies we could
explain a large part of the variation
especially the variation at the third
level. So the variation between studies
you see that only a small part was left.
So you can you could call this a mixed
effects model because it includes uh
moderator variables but still accounts
for possible remaining unexplained
variance at the three levels.
It becomes somewhat more complicated in
very common situation where within a
study you have one sample but within
that sample multiple outcome variables
were measured.
And this is more complicated because
you have in a typical net analysis we
assume that we know the sampling
variance but here we do not only have
sampling variance we also have sampling
covariance. Suppose that you have two
kinds of uh of outcomes. you have
depression and anxiety that are two
variables that are strongly related.
Suppose that in one specific study uh
the effect on both variables is
evaluated. But if in a study by
coincidence that effect size for anxiety
is relatively low. Well, you would
expect for that study that also the
effect size for depression uh will be
high. So you can expect that there is
not only sampling variance but also
sampling co-variance.
Um well I guess most of you are familiar
with the the the formula for calculating
the sampling variance. This is a formula
for calculating the uh sampling
coariance for standardized mean
differences. And note that the sampling
coariance depends on row. Row is the
correlation between the outcome
variables. And this is this is yeah this
is a problem. We typically do not know
this correlation and very often this
correlation is not reported. So how can
we take that coariance into account in
our meta analysis? Well maybe one
solution is to use a tree level model
again with a structure I showed before.
So we have studies within studies now we
have multiple outcomes and for each
outcome we have a sample. In fact this
is not the correct structure here. I say
well we have different outcomes but for
each outcome we have one sample so we
ignore the sampling coariance if we use
this structure in our met analysis.
Yeah but maybe this coariance this
dependence is taken into account by
saying well yes these two outcomes
belong to the same study.
Okay, so that's that's the idea. This is
this is the model we use for instance in
met analysis on uh on 39 studies
reporting on 584 effect sizes. In each
of these studies, the effect was
evaluated of prevention programs uh for
child abuse and neglect.
So why do we have that many effect
sizes? This is because child abuse and
neglect is very hard to measure. you if
you ask to to parents how many times did
you beat your children this week of
course they will say zero so it's very
hard to measure and so there is yeah
right you can also not observe it if if
uh researchers would make observations
at home of course parents will not uh
abuse or neglect their children during
the observations so that's why in a lot
of studies researchers were very
creative in finding ways of getting an
idea of um yeah whether there is child
abuse or neglect. I saw in some studies
they looked at um yeah reports done by
teachers or by uh supporting services
but also sometimes they looked at the
number of visits to emergency rooms or
number of visits to a doctor or
sometimes they they some even in simply
looked at risk factors like the number
of friends of the family or the the
income of the family or things like
that. Yeah. And in In some studies we
only found one effect size but in one
study we found up to 51 effect sizes.
Yeah. So we had a lot of effect sizes.
We we did a three-level analysis and we
found well on average so we calculated
standardized mean differences. So on
average we found a relatively small
effect but it was clearly significant
between parenthesis. You have the
standard error. Um here you can see the
variances between studies between
outcomes within studies and this is the
median sampling variance. So in total if
you sum these three values you have the
total variance. So you can see that
about 11% of the variance. So this is
comparable to to what Mike uh showed. So
the values I squared at the third level
or at the second level. So about 11% of
the total variance is variance between
studies. About 33%
of the variance was variance between
outcomes within studies. And so of
course we we try to explain these var
variances by including characteristics
for instance the type of indicator
variable or that's a variable a
moderator variable at the second level
or for instance the prevention program
that was evaluated and that was a
characteristic of the study.
But is this a good idea? Because I said
it's not a it's not a correct model. we
ignore the sampling coariance and we
hope that it is accounted for by using
such a tree level model. So what we did
we we performed several simulation
studies for instance here using this
this multivariant model. So we simulated
data for two outcome variables that
possibly can covary within studies but
these two outcome variables possibly can
also covary at a second level over
studies. And so we used so we analyzed
or we we generated raw data but we
calculated effect sizes standardized
mean differences and we analyze them
using a tree level uh meta analytic
model.
So here are some results. So these are
the standard deviations for specific
conditions, standard deviations of the
mean effect estimate. And you see that
the standard deviation is going up if
there is more coariance
which is what you would expect. If there
is more coariance that then this means
that the outcome variables overlap more.
There is more overlap. So the estimates
are less precise. They vary much more.
Okay. So you can see that the standard
deviation of the estimates were going up
and you see that there is no difference
between using a three-level model or a
two-level model.
Yeah. In fact, we found that estimates
were almost exactly equal when using the
two models. But here we also looked at
the the median or the mean standard
error. And what you can see here if you
use a tree level model the standard
error is also going up together with the
sampling variance.
Note that the standard error of the
estimate is an estimate of the standard
deviation of the sampling distribution
of the mean effect. Yeah. So you would
expect or you hope that the standard
errors are very similar to the standard
deviations here. And this is the case
for a three-level model. for a two-level
model. You see the two-level model does
not take into account the sampling
coarience. So a traditional model using
a traditional model is not a good idea.
Uh the standard remains the same and as
a result you can see that the type one
error rate is not under control when
using a two-level model. But for a
three-level model it is nicely under
control. We test it here with a
significance level of 0.05. A type one
erate indeed for a three-level model is
0.05.
So the type one error rate it is under
control. Uh what is also nice is that we
now have an estimate of the variance
between studies and within studies. We
can also try to explain these two
variances. So I think it it's you can
solve interesting questions by using
such a tree level model. Of course the
drawback is that it's well it's not that
very well known. Also some software like
or CMA does not allow for doing tree
level analysis. We also make some
assumptions. For instance, we implicitly
assume that the correlation between each
pair of outcomes is the same or we
assume that the between study variance
is the same for each outcome. But we
also did additional simulation studies
varying these variances and and
correlations and we found that results
are fairly robust.
What are alternatives? But ignoring the
dependence is not a good idea. As we
have seen, type one rate is not under
control. An alternative is randomly
choosing one effect size for each study,
which was already mentioned this morning
by Mike
or um it's statistically correct because
in this way you only have one effect
size per study. So effect sizes are
independent. But you of course you lose
information. You do not use all effect
sizes and moreover you do not get an
insight in how many variation is there
within studies and can we explain this
variation
averaging effect sizes within the study
same problem. Um so you lose
information. Moreover, um
yeah, if you want to to use the sampling
variance as a in your meta analysis,
well, the sampling variance of that mean
depends also on the correlation between
the outcomes. So again, we have the same
problem. And what is typically done is
also sampling variance is averaged
within the study. But that's not a good
idea because the more outcomes or the
more effect sizes within a study you
combine, the more precise the result is.
Yeah. So you should take that into
account in your sampling variants. The
problem is how if you do not know what
the correlation is between
uh outcomes.
Um
it's also possible to perform separate
meta analysis for each kind of treatment
or indicator. But of course um
again for each of these separate meta
analysis you only use part of the data.
So it's not a very efficient way.
Moreover, think about that that example
that I gave of child abuse. In one of
the studies you had 51 outcome
variables. So are you going to do 51
meta analysis?
So this is not realistic.
Performing a multivariat meta analysis
that's statistically okay. But again you
have some problems often if you want to
do a multivariate meta analysis
typically you you are also going to use
an estimate of the correlation between
outcomes which is typically not reported
and it's only feasible if you have a
limited set of outcome variables. Again
think back of that example of child
outcomes. If you have 51 variables in
one study,
you cannot expect that that for each
pair of outcomes, you have a good
estimate of the correlation between
these outcomes. Another alternative is
robust variance estimation.
So in fact in in this procedure you are
estimating a two-level model. So a
misspecified model in fact but by using
robust techniques you make sure that the
center is still okay. And indeed it is
it it has been demonstrated well
mathematically but also via simulation
that it gives correct standard that the
results are fine. Um I think also an
advantage of this approach is that you
can use standard two-level model which
is much better known by a lot of people.
So you will not have such a hard job to
explain why you are using three levels.
But I think an disadvantage is that you
do not get separate estimates of the
variance between studies and variance
within studies.
Of course, it's possible related to your
remark this morning. It's possible to
extend this even more to to additional
levels. It's possible to do a four or
five level analysis for instance. So
here for instance, you have a level of
an additional upper level. have the
studies and within studies you have a
level of substies in principle that's
possible but it's not very common
another kind of model um that was
described by by Ben Fernandez Castellia
one of the PhD students in our group is
a crossclassified model so here we say
well we illustrated is also using a data
set on on the loneliness um loneliness
outcome from variables. Um but we had we
assumed that we can have variance
between studies in the size of the
effect. But there can be also uh
variance between the instruments that
can be used
and this model is more complicated or
the structure is more complicated in the
sense that it is a non- hierarchal
structure. So instruments are not nested
within studies. So the same instrument
can be used in several studies at the
same time. studies are not nested within
instruments.
So the same study can use multiple
instruments like like this study. Yeah.
So we have a cross classification. A
population effect size is a population
effect size for this study when this
study uses this instrument. So there are
two effects, two random effects and
again we can include characteristics of
the instruments or characteristics of
the studies.
Very shortly something about the use of
multi-level meta analysis. When is it
used? Well, I did a very quick search in
the web of of science using these uh
keywords in the topics. I found 90
studies and what is remarkable is that
the first study that I found was from
whereas of course this is this is not a
complete overview and there are much
more studies but this gives already a
quick idea. So although the fact that um
that the use of melting levels for math
analysis was already described for
instance in the book of crowd bush and
brick uh in 1992 you see that it is
hardly it was hardly used until the
2010s
and and now you can see that it's
getting ex yeah much more popular. So
this is a nice finding an interesting
finding also number of citations it was
these kinds of studies were hardly cited
until 2010
in what domains were these studies
published well typically in psychology
behavioral sciences
which is also yeah interesting I don't
know how to explain this but it's a
finding we also looked at what applied
to multi level method analytic papers
referred to these three uh papers. So a
paper of of Mike and two papers of our
research group on three level or
multi-level meta analysis and we found
that 104 studies referred to these
papers and and per indeed used
multi-level models. Interesting
uh an interesting finding was that 99 of
these studies used a tree level model
with an intermediate level. So um with a
study level at the highest level and
then within study level at the second
level.
Two of the studies also use a tree level
model but with an additional level. So
for instance yeah um so we had the
sample level we had papers level and
then we had a studies level. So the same
studies was um I think it was also
mentioned by you this morning. So maybe
the same data set is used in different
papers. So this is this situation. So we
did not find here a study with countries
or research teams at the highest level.
There were only three levels that used
the fourle model with samples outcomes
studies countries. Sample outcomes
substudy studies or sample subtasks task
studies.
Again we found that that most of these
studies were in the psychological field.
Well, another um PhD student of our
group uh Lala Yangi did a meta did or
made a review of meta analysis of single
case studies and she found that between
1985 and 2015
178 meta meta analysis were done on
single case studies and 22 of these
studies used multi-level models. It was
striking that most of these almost all
of them were also published after 2011.
So you can see that the use of
multi-level models is becoming much more
popular.
A few more words if I have the time um
on yeah how to present the data or the
results. Well of course if you take into
account each individual effect size for
within studies you can have a lot of
effect sizes. So how are you going to
present this? Well, this is a way of
presenting this. So here here you have
one uh confidence interval for each
observed effect size, but it does not
give a clear overview. Moreover, you
cannot see what effect sizes are nested
in what studies. Okay, you could of
course use different colors, but if you
have a lot of studies, then the use of
colors or different markers also does
not give a good overview. So now we are
exploring ways of uh giving better
presentations of the data and this is a
possibility. Um
so Ben uh is uh is describing several
ways of presenting the data and and so
this is one way. So here we have a dot
for each study. effect. The dot
represents the mean effect for that
study and around that dot and yeah the
the size of the dot represents the
weight that is given to that study in
the three-level meta analysis and around
that dot you have two confidence
intervals. So the the bold confidence
interval refers to the precision of that
mean of that study.
Okay. Whereas the the lighter confidence
interval refers to the median or um yeah
refers to the confidence interval based
on the median sampling variance of an
individual effect size within that
study. So for instance here if you look
at study five you see that the black or
the the bold confidence interval is much
smaller than uh the light one. This is
because you had a lot of effect sizes.
So therefore the mean effect size is
much more precise than an individual
effect size. Whereas for study seven you
have one effect size within that study
and therefore the two confidence
intervals are exactly the same. So
that's one way of presenting.
What can also be interesting is to to
make a caterpillar plot. So of all
observed effect sizes individual effect
sizes. So here you can immediately see
that the majority of effect sizes are
positive. We have a lot are also zero
and some are negative.
It's also possible to make a caterpillar
plot over studies or yeah on the on the
mean effect sizes for the individual
studies. Uh again using these two kinds
of confidence intervals. So maybe this
is also a way of presenting the data.
But as I said, we are simply exploring
possibilities. So if you have better
suggestions, um I'm very curious to hear
them about funnel plots. Well, we can
use uh we can make a funnel plot for the
individual effect sizes, but we can
append this information by making a
funnel plot with the mean effect sizes
for these studies. So here each dot
refers to the mean effect size for one
study.
Maybe we can also add the number of
observed effect sizes within each study
as additional information.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you very much for a very
interesting uh talk. I was wondering I
like the pictures that you showed in the
end. So are they did you make a package
or R functions that we can use to
immediately create those pictures for
our own data?
>> It's the purpose yes to make our scripts
that can be used. uh we will make them
available using our website. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Thanks.
>> Thanks. Is very nice and I'm interested
in various combinations. For example,
there are um three level meta analysis
crossified with some for some of these
meta analysis maybe there are two
dependent variables or more. So do you
think it is possible to write some
general or easy code let's say our
packages for somebody to to analyze
because it looks like uh nowadays for
each problem we have to write a single
our code or to customize to analyze the
models. So I understand you're using SAS
right or other packages.
>> Yes I'm I'm using mostly SUS. Yeah.
>> And there it's easy to say what what the
random effects are.
>> Yeah. Um yeah so so what effects very
randomly over what units
>> yeah so I'm thinking whether it will be
some user friendly either SAS macro or
so that they can easily mix and match
one one of the issue I always have is
they have multiple effect sizes but they
have also dependence so there are should
be something similar to multi three
level meta analysis then uh you always
have struggle how to analyze it we all
know there are methods
But how to implement it is an issue.
>> Yes, that's a very good point. Yeah.
Yeah. We we are aware of that. Um we are
not really planning to to write an
additional package. Uh but we hope that
maybe in existing packages uh extensions
can be made to to model this kind of to
analyze data using these models.
But we certainly will also make
available the codes that we that we use
in in SAS or in uh in R. Yeah, thank
you.
Thanks. Nice presentation. Um did you
did you compare the results of the
cross-classified
multi-level meta analysis to standard
meta analysis and what are the
differences? So what is the benefit of
estimating these more complicated models
>> comparing the cross type?
>> Yeah. To the standard
>> to the standard meta analytics to the
standard. Yes.
>> We didn't need we did a simulation study
um yeah comparing the results of using
this model with a model in which you um
include only one type of random effect.
So the random effect for the studies or
the random effect of uh of the
instruments. We also compared it uh to
the analysis of the data using a tree
level model where you have um
or sorry no um
well a tree level model but with um
sorry I have to I have to think um we
had random effects within studies so it
was not exactly the same structure as I
showed here. So we had within studies we
had two kinds of random effects in our
simulation study and we also analyzed
the data using a tree level model in
which we looked at can we solve this by
taking a combination of these two cross
uh cross factors.
And so we found that the yeah that the
best solution or the best performance
was for the model that indeed took into
account the cross classification
structure. And so the results are as
expected um from other simulation
studies that the type one error rate was
not under control when using other
models.
Thank you for the great talk. Um I was
wondering can you say something about
the minimum number of sampling units
that is needed on level two and level
three because um sometimes we have meta
analysis with um a relatively low number
of studies or if you want to compare
countries you only have a low number of
countries
>> and um how important is it that you get
a certain minimum amount or if you're
under the minimum level is that a huge
problem?
>> Yeah, thank you. That's a that's of
course a very important question and uh
it is an issue. It is sometimes an
issue. Um so first of all for the fixed
effect estimates it does not matter. I
mean we we found in a lot of simulation
studies that fixed effects are well
estimated in even if you have small
numbers of units even if the model is
not correct like like in simulation
study I showed before whether you use a
two-level model or a three-level model
fixed effects estimates are almost
identical so that's not a problem but
for the standard errors
it's important that you use the correct
model and uh you should indeed have
enough units
at least at the highest level. So it's
not a problem if within studies for
instance you only have for some studies
one effect size for other studies two or
three effect sizes. That's fine. It's
especially important that at the highest
level you have enough units. And what is
enough? Well yeah in multi level
analysis in general sometimes uh as a
rule of thumb um they say you need at
least 20 or 30 units. Now we have done a
lot of simia studies and sometimes we
found that with much smaller numbers of
units you still get uh correct results
type one rate is still under control at
least if you do not have in uh moderator
variables in your model if you simply
estimate the mean effect. So sometimes
with 10 or even with five studies you
get reasonable good estimates of the
center and therefore correct uh coverage
proportions of confidence intervals and
so on. Of course if you want to to study
moderator effects and also if you want
to
uh to make inferences on the variances
then you need more um more studies. So
for instance in a simulation study of
Antonio Lopez Lopez from the University
of Morsia
um well he found that if you want to
include moderators at the third level so
at the study level you need at least 20
studies.
Um otherwise your type one rate is too
high. By the way, when you use the RVE
approach of the robust variance estimate
estimation procedure,
um, type one is still under control if
you use somewhat smaller numbers,
although the procedure is somewhat
conservative.
Okay.
Yeah. Maybe one additional remark. Of
course, there is also the issue of
power. So even if with five studies or
with 10 studies,
results might be okay.
the power will be very low.
>> I think you is very interesting. I think
there are a lot of um possible examples
where you could imagine this would be
useful. So I was thinking of um for
example also subgroup analysis and meta
analysis. So you have subgroups within
the studies and you um you mentioned
this right is you could say that within
the same sample they have um shared
variance. Um, so do you have some rule
of thumb maybe um like there's out there
for other types of analysis um when to
include a level in your analysis? Maybe
compare it and then or leave it out to
simplify it a little.
>> Yes,
that's a hard question but of course
again yeah a very interesting and
important question. So what I didn't
really mention is that implicitly we
assume when we use random effects we
assume that the units that we have are
random sample out of an infinite
population. So for instance I I give the
example of instruments. So yeah this was
also a remark we got from a reviewer.
Yeah there are not an infinite number of
instruments available to measure
loneliness.
So that's that that's that's one issue.
So do you want to say something about
individual instruments and then it's not
a good idea to use a level or or use
random effects for the instrument? Then
you can include the instrument in your
analysis as a moderator. You can use
dummy variables for the different
instruments and then you get an estimate
for each instrument. You can so so
that's that's one thing. Second thing is
yeah if if you want to generalize to
instruments in general
what are instruments in general can we
assume that there is such a population
of instruments and also we make the
assumption that these random effects are
normally distributed.
So why is it reasonable to assume that
these random effects are normally
distributed over instruments?
So does it mean you would say that to
purely think theoretical and not look at
how much variance is explained on that
level at all?
>> Okay. Uh yeah. So that's that's indeed
another issue. So yeah, sometimes it's
it's
from a theoretical point of view it can
be can be a good idea to use a four or
fifth level. Um but it's possible that
the variance at an additional level may
be very small. And so in that situation
it's not such a a problem if you ignore
that level. Yeah. The results will be
very similar. And that makes also that
it's easier to interpret your data that
it's easier to communicate about your
results. So it's always yeah trade-off.
How complicated do I want to make this
model? You also do not want to uh to
oversp specify your model. You also do
not want to to catch the pecularities,
the random errors in your data set. So
it's yeah finding a matter of finding a
balance of yeah estimating a reasonable
realistic model on one hand but not
making it too complex on the other hand.
Thank you.