After selecting the studies, we are
ready to extract the data needed for our
meta analysis.
This is the fourth step of the eight
steps of a meta analysis.
What data do we want to extract? Of
course, effect sizes. We want to say
something about the size of the effect.
So uh sometimes effect sizes are
immediately reported in the papers but
sometimes we have to calculate the
effect sizes and we now extract summary
data test statistics p values and so on
that can be used to calculate effect
sizes afterwards.
But we are not only interested in the
size of the effect but we are also
interested in the confidence about the
size of the effect. So we also want to
um extract data like standard errors,
the sample size, test statistics, p
values because these also give an idea
about um yeah how precise the size of
the effect was estimated.
Typically in a meta analysis, we do not
only estimate only a mean effect size,
but we also are interested in um yeah
study characteristics that are related
to the effect size. So it's also a good
idea to uh extract other information
about the studies like for instance
characteristics of participants the way
the dependent variable and treatment was
operationalized
uh some contextual elements the tests
that were used the design that was used
the quality of the study and so on. So
this is not only interesting for doing
moderator analysis afterwards, but it's
also a good idea in your systematic
review that you give a clear overview of
um how the studies that you found look
like.
This means that you will collect a lot
of data.
Um how are you going to collect these
data? Well, it can be a good idea or it
is a good idea to use a coding scheme.
Um, so for instance, one sheet, one
paper for each or one document for each
study or for part of the study. Um so if
you extract data it's always a good idea
to well you could for instance copy
exact um sentences from the original
paper but what is important is that you
also clearly mention um yeah the page
numbers so that afterwards if you want
to go back if you do not uh remember
very well what that meant or if you you
want to know more about the context in
which that sentence was given given you
can easily find back uh uh that part in
the text.
Note that it's it is better to code
somewhat too much than too little. I
mean if out after afterwards you you say
well maybe I also need information on
that characteristic and you did not code
that yet then it is much more work to uh
extract the data um or yeah it's much
more work if you have to look at all
individual studies again to look for
that uh variable. It's better to coat a
characteristic uh too much even if you
use if you will not use it afterwards
anymore than uh one too little. But of
course also pay attention um so if you
have a very long coding scheme. So if
you want to extract a lot of information
it can also very time consuming. So also
think about what information I will use
afterwards so that you do not code far
too much.
So here is an example of such a coding
uh form.
So uh
yeah so these are some study
characteristics and so in the blanks you
fill in that information for the study.
So afterwards, so when you uh filled in
these coding forms,
um it is probably a good idea that you
use uh a spreadsheet uh program like
Excel uh to bring together all these
data so that afterwards you can analyze
them in a statistical program or in a
program specifically for meta analysis.
So here for this study I used or we used
uh several uh sheets. So in the first
sheet you see in the first sheet we have
one line for each study.
And so in the first column in column A
you can see the study ID. So the first
study was study 10,01.
So in the second column you have the
publication year which was 2012. In the
second column you have the publication
type. I think one was published and two
was unpublished. And then in the fourth
column you have another uh
characteristic. So here you have an
overview of all studies that were found.
So probably another column is the
authors um and so on or the complete
reference.
In a second sheet, we have here
um again
the study ID
but now we also have an additional
column sample ID and you see that for
some studies like study 10,2
you have two samples.
So in that study two groups of persons
were studied.
The same is true for study uh 108.
So also there there were two samples.
So whereas the first sheet had one line
for each study, in this sheet we have
one line for each sample, for the
majority of the studies there was indeed
only one sample but for some studies
there were more than one sample. And
then in the following columns you have
some uh yeah uh characteristics of these
samples.
In a third sheet
you have the results results that will
be used afterwards to calculate effect
sizes or yes this was a study about uh
uh reliability coefficients.
What you see here in the last column are
the alphas, so the reliability
coefficients. But for some studies and
for some studies and for some samples
you had different skills that were given
to these samples like for instance in uh
in study 10,03.
So in sample one
there was the scale laca lart and laca l
pierce. So two different subs skills of
uh the laca scale
and so for each of these subscals you
have an alpha coefficient.
So in that way by using multiple sheets
um yeah it is possible to yeah to keep
the number of variables and the number
of rows limited. Of course, it's
important that you can link these
different sheets to each other. So, um,
make sure that in the tree sheets then
you have the same variable names like
for instance ID study and ID sample.
Also for the data extraction it's
important that you make sure that this
is done in a reliable way. So also here
you have to make sure that your coding
scheme is very clear. So again for
consistency but also for replicability
it's important that this uh scheme is
very clear and that you report on that
scheme as well or that you make it
somewhere available uh as supplementary
material uh linked to your paper for
instance. Also here the coders should be
trained. Also here it is a good idea uh
to let at least part of the coding done
by two independent coders and to report
on the reliability.