After performing your meta analysis,
it's important that you look critically
at the value of your analysis and that
you are very transparent about the
quality of the results.
In this screencast, we will look at
three aspects. First, the assessment and
correction of publication bias. Second,
checks of potential outliers and their
impact. And third, checks of the
assumptions that are made during the
analysis.
First, publication bias.
We have already discussed where
publication bias can come from. In many
fields, the probability that a finding
is reported and published is higher when
the finding is statistically
significant.
Therefore, one way to detect publication
bias is to compare the overall effect
size for published and unpublished
results. You could, for instance, do a
moderator analysis with the publication
status as a dummy moderator.
If the regression weights of this
moderator variable is statistically
significant, this is an indication that
there is publication bias. Possible
issue is is the statistical power
because it may be hard to find
sufficient unpublished studies to do
this moderator analysis.
An alternative approach is to make use
of plots.
A funnel plot is a scatter plot which on
the with on the x-axis the observed
effect size and on the y-axis the sample
size. You would expect a pattern like
this one. We have seen that observed
effect sizes vary around the true effect
size. But for large studies the sampling
variance is smaller and for than for
small studies. This is exactly why you
see what you see in this scatter plot at
the top. So for large studies the
observed effect sizes do not vary a lot.
Whereas at the bottom for small studies
there is much more variation.
In this way you get a pattern of an
inverse funnel. Hence the name funnel
plot. In this example the population
effect size is probably somewhere around
0.10.
But look at the funnel plot that I made
for the bush met analysis on the teacher
expectancy effect. You can see that the
pattern is not a symmetric triangle
anymore. In the left corner, there are
no dots. Maybe there were some small
studies that found a very negative
observed effect size, but a negative
effect size is not what we would expect
here because a negative effect size
would mean that teachers are giving
higher grades to the so-called weak
students.
It's therefore possible that
researchers, reviewers, or journal
editors were surprised by the negative
effect size and attributed this
unexpected result to coincidence because
of the small sample size and therefore
decided not to report or publish the
findings.
In the right corner, on the contrary,
you can see multiple dots. It is
possible that exactly because of the
small sample size in some studies
researchers obtained by coincidence a
very large observed effect size. Maybe
researchers and reviewers were
enthusiastic that they found such a
spectacular effect size that may even be
statistically significant despite a
small sample size and therefore reported
and published these study results.
Note that in this way publication bias
leads to a negative correlation between
the sample size and the observed effect
size. In general, the larger the
studies, the smaller on average the
observed effect size.
An alternative plot is a contour
enhanced funnel plot. Again on the
x-axis you have the observed effect size
and on the y-axis the standard error
with a smallest value on the top. First
look at the dots. You can see that the
pattern is not symmetric which is an
indication of publication bias. Now look
at the triangles. In contrast to an
ordinary funnel plot, this time the
middle of the triangle is not the
average effect size, but rather zero.
With different colors, the areas are
indicating what would lead to
statistically significant results. Here
the white area refers to observed effect
sizes that are statistically not
significant. The light gray area refers
to values that would give a p value
smaller than 0.05.
Dark gray smaller than 0.01. And outside
the dark gray area, P values smaller
than uh 0.001.
What you can see is that in this extreme
example, the data set includes only
observed effect sizes that were
statistically significant, mainly with P
values smaller than 0.01.
The asymmetry is clearly related to the
size of the p value.
A similar plot is a radial plot or a
gold braid plot which is illustrated
here for the round bush data on the
teacher expectancy effects. A scatter
plot is made with the effect size
divided by the standard error on the
yaxis and one over the standard error on
the x-axis. An unweighted regression
analysis is done with the intercept
constraint to zero. The slope now can be
interpreted as the overall effect which
is indicated on the arc with a
confidence interval.
If there is no publication bias, the
dots are supposed to be symmetrically
distributed around the regression line.
Here we see that on the left side so for
the smaller studies the dots are
typically above the regression line
which is an indication of publication
bias.
Note that in addition confidence
interval lines are drawn. It can be
expected that 95% of the Z values are
within these intervals. The plot
therefore can also be used to detect
outliers.
We have seen that publication bias may
lead to a negative association between
the observed effect sizes and sample
sizes. Therefore, another way to assess
publication bias and to test for
publication bias is to estimate and test
a measure of association between effect
sizes and the size of the study.
Measures that are often used are Kendall
tow or Spearmman's rank correlation.
Still another approach is to include the
standard error as a predictor in the
model. In other words, to study the
moderating effect of the standard error.
An important remark, however, is that a
negative correlation does not
necessarily mean that there is
publication bias. Of course, it's
possible that by coincidence you will
find the correlation between observed
effect sizes and sample sizes. But
measures and tests for association also
often ignore completely the between
study heterogeneity and therefore
ignores a source of variation or
uncertainty about the effect sizes
resulting in an inflated type one error
rate.
Moreover, it's possible that in small
studies the treatment is longer, more
intensive or more personalized exactly
because this is more feasible if the
number of participants is limited. And
this may be the reason for finding
larger effect sizes in smaller studies.
For instance, typically much larger
effect sizes are found in single case
experimental studies compared to group
comparison studies.
In some a negative correlation or an
asymmetric funnel plot may be an
indication of publication bias, but
definitely not a proof.
Note that for some effect sizes such as
a standardized mean difference G, the
sampling variance depends on the size of
the effect and hence you can expect a
correlation between the standard error
and the observed effect size even
without publication bias.
Hisan described the variance stabilizing
transformation of G which makes that the
sampling variance of the resulting
effect sizes does not depend on the size
of the effect sizes anymore. Using the
transformed effect sizes improves the
results of Edgar's regression test.
Similarly, transforming correlations to
Fisher Z values makes that the sampling
variance depends on the sample size
only, not on the size of the effect size
anymore.
There are also several approaches to
correct for publication bias. The first
approach is a trim and fill method.
Here we see another funnel plot. There
is some asymmetry which may be due to
publication bias.
On your right side, you see some
observed effect sizes that are
relatively large. Especially the
observed effect size of plus 4.5 is
striking.
On the left side, there seems to be a
gap
because without publication bias, we
would expect a symmetric funnel. In the
first step, we will drop some dots in
order to make the funnel symmetric. In
the trim and fill method, this is done
in an iterative way. If asymmetry is
found, the most extreme dot is removed
and the symmetry is tested again. This
continues until there is no significant
asymmetry anymore. This is the trimming
phase. At the end of this phase, the
overall effect size is estimated again,
an estimate that is supposed to be
unbiased.
In the second step, the filling phase,
the dots that were dropped are
reinserted again. But for each dot that
is reinserted at the right side, a dot
at the left side is added as well. A dot
that deviates to the same extent from
the new overall effect size estimate.
The idea is that the dots that are added
on the left side could have been the
results of studies that were not
reported or published because these
effects were unexpected and
statistically not significant.
Here you see the results. The black dots
are the dots that are added based on the
black diamond at the bottom of the plot.
You see that the overall effect size
estimate now is so much smaller than
before. Yet it still is statistically
significant.
But of course, adding effect sizes that
were in fact not found in the literature
can be tricky.
Therefore, the trim and fill method
should be used with care. For instance,
you can use it as a kind of sensitivity
analysis. You explore whether the trim
and fill method would change your
conclusions. If so, you have to warn the
reader that there may be an issue of
publication bias that would affect your
conclusion. But if not, it makes you
more confident that your conclusions are
credible.
A drawback of the trim and fill method,
however, is that it can lead to wrong
conclusions if there is heterogeneity.
Also aggressive regression can be used
to obtain a bias corrected estimate
because a standard error is used as a
predictor in the regression model. The
intercept can be interpreted as the
expected effect size if the standard
error is zero. So for infinitely large
studies. Therefore the intercept can be
considered as an estimate of the mean
effect size that is free of publication
bias. Another approach is the use of
selection models in which we account for
the process of selecting studies for
publication. The starting point is the
assumption that the the larger the p
value, the harder it is to publish the
results. Studies with large p values
therefore may be under represented in
the metalytic data set. In this
approach, we try to describe this
relationship. You can use a discrete
function for instance saying that there
is a given probability of publication
for a p value larger than10 a larger
probability for a p value between10 and
0.05
an even larger probability for a p value
between 0.05 and 0.01 and so on. But you
could also use a continuous version in
which the probability of publication is
increasing gradually with an increasing
uh p value
with a decreasing p value. The function
can be defined in advance or one can try
to derive the function using the data.
In a meta analysis, one tries to
compensate for the under representation
of studies with large p values by giving
larger weights to studies with larger p
values.
Although this is an interesting approach
to correct for publication bias, it's
rather complex and tech it's a rather
complex and technical approach.
Moreover, there is always the risk that
the weight function that links the
publication probability
and the p value is misspecified.
Moreover, especially if you want to
derive the weight function using your
data, you need a large number of
studies, say more than 100.
Still another approach is the puniform
approach. Here the underlying idea is
that if there is no publication bias and
you would test the null hypothesis that
the overall effect size is equal to the
real value, the p values would follow a
uniform distribution.
In the puniform approach, we will use
only the data of studies that found
significant results because we can
assume that for this set there was no
bias. All findings were published. We
then calculate for these studies the p
values that would be obtained when
testing that the overall effect size is
equal to our estimated overall effect
size.
If our overall effect size estimate
would be unbiased, we therefore can
expect that the p values are uniformly
distributed.
If the distribution of p values deviates
significantly from a uniform
distribution, this is therefore an
indication that there is publication
bias.
A bi corrected estimate for this overall
effect size is obtained by investigating
for which value the distribution of p
values is closest to a uniform
distribution.
Another potential issue is the
following. Sometimes we obtain effect
sizes that are that are far away from
other effect sizes and these outliers
can have an important impact on our met
analytic findings and therefore may give
a biased idea of what is typically
observed.
I have shown this forest plot before.
You see that the effect size that I have
highlighted is about 1.2 whereas most
effect sizes vary between zero and 0.5.
Such a large value can increase
substantially the mean effect size
estimate.
But here you note that this large effect
size also has a broad confidence
interval. So probably this effect size
comes from a small study. Because of the
small precision, the weight that is
given to this effect size in the meta
analysis is not very high. So maybe this
outlying value does not really have an
important impact on the results.
Let's look first how you can detect
outliers. The first way is visually like
we did in the forest plot in the
previous slide.
In the final funnel plot on this slide,
you can see that there are four studies
with somewhat outlying observed effect
sizes.
Study 8, study 56, and studies 47 and
48.
VBA and Chung proposed to look at the
studentized deleted residuals for the
study. You calculate the difference
between the observed effect size and the
estimated effect size for that study but
estimated in a meta analysis without
that study. Hence the minus i in
annotation.
This deviation is standardized by
dividing it by the corresponding
standard error.
If you look at all the standardized
deleted residuals, you see again that
studies 8, 47, 48, and 56 stand out.
You can also calculate how much the
estim the estimated effect sizes for all
case studies change when dropping study
I. You can calculate the cook's distance
to express the size of the change.
Again, the same studies pop up.
A third way to detect influential
outliers is to look at how much the
covariance matrix of the parameter
estimates changes. For a random effects
model without moderators, this matrix
includes only one value, the sampling
variance of the overall effect estimate.
To express the impact of dropping study
I, you can calculate the ratio of the
sampling variance of the mean effect
estimate without and with accounting for
study I. If the ratio is smaller than
one, this means that the sampling
variance is larger when study I is
included. In other words, that including
study I reduces the precision.
Again, you can see that this is the case
for the same four studies.
When there are outlying values in your
data set, it's important to reflect on
where they come from. One explanation is
that you made an error in the
calculation of the effect size. Another
explanation is that the data that were
reported are not correct. In one of our
meta analysis, we wrote to the research
research team of a paper to ask whether
they could check their data because the
effect size that we found for their
study was considerably larger than the
effect size we found for other papers.
And indeed, the authors replied that
they found an error in their
calculations. So after correcting the
error, the effect size for their study
was very much in line with those of
other studies.
In these cases, it's of course important
to correct the errors. If you really
have strong doubts about the correctness
of data, but correcting the data is not
possible, you can leave out the outlier.
Another explanation is that a study in
which an outlying effect size was
observed differs substantially from the
other studies. For instance, in a
population of participants or in the
study setup.
In this situation, it's probably a good
idea to leave out that paper or to
discuss that paper separately but not
include it in the meta analysis.
Another explanation can however be that
an extreme value was found by
coincidence. If effect sizes are indeed
normally distributed, it is to be
expected that from time to time you will
find an extreme value. Automatically
dropping effect sizes that are somewhat
larger or smaller therefore may give a
biased view on the average effect or
especially on the size of the between
study variance.
If you find outlying values and you are
sure that they were correctly calculated
and they come from studies that are
otherwise comparable to the other
studies, I suggest to do a sensitivity
analysis. The idea is that you look at
what these outlying values mean for the
conclusions of your meta analysis.
A first kind of sensitivity analysis is
to leave out one study at a time and
redo the meta analysis. If you would
have 100 effect sizes from 100 studies,
this would mean that you would do 100
meta analysis each combining 99 effect
sizes. If you would find that your
conclusions remain the same, for
instance, that there is a significant
positive effect, that would strengthen
your confidence in this conclusion. If
however the conclusions change, for
instance, if sometimes the mean effect
size would be significant, sometimes
not, you are less certain about your
conclusion. In that case, it's also
important to share your uncertainty with
a reader of your research report.
As an alternative sensitivity analysis,
you can leave out all outlying values at
the same time and compare the results
with the results of the analysis,
including all effect sizes.
Third, it is important to check whether
the assumptions you made in the analysis
make sense and to be transparent on
these checks.
First assumption that is made when using
a fixed effects model is that all
population effects sizes are exactly the
same. So that there is no heterogeneity.
When including a moderator the
assumption is somewhat relaxed.
Conditionally on the value of the
moderator there is no heterogeneity or
in other words the moderator explains
all potential heterogeneity.
Of course, you could do a homogeneity
test to test whether there is convincing
evidence of heterogeneity. But
unfortunately, this test is not without
problems. For instance, the power can be
low. Therefore, before using a fixed
effects model, it is vital that you
reflect on whether you can re really
expect that there is no heterogeneity.
Only when studies were set up in exactly
the same way or when you are sure that
study characteristics that may affect
the size of the effect are included in
your model, it makes sense to use a
fixed effects model. But because this
assumption is very often unlikely, it's
probably better to use a random effects
model by default.
In the random effects model, on the
contrary, you do not assume a common
population effect size, but rather you
assume a distribution of population
effect sizes. Techniques to estimate the
model parameters often assume that again
after correcting for potential moderator
variables, the population effect sizes
follow a normal distribution. To check
this, you could make use of a QQ plot.
Here a QQ plot for the effect sizes from
the teacher expectancy meta analysis of
Renbush. On the Y-axis you have the
standardized deviations of the observed
effect sizes from the mean effect size.
These are the deviations divided by
their standard error. On the X-axis you
have the standard normal distribution.
There were 19 studies. So 19 deviations.
For the smallest deviation, the first of
the 19 deviations, the theoretical
quantile quantile is calculated as the
ZV valueue from a standard normal
distribution for which the cumulative
density is equal to 1 minus.5 divided by
19.
Similarly, the theoretical quantile for
the 18th deviation is 1.41.
If the effect sizes are normally
distributed, you expect that the dots
are more or less on one straight line.
Fortunately, the results are quite
robust for violation of this normality
assumption. So unless the QQplot shows
an important deviation from a normal
distribution, you should you do not have
to worry too much. Later on we will see
how we can obtain robust standard errors
uh for constructing confidence intervals
or performing significance tests by
using RVE. In this approach we do not
make the assumption of normality. So it
can be a safer approach.
Further we assume that effect sizes are
statistically independent which means
that one effect size does not give
information on another effect size. The
assumption can be violated when you have
multiple effect sizes from one study.
The effect sizes from the same study are
probably more alike in effect sizes from
different studies because the effect
sizes from one study may be based on the
same sample or at least on very similar
samples.
Similarly, also the dependent and the
independent variables may be measured in
a more similar way for the different
effect sizes from the same study.
If there is dependency, it is good to
account for this dependency. For
instance, by using multi-level models
which will be discussed in a later
screencast.
We also assume that the between study
variance is the same for all studies.
Also, in a categorical moderator
analysis, we assume typically that the
between study variance is the same for
all categories. This assumption may be
violated. For instance, suppose you make
a distinction between studies done in
the US and studies done in the rest of
the world. It's quite possible that the
variation between studies in the US is
smaller than the variation between
studies in the rest of the world. In
some software packages such as in such
as in the comprehensive meta analysis
software, you can choose whether you
assume a common between study variance
in all categories or whether you want to
estimate a between study variance
parameter for each category separately.
Of course, in the last case, you need
sufficient studies in each category to
be able to get a good estimate of the
category specific variance.
In this way we arrive to another
assumption.
The assumption that we have sufficient
studies. This is not a problem when
using a fixed effects model. In a fixed
effects model you can easily combine the
results of two studies. But when using
random effects model we are estimating
the between study variance and this
variance is also used to weight um
effect sizes and to obtain standard
errors. And it is clear that with only
two studies you cannot obtain a good
estimate of the between study variance.
Ideally you have at least about 20
studies.
You could also do meta analysis with for
instance only 10 studies but then you
have to be very prudent with the
results. And of course if you want to do
moderator analysis 10 studies is likely
a too small number of studies.
Another assumption is that the observed
effect sizes are unbiased estimates of
the population effect sizes. That's the
reason why we apply HCH's correction
factor to the standardized mean
difference.
Otherwise, the observed effect sizes are
somewhat biased for smaller studies.
We also assume that the sampling
distribution of our observed effect
sizes is a normal distribution. We have
seen that the sampling distribution of
the correlation can be skewed especially
for small sample sizes and when the
population correlation is close to
minus1 or + one that also that is also
the reason why we typically use fisher
transformations. This transformation
makes the sampling distribution more
symmetric and normal.
Similarly, the odds ratio has a skew
distribution, but the loss ratio has an
approximately normal sampling
distribution.
Next, in a systematic review, we
typically aim to find all existing
studies that are relevant for our
research interest. Of course, we
probably will not be able to retrieve
all relevant studies, but at least we
make the assumption that our sample of
studies is a random sample from all
existing studies. Here you can see a
link with publication bias. If you
include published studies only, then
your sample of studies is not a random
sample from the population of existing
studies. This is not a problem in say
but when your sample of studies
systematically differs from the
population of ex of all existing studies
there is a risk that the effect sizes
you found are also not representative
for the effect sizes that were observed.
In other words, there is a risk of bias.
Finally, if you do a meta regression
analysis, you assume that the
association between the effect size and
the moderator is linear.
It's a good idea to make a regression
plot to check this assumption visually.
Of course, also here a sufficiently
large number of effect sizes is needed
in order to make a distinction between
different kinds of association.