In this video, we will look at use of
RVE or robust variance estimation for
the meta analysis of dependent effect
sizes.
A short recap, we have seen that a
traditional fixed effect model or a
random effects model assume that effect
sizes are independent.
This is a reasonable assumption when
studies are done by separate groups and
each study reports only one effect size.
Yet very often there are different
sources of dependence. You can have
dependence across studies. For instance,
when multiple studies are done by the
same research group.
In that case, effect sizes from the same
research group are likely more similar
than effect sizes from different
research groups because a research group
may have operationalized the variables
in a very specific way. Sampled study
group participants from a similar
population and so on.
Another situation is where studies are
reporting more than one effect size. for
instance, when they evaluate the effect
at multiple time points for multiple
outcome variables or when some
variations of treatments are evaluated.
In these scenarios, multi-level models
may be helpful.
An ordinary random effects model can be
considered as a two-level model with
systematic variation between studies and
sampling variance within studies.
To account for dependencies, one could
define additional levels, upper or
intermediate levels.
For instance, to account for the
similarity of studies from the same
country, we could define an upper
country level. Whereas to account for
the similarity of results from multiple
substudies, we define an intermediate
substudy level. In other words, instead
of assuming that observed effect sizes
vary because of sampling variance and
systematic between study variance alone,
we now say that on top of the sampling
variance, there can be multiple kinds of
systematic variance. For instance,
variance between countries,
variance between studies from the same
country,
variance between substudies from the
same study. To that end, we use a
metalytic model with a random country
effect, random study effect, and a
random substy.
Other more complex models are possible
as well. For instance, think about a
scenario where studies may report
multiple effect sizes and when the same
instrument may be used in multiple
studies. In this situation, instruments
are not nested within studies because
the same instrument is used in multiple
studies.
But the other way around, studies are
also not nested within instruments
because the same study may use multiple
instruments.
Again we can use random effects to model
the effect of the studies and the effect
of instruments. But now these random
effects are not nested or hierarchally
structured but rather cross-classified.
Another common situation is where in one
study multiple effect sizes are
calculated on the same sample of
participants.
You remember that the sampling variance
is typically estimated before doing a
map analysis and therefore is considered
as known during the meta analysis.
But in a situation where you have
multiple effect sizes calculated for the
same sample, there's not only sampling
variance but also sampling co-variance.
For instance, for two standardized mean
differences calculated in the same study
for two different outcomes but based on
the same sample, we have a co-variance
that can be calculated with this
formula.
You see the parameter row in this
formula which refers to the correlation
between the two outcome variables.
A positive correlation between the
outcomes will also result in a positive
correlation between the effect sizes. So
if two outcomes correlate positively and
by coincidence you have thrown a sample
for which the standardized mean
difference for one outcome is relatively
high. You can expect that the other
effect size will be relatively high as
well.
After calculating the sampling variance
and co-variance, you can then perform a
multivariant meta analysis treating the
sampling variance and coariance as
known.
An issue, however, is that the row is
unknown
and that often studies do not report an
estimate of this correlation.
Therefore, we could use a reasonable
guess for row and then try out other
values to investigate whether the
conclusions of our meta analysis are
sensitive to the value chosen.
As an alternative, we can use the
following trick. We can treat the effect
sizes from the same sample within a
study as if they are based on separate
samples but for different substies
within that study.
The advantage is that we do not need to
estimate the sampling coariance.
The association between effect sizes
from the same study is accounted for by
modeling the effect sizes as nested
within studies.
In some simulation studies, we have
shown that this trick seems to work
relatively well.
The multi-level modeling framework is a
very flexible and helpful framework.
Yet, a drawback is that we make several
assumptions that may be wrong.
First assumption is that the model is
correctly specified.
For instance, we have to define what the
different levels are. Can use a threele
model, but maybe sometimes a four or
five level model is more appropriate.
Note that when we use a trick of
considering effect sizes coming from the
same sample as effect sizes coming from
separate samples from the same study,
our model is not correctly specified.
Related to this, we need a sufficient
number of units to be able to estimate
the variance of an additional random
effect. For instance, if you would have
data from two countries
only from two countries, you cannot
estimate the between country variance
and hence it does not make sense to
include a random country effect.
Or if you would have data from 10
studies coming from 12 countries in
total, it is hard to disentangle the
country effect and the study effect. So
again it does not make sense to include
that country level
and suppose you have 10 studies from the
US and 10 other studies each coming from
another country.
In that situation it is possible to
estimate the variance between countries
and the variance between studies within
countries. But here the between study
estimate would be based only on the
variation between studies within the US
whereas in other countries this variance
may be substantially different.
Another assumption is that at each level
we make the assumption that residuals or
random effects are independent and
normally distributed.
assumptions that may also be violated.
Another issue is that the sampling
variance may be incorrectly estimated.
For instance, the sampling variance of a
standardized difference between the mean
pre-est score versus the mean post- test
score depends on the correlation between
the pre and post test post- test scores.
Unfortunately, often studies that use
such a design do not report that
correlation and hence we have to make a
guess of that correlation in order to
estimate the sampling variance.
Often a correlation of 50 is used but
this
may be wrong and therefore the sampling
variance estimate of the observed effect
size may be wrong.
As a consequence, the weights that are
used may not be perfectly inverse
variance weights. Moreover, standard
errors obtained for the model parameters
may be wrong and hence confidence
intervals and hypothesis tests that make
use of these standard errors may be
invalid.
as a safety net, we could make use of
robust variance estimation or RVE.
The idea is that instead of estimating
standard errors as a function of the
random variances in our model, you base
the standard errors of the observed
variance.
You base the standard errors on the
observed variance in effect sizes.
In that way, the standard errors do not
depend anymore on the model itself,
making them robust for misspecification
of the model.
Because the standard errors are not
model based based on the data, they are
also called empirical standard errors.
They're also called Uberwide standard
errors and the estimation is also called
cluster robust variance estimation
within our situation. The studies in
which there may be multiple effect sizes
being the clusters.
More specifically, in the case of meta
analysis, we define observed residuals
as the deviation of the I observed
effect size T in study J from the
overall effect size data.
Instead of assuming that the variance in
observed effect sizes is the sum of the
systematic variance between studies,
systematic variance between sub studies
and the sampling variance. We now
estimate the variance and coariances.
The estimated variance of the observed
effect sizes is the observed variance in
the residuals.
Co-variance between effect sizes from
the same study is estimated by
calculating the coariance in the
residuals from the same study.
The coariance between effects from
different studies is assumed to be zero.
The great thing about RVE is that the
standard errors are now fine even if the
model is not correctly specific. For
instance, when you use a random effects
model that does not explicitly model the
dependence of effect sizes that come
from the same study.
Moreover, RVE does not make the
assumption of normality anymore.
We can also use it when observed effect
sizes are not weighted according their
uh precision.
Yet using RVE also has its limitations.
For instance, when you have sub studies
within studies that use a two-level
model rather than a three-level model,
the standard errors you will obtain for
the overall effect is fine, but you will
not get separate variance estimates for
the variance between studies and the
variance between substies.
Moreover, if the model is not correct,
observed effect sizes may not be
optimally weighted and hence the metalic
results may be less precise.
Therefore, an optimal solution seems to
be to use a model that is as good as
possible,
but combine this model with RVE as a
stafnet for a possible misspecification
of the model.
Pistski and Typton proposed three kinds
of models to be used in combination with
RVE.
The first model is a hierarchal effects
model which in fact which is in fact the
multilevel model for instance to be used
when within studies you have multiple
substudies with different samples.
The second model is a correlated effects
model which is a multivariate model to
be used when within studies multiple
effect sizes are calculated for the same
sample.
The hierarchal and correlated effects
model combines both models.
To illustrate the approach, look at the
example
of a very recent meta analysis in which
I was involved. In this meta analysis,
we studied among other things the
association between the perception of
one group that another group of persons
persons is not really human
on one side and the willingness to use
violence against that other group on the
other side.
In this meta analysis, we combined data
from multiple projects.
Each project project one or more studies
were done and in each study one or more
samples were investigated and for each
sample one or more effects were studied.
Therefore by using the trick of
considering different samples as
independent samples from multiple
substies we would have five levels.
Yet using the hierarchal and correlated
effects model, we would have four
levels.
Here the results.
I first fitted a traditional random
effects model. This is a twolevel model
because this model does not account for
the dependence between effect sizes. So
does not account for the overlap in
information given by effect sizes from
the same sample, study or project. The
standard error is probably
underestimated and therefore the
confidence interval around the overall
association is too small. The confidence
interval is too optimistic.
We see indeed that when using RVE for
the same model, the standard error is
considerably larger and so the
confidence interval is also larger.
Let's look at results when using a
hierarchal 51 or a multivariat model
with a guest row of.5 or8.
Interestingly, for these three models,
we get very similar results. Using RVE
on top of these models slightly
increases the confidence interval width,
but that the results are dead very
similar for these three kinds of models
with or without using RVE increases our
confidence in these results.
To be honest, I do not have an
explanation why the confidence interval
when using RVE in combination with a
two-level model is smaller than the
confidence interval when using the
multi-level or multivariate model. I
think it would be interesting to do a
simulation study to compare
systematically these different
approaches.
To conclude, I recommend using an
appropriate model combined with RVE. In
this way, you combine the advantages of
both approaches. By using RVE, the type
one error rate is under control.
By using an appropriate model, you get
information on the different population
variance parameters
and studies will be appropriately
weighted.
A drawback of this approach is of course
its complexity.