In this video, we will look at the
reporting and discussion of the results.
First, it is important that you describe
the process of your review or meta
analysis because this will make your
study replicable and helps the reader
understand and contextualize your
findings.
For instance, a good practice is to
describe this process of searching and
selecting studies. To that end, a
flowchart can be helpful to describe how
many studies you initially found and
then explain how you ended up with a
smaller set of studies.
Here
you see a more elaborated flowchart
based on the Prisma format that you can
download via the link given in red. Note
that in this meta analysis, more than
18,000 sources were initially
identified.
But after screening the titles and
abstracts, the large majority of sources
was excluded.
After reading the full text of the
remaining sources, only 67 studies were
considered eligible.
In the flowchart, the reasons for
excluding studies are also listed
together with a number of studies
excluded for each of these reasons.
Also, other aspects of the metal
analytic process should be described
such as how effect sizes were
calculated. What software was used to do
the analysis, what decisions were made
and why, what problems were encountered
and so on.
Also explore and describe the data by
means of tables and graphs before doing
the actual statistical analysis.
It's a good idea to make a table with
the most important features of the
studies that were found. In this way,
the reader gets a good idea of what kind
of research was done and also what kind
of research has not yet been done. It's
also an efficient way to give a lot of
information on each of the individual
studies.
Such a table can be quite long. So
sometimes it's not included in the paper
itself but added in an appendix or in
online supplemental material.
Forest plot gives a nice overview of the
effects that were observed. In this plot
for instance, one can immediately see
that the majority of studies found a
positive effect and about half of them a
significant positive effect.
A similar plot is a caterpillar plot. In
contrast to the forest plot, observed
effect sizes are now ordered from small
to large, resulting in the shape of a
caterpill.
Based on the plot in this example, you
can immediately see that a large
majority of studies found a positive
effect size, but that only a minority of
studies found a significant effect.
It's also good to describe the
proportion of positive and negative
effects as well as a proportion of
positive and negative significant
effects.
After describing the data clearly report
on the results of the meta analysis
again a forest plot can be helpful.
A forest plot does not only give the
individual observed effect sizes but
also gives the mean effect size with a
corresponding confidence interval
which you can see here at the bottom of
the plot.
Here
are an example of how you can report
results of a moderator analysis for
categorical uh moderators. For the
moderator level of processing, for
example, there are two categories of
effect sizes, local and global. For each
category, the number of observed effect
sizes is reported as well as the mean
effect size and the results of the t
testing that this mean effect size is
zero.
In addition, the results of an F test is
reported. Testing the moderating effect.
This is this is whether the expected
effect size is different for the
different categories
to communicate on the findings of
categorical moderator analysis. You can
also use sorted caterpillar plot with it
with for the different categories the
observed effect sizes as well as the
estimated mean effect
which is given in the shaded areas.
In this example, it shows that the
majority of effect sizes fall in the
first category and that for this
category the mean effect is largest.
or numerical
or continuous moderator variables,
regression plot can be helpful. Here the
size of the dots refers to the weight
that is given to the observed effect
sizes. In other words, refers to the
precision of the effect sizes.
Of
course, you should also help the reader
in interpreting the results.
In this regard, I want to make an
important remark regarding the external
validity. The golden standard in
empirical research is to draw a random
sample of participants from a population
of participants so that we can more
easily generalize the findings to that
population.
In a meta analysis, we also typically
consider the observed studies as a
random sample or population of studies
that are done or could have been done.
But in fact, we did not draw a random
sample. We collected the results from
studies that we found.
We have seen that publication bias can
be an issue. The studies that you find
may be a systematic selection of the
studies that were done.
But even if you could find all the
studies that were done, the studies that
are done are probably also a systematic
selection of studies that could have
been done.
For instance, if you search for studies,
it's not unlikely that onethird or even
half of the studies are from the United
States and another large part from
Europe. Often
there is a smaller part of studies
coming from Asia and very little very
few studies from South America and
especially Africa.
Therefore, it's hard to generalize the
findings to the whole world.
In addition, it's possible that
interventions were studied not only in
contexts in which it is expected that
these interventions may work which also
can give a biased idea of the overall
effect of the interventions.
In some take care with interpretation of
your results. Always wonder to what
extent your results can be generalized
and how the population of studies to
which you would generalize your findings
looks like.
Another golden rule is that in order to
draw causal conclusions, it's best to
assign participants randomly to
different conditions while keeping all
other variables under control. If you
then find the difference between
conditions in the outcome variable, it's
likely that this difference is caused by
the condition.
But in a meta analysis, you cannot
randomly assign studies to conditions
and keep other characteristics under
control. You simply can observe the
characteristics of studies and the
effects that these studies found.
Therefore, if you observe, for instance
that studies with female researchers
found higher effects than studies with
male researchers, you cannot say that
the intervention effect is affected by
the gender of the researcher.
Other study characteristics may be
related to the gender of the researcher
and these other characteristics could be
the real reason why the effect is
different.
For instance, female researchers may be
more common in some countries or they
may be more common for some participant
age groups or for some kinds of
interventions.
It is of course also important to check
the assumptions that that you made in
the analysis and to report on these
checks.
Like we discussed earlier, it's a good
idea to check for evidence for
publication bias and possibly correct
for publication bias.
Also look for possible outlying effect
sizes and their impact on the results
and check other assumption as well like
for instance the assumption that effect
sizes or at least residuals are normally
distributed.
Finally I highly recommend doing several
sensitivity analysis.
In a math analysis, we indeed have to
make a lot of decisions and often it's
not clear what decision is the best
decision. Therefore, it's a good idea to
assess what the effect is of your
decisions by looking at whether and how
your conclusions would change if you had
taken another decision. If the
conclusion remains unaltered, then this
confirms that your conclusion can be
trusted.
Yet if the conclusion changes when
another decision is taken, this reduces
your confidence in your conclusion. It
is important to be transparent about
this in your report and so to to share
to share your uncertainty about the
conclusion.
For instance, you can look at how
sensitive the conclusions are for the
inclusion or exclusion of outliers.
Also, when calculating effect sizes, we
may have to make decisions. For
instance, sometimes no information is
given on the correlation between pre-est
and post- test scores. Whereas this is
needed to calculate the precision of a
standardized mean difference in such a
design.
Therefore, you can impute a value, but
it is good to assess how sensitive the
conclusions of your meta analysis are
for the value that was imputed.
Similarly,
one could choose to include all studies
in the met analysis or only um include
studies with a strong design or a high
quality. You can assess the impact of
this choice on the conclusions by
comparing the results of both choices.
Further, you can assess the robustness
of the conclusions for the researcher
who did the research
uh the effect size calculation, the
analysis and so on by letting another
researcher redo these steps and then
compare the results.
Also redoing the analysis with other
model choices can help to assess the
confidence one can have in the
conclusions.
I want to conclude by saying that good
reporting is an essential component of
good research.