In this video, we will look at the study
retrieval.
In the introduction, we have seen that a
meta analysis typically consists of
eight steps.
In this video, we will look at the first
three steps. Formulating a research
question, doing a systematic search for
studies, and selecting the relevant
studies.
Let's first look at the first step. the
formulation of the research problem
as well as in other studies. It is
important that you have a clear problem
for formulation. So before you start
your study, so before you collect data,
it is good that you know very well what
exactly you want to study.
So this includes information on for
instance a population. So about what
units you want to say something
the variables. So what characteristics
you are interested in
possible hypothesis or research
questions. So these are about the
relations between these variables
and then finally a further limitation of
the problem. So you you want to define
what exactly you want to study um about
these hypothesis or research questions.
To give an example, suppose in a study
one is interested in the relationship
between challenging behavior of persons
with mental retardradation and the
behavior of staff.
This research question may be too broad.
If you were to do a met analysis, then
it is possible that you will find a lot
of studies and also very yeah
heterogeneous studies. So it may be a
better idea idea to limit the problem
somewhat. For instance, it's possible to
limit the problem to uh the self-injury
injurous behavior of persons with severe
mental retardradition and stimulating
behavior of staff. So you limit the
problem by looking at the specific
behavior of um persons with retradation
and specific behavior of the staff and
you look at a subgroup of persons with
mental retradation. So this may make
your systematic review or meta analysis
more uh realistic more feasible
to define the research question. A
helpful model is the PICO model.
In the PICO model, the P stands for the
population,
the I stands for the intervention or the
interest, the C for the comparison, and
the O for the outcome.
So, a good research question
says something about these four
elements.
To give an example,
a good question could be what is the
effect on drug abuse in secondary school
students of giving information at school
rather than giving sanctions to drug
users. So the population are students
from secondary schools.
intervention is giving information at
school
and you compare
this intervention with another uh
condition more specifically giving
sanctions to drug users and to evaluate
that intervention you look at the
outcome drug abuse.
Next, you're going to search for
studies.
And very often, we want to do a
systematic search. So, if you want to do
a systematic review, then we need to do
a systematic search as well. And we talk
about a systematic search. If we are
using a thorough and transparent search
for all relevant studies,
published and unpublished studies. So we
look at articles, books, conference
papers, dissertations, research reports
and so on. So we look for all studies
that potentially say something um about
our research question.
To that end, we can look for literature
in several steps. I will discuss six
possible steps.
The first step is the use of online uh
databases.
So, it may be a good idea to ask
somebody working in a library to help
you with that.
or you can find on the website of uh the
university libraries
uh some information about how you can
search databases.
There are several databases to which uh
we have access at the gloven the more
the most important databases probably
are ERIC psychonfo
citation abstracts international web of
science and so on.
We can also use Google or Google Scholar
uh to look for interesting studies or
other search engines like Alta Vista or
Jahu. But a problem with these um search
engines is that
you cannot replicate the search. I mean
if somebody else would uh try to repeat
your search
uh say in for instance one year or two
years the person will probably not get
exactly the same hits as you got uh when
you do the search. Now this is not true
for the other databases. So if you use
for instance ERIC, if you search today
in the ERIC database with a set of
keywords and you do the same search
again next year with the same keywords
and you say I'm only interested in
studies until for instance the end of
2021, you will get exactly the same
results.
So you can replicate um the search if
you use such a database which is not the
case for Google, Google Scholar, Alta
Vista, Jahu and so on. So that's a
reason for using um these scientific
databases only.
The same is true for Limo or Limo. This
is the system that is used at K Louven
that can be used to uh search databases
or search immediately in all uh uh
journals that are available at K Louven.
So also there what databases are in limo
or what journals are in limo can vary
from day to day
and it is impossible or it yeah it is
impossible to know next year what
databases and what journals exactly were
in limo today. So also there it is
impossible to replicate the search.
Moreover, of course, people from outside
K Louven uh may not have access to limo.
So, which also makes that your search is
not replicable. So therefore I recommend
to use these major databases
and the major databases are for the
field of medicine but for the field of
behavioral sciences or psychology psycho
and for the field of educational
sciences ERIC
it is also a good idea to combine
multiple databases.
So for instance, if you're interested in
specific therapy, behavioral therapy,
well, you can find studies in Psych Info
as well as studies in Pepmmet.
And there probably will be a lot of
overlap between the studies that you
find in the two databases, but it's
possible that you also find uh relevant
studies only in Psych Info or only in
Pepmmet. So therefore it is a good idea
to combine multiple databases to find as
many studies as possible.
If you go to limo at Kuran and you click
on databases then you can type in for
instance Eric and then one of the hits
is um yeah the second one here
educational resources information center
ERIC. So that's the database with the
educational uh studies in it. If you
click on online access then yeah you can
consult this database online.
To search these databases you try to
translate your research question or
research problem in keywords.
Again, the PICO model can be helpful to
make sure that you are searching for
studies on the population, intervention,
and outcome variables of interest.
You can make use of quotes to keep words
together.
For instance, if you're looking for
studies on machine learning, you do not
want to find all papers on machines and
all papers on learning. By using quotes,
you can search for the concept machine
learning.
Another trick is to use an asterisk to
truncate a word by using meta analy with
an asterisk. For instance, you will look
for studies that talk about meta
analysis, metaanalytical,
meta analysis, meta analyzing and so on.
Also, using boolean operators to link
the keywords can help. For instance, if
a paper does not use the concept machine
learning but talks about artificial
intelligence or AI, this paper may also
be relevant. Therefore, you can search
for studies that use the word machine
learning or artificial intelligence or
AI.
If a study uses at least one of these
three terms, you will find the study.
You can use the and operator to look for
studies that talk about something and
about something else. For instance, if
you're looking for the use of AI in
education, you could search for AI and
education.
You can further restrict your research
by using the not operator. If you're
interested in AI in primary education,
you could say AI and education, not
higher education.
Finally, the use of the near operator
can avoid that you will get too many
irrelevant hits
when using and. Using near four in
between two terms for instance means
that the two terms should be not more
than four words apart from each other.
In that way you can for instance look
for studies that talk about AI and
education in the same sentence.
Finally in many databases you can
indicate in what fields these words
should be searched for. Often we will
get far too many hits if we look for
these words in the whole paper.
Therefore, we typically look into the
titles, keywords and abstracts. In Web
of Science, for instance, these fields
are indicated by TI, AK, and AB. But you
can also search in all these three kinds
of fields together by referring to D S
which stands for topics.
There is of course always the risk that
your research is missing relevant
studies. If you already know that there
are some important papers that are
definitely eligible, you can check
whether you can find these papers with
your search string. If not, you may want
to adapt your search.
an example. So in a study we have done
about uh the staff reactions to
challenging behavior in people with
severe mental retardation. We used the
following keywords.
So you can see that we have three that
we have defined three groups of
keywords. The first group of keywords
was about yeah the the persons with
mental retardation. We said well
disability
or mental retardation or complex needs
or high support needs or cognitive
impairment or learning difficulty should
be included in the paper.
Then we have a second group about the
behavior of these persons. So we said
that challenging behavior or problem
behavior or aggression or self-injury or
self-insurance behavior should be
included. And then also a third uh one
or more um terms from the third group
should be included more specifically
staff care care worker or special
educator.
Note that um yeah you you see that we
included problem behavior with a U. It
may also be a good idea to include
problem behavior with an O only. So
without the U.
So in that way you have the UK and the
US notation. And in that way it's
possible that you will find even more uh
studies
an example. So in a study we have done
about uh the staff reactions to
challenging behavior in people with
severe mental retardation we used the
following keywords.
So you can see that we have three that
we have defined three groups of
keywords. The first group of keywords
was about yeah the the persons with
mental retardation. We said well
disability
or mental retardation or complex needs
or high support needs or cognitive
impairment or learning difficulty should
be included in the paper.
Then we have a second group about the
behavior of these persons. So we said
that challenging behavior or problem
behavior or aggression or self-injuring
or self-insurance behavior should be
included. And then also a third uh one
or more um terms from the third group
should be included more specifically
staff care care worker or special
educator.
Note that um yeah you you see that we
included problem behavior with a U. It
may also be a good idea to include
problem behavior with an O only. So
without the U.
So in that way you have the UK and the
US notation. And in that way it's
possible that you will find even more uh
studies.
Second example, in another study in
which we studied uh students
misconceptions of statistical inference,
we again used uh three groups of
keywords. And so for each of the groups
at least one of these terms should be
included in the paper. So we had
misconception or error or misuse or
misinterpretation or misunderstanding or
fallacy. And then the second group was
inference or sampling or normal or
confidence or interval or test or level
or p value. And then the last group was
course or college or university.
So again here you can see that use of
the pico model can help you to define uh
keywords
to find um other keywords that could be
relevant. It is possible to use the
taros. So for instance in Eric so here
we are in Eric you can click there on
search tools and then tool type you can
click on this and then if you type in a
word like misconceptions which is a
relevant uh keyword for uh the study we
were interested in. So then Eric is
given giving several suggestions or is
uh giving some related words like
cognitive structures, comprehension,
concept formation, concept mapping,
learning processes and so on.
So in this way we can look for what
other keywords could be relevant for our
search and you can then decide to
include these keywords as well.
This is also in ERIC. So here in ERIC I
indicated that we are looking for
keywords in the abstract or
as a heading word or in the title
and then you get a set of hits in the
best case. uh probably you will get a
lot of hits.
And you can see here in Eric um if you
uh use limo to access access Eric you
will find in the hits a link um K Louven
that can be used to go to the full text.
So to to find the full text um
electronically
note that there is a trade-off between
recall
so we want to to find all relevant
studies.
So we hope that the proportion of
relevant literature that is found is as
high as possible. Ideally you will find
all relevant literature.
So this can be done by uh using very
broad keywords. So the broader the
keywords you use, the more studies you
will find and the li the more likely it
is that you will find all relevant
information.
But the drawback is that in that way
your search will not will be not be very
precise. It's possible that you will
find a lot of hits that are not
relevant. So and if you get thousands of
hits it can be a huge work to select the
relevant studies afterwards. So you have
to find uh to try to find the balance
between recall and precision.
So that's the first step
uh the use of databases. A second step
can be browsing secondary sources. What
are secondary sources that can be for
instance encyclopedias?
So if you are interested in for instance
learning analytics well you can look in
encyclopedias what uh is said about
learning analytics. So typically also
think about Wikipedia for instance
typically uh a lot of references are
given uh that can be used to uh find uh
important studies. You can also go to
special journals. So there are some
journals like psychological bulletin,
educational research review that report
um or that publish a lot of reviews
or or a lot of meta analysis.
So maybe there were already meta
analysis or systematic reviews about
your research topic or there are reviews
about uh yeah very related topics. So it
can be a good idea to look in these
journals for relevant reviews so that in
that way you already have an idea of
what interesting studies could be
also in other journals of course uh
often reviews are published. You can
also look at handbooks
at uh conference programs and
proceedings and so on. So secondary
sources are sources that are not
reporting directly on individual studies
but they are referring to studies that
can be looked uh for afterwards
in a second step in third step. So once
you have found interesting studies
you can look at the references.
So there are two ways you can uh uh yeah
do a backward search which which means
that you look in the reference list of
these important uh studies. So you look
at what other studies does this study
referred to and probably also um studies
will be referred to that are relevant
for your systematic review as well.
You can also do a forward research which
means that you look at who or what other
papers site this relevant study.
So to that end so look again at the hits
we found um from a database here from
Eric you can see there a link for a
specific uh for each specific paper to
find citing articles. So you if you
click on that link you will see what
papers refer to this paper.
So we we call this a forward re uh
search because the papers that link to
this paper are newer papers.
A next step could be uh taking contact
with researchers.
So if you found that there are some
specific researchers that are apparently
doing a lot of research that is relevant
for your review, well you can contact
these researchers to ask whether they
have additional studies, studies that
you did not yet find.
So you can talk to researchers at
conferences or you can uh
ask your professors um in the field
whether they know of uh interesting
studies that you did not found find yet.
Uh you can go to electronic discussion
lists or you can uh yeah you can ask uh
researchers
um that are important in this field.
Important is that you look for
heterogeneous contacts. If you always
um
yeah go to the same type of researchers
then there will be bias in the list of
studies you find. So if you know that
there is a discussion in the domain
between so if there are different
schools within the domain that some
groups of researchers uh use a specific
type of of methods for instance and
another group of researchers use another
type of methods. It's important that in
the two schools or in the two groups of
researchers you try to find um studies.
Next step could be browsing journals.
So again online you can use databases to
see what journals were what articles or
what papers are published in journals.
Of course here you are going to look at
journals that um um that are within the
scope of your systematic review. So that
that these are publishing a lot of
papers in the field of interest for you.
And then the last step is looking for
research registries.
It's more and more the case that uh for
instance governmental organizations
require when they give funding to to uh
research groups or to projects they
require that um the data are sent uh to
these organizations or at least uh a
report is sent to these organization
independently of whether uh the results
were statistically significant.
Um so for instance uh the food and drug
administration of the US or the
institute of education sciences of the
US they ask or they keep a record of all
studies that were funded uh by these
organizations.
um
a note. So we try to find all relevant
studies
but take into account or keep in mind
that all relevant studies that were done
are not necessarily representative for
all studies that could have been done.
very often it is the case that some
specific subopuls or interventions or
outcomes or designs are not yet
sufficiently studied.
So it's important that you take this
into account when you make
interpretations or or draw conclusions.
But it can also be an important role of
a meta analysis or a systematic review
to give an overview of what has been
studied yet and what does not have been
studied
what does not was not studied yet. So
based on your systematic review, you can
uh suggest uh directions for future
research.
In the previous step, we search for
studies. Often we will initially find a
lot of potentially relevant studies. In
the next step, we make a selection of
the studies that are really relevant.
It's not uncommon that initially there
are two or three thousand potentially
relevant studies, but that from these
studies only about 100 studies appear to
be really relevant and are to be
included in the meta analysis.
For the selection of studies, we make a
list of inclusion and exclusion
criteria.
for instance about yeah the population.
So do we look at all kinds of of persons
or do we look do we look only at a
specific age
uh range?
You can also uh limit the type of
treatment or the duration of the
treatment.
You can also say that uh you will only
look at uh studies using a specific
design. For instance, you can say that
there should be a control group or at
least a control condition.
You can also look at um or use the study
quality as an inclusion criteria. So you
can say that only studies of a good
quality will be included
or of course you can say that yeah we
need enough information about the
outcome variable or about specific uh
study characteristics before we can
include that study in our systematic
review.
So it is important to make uh an
explicit list of inclusion and exclusion
criterion criteria and it's also
important to report on that list. Why is
it important? Well, it's important
because in that way you can uh make a
selection of studies in a consistent
way. So it's important that if you
selected a study for uh for your
systematic review then another study
that is very similar uh also has to be
included in your systematic review and
the other way around if you decide that
a specific study should be excluded then
a very similar study should also be
excluded.
So that's consistency but also for
replicability.
So this means that other researchers
should be able to replicate or repeat
your research and come to very similar
conclusions. So therefore it's important
that you uh make clear what exact
inclusion and exclusion criteria you
used so that if another person would do
the search and the study selection again
that that person will get exactly the
same uh uh results.
A remark is that if you use a very
narrow criteria
then you will probably have uh will end
up with a small set of studies which is
not good in a sense because the smaller
the set of studies the lower the
statistical power.
On the other hand if you use narrow
criteria then your set of studies will
be probably more homogeneous. So we'll
be more alike which is which makes that
uh it is easier to draw conclusions or
to interpret the results.
So a possible approach is that um you
start with somewhat broader criteria
in a pilot search and if you see that uh
you will have too many hits. So making
it not feasible anymore uh to do this
search
uh to do this uh systematic review then
you still can refine um the search.
So an example an example of in an
exclusion criteria we used in a
systematic review on the effects of
priming.
Yeah. For instance, one of the uh
criteria was the relationship between
the prime and a target should be of a
direct semantic nature. Not I will not
give uh details about the meaning of
this but you see that uh we said studies
investigating other types of of priming
such as phological priming morphological
priming and so on were excluded.
We said the primes have to be presented
subliminally
which means that it is beneath the
conscious threshold. And then we defined
further what we called the cons
conscious threshold
and so on and so further.
In this study, we
found based on a search in databases 749
published articles.
And here we can see an overview of um
what happened to these articles. So what
how many studies we excluded for various
reasons.
So for instance 213
studies were excluded because the prime
was not presented unconsciously
and then it is uh further explained. So
for instance the prime duration was uh
more than 100 milliseconds. This was the
case for 139 uh studies and so on. So we
give a a rather complete overview of the
reasons why we decided to exclude
studies
and after excluding a lot of the studies
only 46 uh articles remained in our data
set. So the final meta analysis included
only 46 published articles. So you see
that we uh started from 749
studies and we ended up with only 46
published articles. This is not
uncommon. Sometimes we even have much
more hits. We we start from say 1,000 or
two or 3,000 papers and at the end we
sometimes have even a smaller number of
uh papers that are included in the meta
analysis.
So it's clear that this process of study
selection is a very timeconsuming
process.
One of the selection criteria could also
be that the studies should be of
sufficient quality.
So this means that we have to make sure
that the quality of the individual
studies is
um high enough. But whereas this is true
in theory, in practice, this is uh a
very difficult issue. Why? Well, first
of all, quality is a continuum. It's not
a dichotomy.
There is no perfect study.
So even if as a researcher, you
permanently have to make decisions and
you very often know that there is no
perfect decision. So if you decide
option A, you know that there are some
disadvantages. If you choose option B,
there are maybe other disadvantages.
So there is no perfect study. Um
but of course there are differences
between studies in the size of the
quality, but it's a continuum, not a
dichotomy.
Another problem is how to judge quality.
If you ask multiple people what a
qualitative good study is, probably you
will get different answers. So there are
a lot of criteria that can be used and
maybe it's also a good idea to use
multiple criteria.
But if you use multiple criteria, how
are you going to
weight this criteria?
If you want to say something about the
quality of a study in general, are you
going to calculate an average of these
criteria and to what criteria you are
going to give larger weights than to
what other criteria? Or maybe it's
possible that you have 20 criteria and
that a study performs well on 19
criteria, but that that study does not
perform well on the 20 criterion. Now
based on that you say well this final
criterion is for me that important that
if a study fails on this criterion
I cannot call this study a good study.
Another problem is very often the data
to judge quality are not reported.
For instance,
um in qualitative good study,
assumptions are tested. Assumptions
underlying statistical tests are
checked. But very often
uh researchers check these assumptions
but simply do not report that they
checked these assumptions.
So how can you can you judge the quality
based on
information that is not complete?
If it's not, if researchers do not
report on the check of the assumptions,
can you conclude that they did not check
the assumptions?
Another problem is the problem of
efficiency. If you are very severe, if
you want to include in your math
analysis only the studies from with the
highest quality, then maybe at the end
you will only combine two or three
studies.
Whereas if you are more lenient maybe in
your meta analysis you can include 20 30
studies and you can say okay the other
studies have a lower quality but still
studies with a lower quality can still
give some information about the
population effect size.
Another problem is the problem of bias.
For instance, we know that the internal
validity of experimental designs is
higher than the internal validity of
correlational designs.
But sometimes it's very hard to use an
experimental design.
So for instance um if you want to test
whether smoking results in lung cancer
or an increased probability of lung
cancer you cannot use an experimental
design in sense that you cannot say to
one group of people that is randomly uh
um selected. You cannot say to one group
from now on you have to smoke one
package a day and to another group that
is also randomly selected you cannot say
now you cannot uh smoke anymore for two
years.
So there are some practical and ethical
concerns that make that sometimes you
cannot use experimental designs and you
will have to use um designs with lower
internal validity
as an illustration of the lack of
consensus.
So I have here an overview of what some
organizations said about single case or
single subject experimental designs
about the value of these designs
um to give evidence to be included in
the met analysis. And then you can see
that some organizations
said well single case experimental
designs give persuasive evidence whereas
other uh organizations
said well they give some evidence but
less than uh for instance group
comparison designs and some
organizations said no single case
experimental designs are non-informative
at all.
Various free-touse tools or checklists
are available online
that are meant to evaluate the quality
of studies. Note that on this site you
cannot only find checklists for primary
studies including RCTs, qualitative
studies, diagnostic studies and so on
but also to evaluate the quality of
systematic reviews and meta analysis.
Also
on this page you find several tools for
quality appraisal of studies. The risk
of bias 2 tool for instance is good tool
to evaluate the quality of randomized
trials. Robins one for assessing the
quality of non-randomized trials.
Here
you see some questions of the risk of
bias 2 tool to get a question some
further explanation and then you can
give an answer yes probably yes probably
no
or not indicated
hard job.
If you look at these tools, well, in
general, these types of um aspects come
back regularly. Construct validity,
which is about um how the variables are
measured.
External validity is about the
generalization or the generalizability
of the results.
Internal validity is about
um the problem of uh possible
confounding variables
and then then the statistical conclusion
validity is about whether statistical
tests are or statistics were used in a
correct way. So these general criteria
come back very often in these tools.
Suppose that at the end you assessed the
quality of individual studies. How do
you deal with quality then afterwards in
your meta analysis? One option could be
that you include only the very best
studies.
Or you could also say well because this
will reduce the power the precision
because in that way I I will only
include a few studies maybe it's better
to include much more studies and I'm
going to exclude only the very worst
studies.
Still an alternative is that you include
all studies but that you weight the
studies according to the quality that
you give a larger weight the the larger
the quality of a study is.
It's also possible to investigate the
effect of quality. You can include
quality as a predictor variable in your
meta analysis to look at whether the
quality is related to the size of the
effect that was observed.
It's also possible to do a kind of
sensitivity analysis by performing a
meta analysis with all studies and
performing a meta analysis only on the
better studies and then you compare the
results to see whether there is a
difference between
um
highly qualitative studies uh compared
to the whole set of studies. If there is
no difference, conclusion is we do not
have to worry too much about quality.
The results are not affected by the
quality. If there is difference then
it's a good practice to present the
results of both analysis and to make
sure that the reader of your meta
analysis is aware of the problem of
assessing the quality and um
yeah the difficulty of interpreting the
results of your analysis.
So in general some guidelines I would
not include studies if they really have
a low quality. I definitely would use
several indices for quality. I also
would look for the effect of the design.
So if you have experimental designs and
correlational designs, I would also
include the type of design as a
predictor in the analysis to see whether
the effect depends on the design.
It's also a good idea to train coders of
the individual studies
um
coders that um assess the quality of
studies to make sure that all coders are
assessing the quality in exactly the
same way.
And it's also a good idea to assess the
size of reliability between uh the
coders.
If you code the quality, it's important
that you are also transparent about what
criteria you used to assess quality.
And an argument that is sometimes given
uh for including only peer-reviewed
papers is that peer-reviewed papers in
general have a higher quality because
these papers were already reviewed by
experts in the field.
This is true but there is a problem.
I already mentioned that is important
that you use very clear and ambiguous in
an exclusion criteria.
So this is important for obtaining
consistency.
So for instance, this also includes if
you uh uh say that uh only studies with
a good quality are included
that you defined what good quality is
for you. So how you operationalized good
quality
but not only for consistency also for
replicability it's important that you
have very clear in and exclusion
criteria and that you report on these
criteria.
It's also important that the coder so
that the person or the persons who make
the selection of the studies are trained
so that they very that they know very
well what the different in and exclusion
criteria mean and that they are able
that they have the knowledge to judge
whether these criteria are met.
It's also a good idea to do at least
part of the selection
by two independent coders. Why is that
good? Well, in that way you can study
whether um the study selection is done
in a reliable way. So in principle the
two coders should come to exactly the
same study selection. If this is not the
case then you can look at uh uh you can
have again uh have a look at uh the
inclusion and exclusion criteria or the
operationalization.
So maybe the criteria are not clear yet.
It's also a good idea to report about
the reli reliability of the selection
process. So for instance, you could uh
uh report on the percentage of
agreement.