In this session, I will talk about the
meta analysis of diagnostic studies.
What is a diagnostic study?
The purpose of a diagnostic study is to
evaluate the quality of diagnostic test.
So think for instance of a self test for
corona.
You hope that your tests can make a
distinction between people who are
positive and people who are not ne uh
positive.
In diagnostic studies, often multiple
tests are compared to each other, but
it's also possible that only one
specific test is studied.
What kind of data reported in a
diagnostic test study?
Well, if you want to say something about
the quality of a diagnostic test, we
need to
have uh yeah a standard or we we need to
have a criterion to decide on whether a
person is positive or not. and we use
that criterion to see whether our test
that we want to evaluate works well.
So let's look at the cases that are
positive. We hope that with our tests,
most of these cases that are positive
are also positively tested. So we hope
that the cases that are truly positive
is as high as possible
compared to cases that are positive but
that are not positively tested.
So these cases are called false
negatives.
So we hope that the true positives is
larger than the false negative number.
Similarly, for the cases that are in
reality negative,
we hope that most of them are tested
negatively. So, these cases are called
true negatives and that there are only a
few or non uh cases that are positively
tested. So, these cases are called false
positives.
So in general, we hope that the dark
blue and the dark red cell uh include as
many cases as possible and that the
other two cells include as few cases as
possible.
So think for instance of an instrument
uh a screening instrument for the down
syndrome.
So suppose that in a study
we have data from about 5,000
uh persons 5,000 uh babies.
Some of them are
positive. So some of them shown down
syndrome
more specifically about 10 persons and
the other persons are not positive.
So suppose that these 5,000 babies were
also screened previously so during the
pregnancy
and that from the 10 positive cases nine
cases were positively tested in using
the screening instrument and one of them
was not detected using the screening
instrument
from all the negative cases.
So there are um 4,800
negative cases.
From all these negative cases, most of
them were tested negatively based on the
screening instrument, which is good. But
351 cases were tested positively.
So of course um both errors are not
desirable. So if a specific baby has the
down syndrome and this was not detected
using the screening instrument, this has
negative consequences. For instance,
maybe uh the parents um would have um
decided to abort the baby or maybe um it
has negative consequences in the sense
that that the parents are not prepared
at all for having a baby with Down
syndrome.
the other type of error. So the negative
and the cases that were tested positive
whereas in fact these babies did not
have the down syndrome
also is not desirable.
This induces unnecessary stress for the
parents. So if parents are told that
maybe uh the baby that they will get um
will have the down syndrome whereas in
fact this is not true.
This induces ne unnecessary stress.
The measure that we can use to express
the quality of the screening instrument
is the odds ratio. Here we can talk
about the diagnostic odds ratio.
We have already seen the odds ratio as a
measure of association between two
dichoamous variables. So we can use this
uh measure here as well.
Odds ratio can be calculated by
multiplying the true positives and the
true negatives. So that are the dark red
and the dark blue cells. And we divide
this multiplication by the false
positives multiplied by the false
negatives. So these are the two kinds of
cases for which we made a wrong
decision.
The diagnostic odds ratio in the example
is 114.08.
Note that there will be no association
between the two uh uh variables if the
odds ratio is equal to one. So here the
ratio is clearly much higher than one.
An alter of one would mean that the
screening instrument does not say
anything about um whether or not um a
case is positive.
We've also seen that an drawback of the
ozio is that it has a skewed
distribution. It's also not very um very
handy that the
um the absence of an effect the absence
of an association means that the odds
ratio would be equal to one. it's easier
um if if the value if the um measure of
association would be equal to zero if
there is no association at all.
Another drawback of the odds ratio is
that the sampling variance is not easily
uh calculated.
So therefore very often the natural
logarithm of the odds ratio is taken. So
we use the LO odds ratio. In this
example, the LO odds ratio is 4.74.
A loss ratio equal to zero means that
there is no association at all. So again
here we see that there is evidence that
the screening instrument seems to work.
The sampling variance of the lostu can
be calculated by taking one over the the
sample size in the first cell plus one
over the sample size in the second cell
and so on. And so in our example this
gives a sampling variance of 1.11.
We can use that uh sampling variance to
calculate a confidence interval around
the loz ratio. the sampling distribution
of the loit loss ratio is more or less a
normal distribution.
So we can calculate the confidence
interval or 95% confidence interval by
taking the mean or the uh the estimate
of the local ops ratio and subtracting
or adding 1.96
times the square root of the sampling
variance. This gives us confidence
interval starting from 2.67
going to 6.81.
A zero is not included in the confidence
interval. So again here it's clear that
there is an association between the two
variables or in other words that the
screening instrument says something
about um uh being positive or not.
Remark uh suppose that uh one of the
cells does not include
uh cases or that in one of the cells the
number is equal to zero. In that case
you cannot calculate um the odds ratio
and or the sampling variance of the odds
ratio. So a solution um that is often
used is that you can add 0.5 to all of
the four cells to avoid that in one of
the cells you have zero.
Now suppose that you have a sample of
studies of diagnostic studies
and in each of these studies you have an
ulcer rates or you can calculate an
ulcer rates. How can you combine the
data from these um studies? Well, we can
combine these diagnostic odds ratios or
more specifically we can combine the
loss ratios using ordinary precision
weighted metalic techniques that we have
seen before.
You can also if in some of the studies
uh odds ratios are calculated but in
other studies you have standardized mean
differences. We have seen that you can
convert loss ratios to standardized mean
differences using this formula. So the
standardized mean difference is equal to
the loss ratio multiplied by the square
root of 3 / pi.
And so this means that you have to to
multiply the sampling variance of the
lock ratio by three divided by pi
squared to obtain um the sampling
variance of the standardized mean
difference.
Of course you can also calculate um lo
ratios based on standardized mean
differences. So convert um measures in
the other direction.
Um when are you going to use loss ratios
in your meta analysis? When are you
going to use standardized main
differences? So you can choose between
these two options. But a good idea is to
use um yeah the effect size that is uh
more commonly used in our set of
studies. So if you have 10 studies in
which a loss ratio can immediately be
calculated and one study in which a
standardized mean difference is uh
reported then it makes sense to convert
that one standardized mean difference to
the loss ratio.
Note that by calculating an odds ratio
or loss ratio, you lose some information
in the sense that it's possible that
different kind of tables will give
exactly the same uh os ratio and
therefore also the same loss ratio. So
you lose information that is uh included
in your table by uh calculating the odds
ratio. Can we avoid losing information?
Yes, we can.
It is possible to calculate two measures
of quality instead of that one measure
uh the odds ratio. More specifically, we
can calculate the sensitivity and the
specificity.
What is the sensitivity?
The sensitivity
is the number of true positives divided
by the total number of positives. So
here in the example we have 10 positive
cases and nine of them of them were uh
were detected using the screening
instrument. So that means that the
sensitivity is 90%.
So it's the probability that a positive
case will be tested positively.
The specificity
is the number of true negatives divided
by the total number of negative cases.
So in our example,
there were 4,800
negative cases and 4,449
of these cases were indeed tested
negatively. So that means that for 93%
of the negative cases um these cases
were tested negatively.
So we hope that both the sensitivity and
the specificity are as high as possible.
Note um 93%
of the negative cases were tested
negatively. So this means that 7% of the
negative cases were tested positively.
So this is called the false positive
rate. The false positive rate is the
probability that a negative case is
still tested positively.
What is also sometimes reported in
diagnostic studies is the like likely
likelihood ratio
for cases that were positively tested
and the likelihood ratio for cases that
were negatively tested.
What is that likelihood ratio for
positive positively tested cases? Well,
that's the probability
that a positive case is tested
positively. So that's the sensitivity
divided by the probability that a
negative case is tested positively. So
that's one minus specificity.
And the likelihood ratio for the
negative negatively tested cases is the
probability of
a positive case tested negatively
divided by the probability of a negative
case tested negatively. So it's one
minus the sensitivity divided by um the
specificity
and the ratio between that uh likelihood
ratio for the positively tested cases
divided by uh the likelihood ratio for
the cases that are negatively tested.
that ratio is another way um of
calculating the diagnostic odds ratio.
Now instead of doing a meta analysis of
the diagnostic odds ratios, it's also
possible to do meta analysis of the
sensitivity and specificity values.
One way is to do two separate met
analysis. So again using precision
weight uh weighted analysis but
separately for the sensitivity values
and specificity values.
Another approach which is somewhat more
efficient is to use a bariate meta
analysis.
So how does it work? Well, we say that
um
the number of positive test results
for positive cases
in study I and the number of positive
test results for negative cases in study
I. These two numbers
follow binomial distributions.
So the number of positive test results
for positive cases in study I follow a
binomial distribution with uh yeah the
number of positive cases and with a
probability. So the probability that a
positive case is tested positively. So
that's the sensitivity
for the negative uh cases. The
probability
of that binomial distribution is the
false positive rate. So one minus um the
specificity. So that's the probability
that a negative case will be tested
positively.
And then we say well these two
probabilities so the sensitivity and the
false positive rate they follow a normal
distribution across studies.
with means
theta 1 and theta 2. So theta 1 is the
overall sensitivity across all studies
and the U1 I is the random effect of
study I for the sensitivity.
So if that is positive then this means
that the true sensitivity for study I is
larger than the mean sensitivity across
all studies.
The same is true for the false positive
rate. So theta 2 is the overall false
positive rate across all studies and the
U2I
is the random deviation for study I. Um
so if that is positive then the false
positive rate for that study or the true
false positive rate for that study is
larger than the overall false positive
rate. And we assume that both random
effects follow a normal distribution a
multivariate normal distribution with
means zero and with variances and a
covariance that should be estimated.
So now yeah we use a multivariate or a
bariate meta analysis. So now we have
two between study variances. So the
between study variance in the
sensitivity rate and the between study
variance in the false positive rate and
there is a co or there's possibly
co-variance
um between the two um parameters across
studies.
Note the sensitivity and the specificity
that is found in a specific study
depends on the cut off or the threshold
that is used in that study. So suppose
that you have that you have a test value
and that um when the value exceeds a
specific value the threshold you
conclude okay that case is positive when
that person or the test value does not
um exceed the threshold then that person
is called a negative case.
Well, and suppose that you have um in
reality
so two distributions two normal
distributions of these test values. Uh
the uh the blue distribution is a
distribution of the negative cases. So
the really negative cases, the red
distribution is the distribution of the
cases that are in reality positive.
And you can see that um part of the
negative cases have a value um that is
larger than the threshold. So that's the
light blue um surface. So these are the
false positives.
You can also see that from all positive
cases. So that's the right normal
distribution. Part of them have has a
value lower than the threshold. So these
cases are not tested positively whereas
they are positive. So these are the
false negatives. So that part is given
in light red.
Note that by increasing the thresholds,
so by moving the green line line to the
right,
the number of false positives will
become smaller. So this means that the
specificity that is found in that study
will become higher. At the same time,
there will be more false negatives. So
the light red surface will become
larger. So this means that the
sensitivity will become lower. So by
incre increasing
the green line you increase the
specificity which is good but at the
same time you decrease the sensitivity
which is not good.
So therefore you can expect that there
is an association between specificity
and sensitivity.
So that there is a a co-variance. So in
the previous slide I explained that we
can estimate the coariance between
specificity and sensitivity. Well in
fact we can expect that there is a
negative association between the two
measures because different studies can
use different thresholds.
And so studies using a very large
threshold
will probably have a higher specificity
rate but a lower sensitivity rate.
So the sensitivity and the specificity
depend on the cutoff used. So this means
that the results of the math analysis
are not very not that interesting in the
sense that uh variances in specificity
and sensitivity may not reflect true
differences um between the study
findings but may rather reflect
difference between studies in the
threshold that is used
as an alternative approach which is
however um statistically equivalent. You
can also use the receiving operating
characteristic curves.
So the rock curves.
So a rock curve summarizes the data per
study or possibly over studies. So a
rock curves looks like this. So on the
yaxis you have the sensitivity.
On the x axis you have um the one minus
the specificity. So on the y-axis you
have the probability
that positive cases are tested
positively.
On the x-axis you have the probability
that negative cases are tested
positively.
So you hope that um a study will find
Yeah. Well, and and for each study you
will have you can calculate these two
measures and you hope that the
sensitivity will be as high as possible
and the one minus the specificity will
be as small as possible but you can
expect that there is a relationship
between the two.
So the higher the sensitivity, the lower
the specificity and therefore also the
higher one minus the specificity.
Now suppose that yeah so here you can
see the results of multiple studies.
Each dot stands for one specific study.
Um all these studies uh studied one
specific instrument.
So all these data together give some
evidence that that instrument seems to
work. If the instrument does not work at
all,
then the dots would um would be
scattered around that diagonal um line.
More specifically, then you would expect
that the probability that positive cases
are tested positively is exactly the
same as a probability that negative
cases are positively tested.
So in that case um the dots would be
distributed around that diagonal uh
line. But here you can see that the
majority of the dots are higher than
that uh diagonal line. So which means
that even if the yeah the spec
yeah for given a specific specificity
um sensitivity one minus the specificity
is smaller.
So this is what we hope to find.
You can go to that site uh
uh from which I I have put the link on
the slide to play around with a
threshold. And you can see indeed that
if you change a threshold then you would
uh expect to find another sensitivity
and another one minus specificity. And
so that curve
um that is uh given in that uh in that
plot
um yeah describes how um the sensitivity
and u the specificity are related to
each other and um the values
depend on the threshold that is used.
So based on that curve
you can find the best solution. You can
um you can think about what is the cost
of making
one specific error and the cost of
making another type of error. For
instance, what is the cost of not
finding a positive case
versus what is the cost of um saying
that the case is positive whereas that
case is not positive.
And by balancing these two costs, you
can decide on what threshold you could
use.
Note that uh the second plot here looks
better than the first plot.
In the second plot, the instrument seems
to to be able uh better to make a
distinction between these two
distributions.
So whereas in the first plot in the
upper plot there is a large part or
large surface of false positives and
false negatives
in the
um the plot at the bottom it's clear
that these two surfaces are much
smaller. This is also reflected in the
um rock curve. You can see that here the
rock curve is much higher is much
farther away from the diagonal line.
A measure that can be used to express
express how good the instrument is is
the area under the curve.
So the area under the diagonal line
would be 0 50.
So the area under the curve for the
instrument
at the uh upper plot is 73. For the
under plot it is almost one. So you can
see that uh there's only a small part of
the total surface that is on the left
side of the curve. So you hope that that
curve that that area is as large as
possibly possible. Ideally this equal to
one.
So the higher the area under the curve
the better.
Now how you how can you met analyze
rock curves?
Well you can use this model. So at the
lowest level so within studies we have
the same equations as before. So we say
that the number of positively tested
cases
um given that cases are positive follow
a binomial distribution with number of
positive cases and with a specific
sensitivity rate. the number of
positively tested negative cases.
Uh it follows a binomial distribution
with the number of negative cases in
that study and with a probability that
is equal to one minus specificity.
And then we say well these two um
probabilities so these two pies
can be described as a nonlinear function
of theta i plus
alpha i * x i j * x - beta xig J.
So there are two uh probabilities. So pi
1 i and pi 2 i. So the j in the equation
uh of level two refers to positive
subjects or negative subjects.
and the Xig J
is equal to one for positive subjects
and zero for negative subjects.
And then the parameters that are
estimated in our meta analysis are the
means of theta eyes and the alpha eyes
as well as the variances and the
covariances across studies of these two
parameters. But what are the uh the
meanings of these parameters?
Well,
so suppose that you have um so so so
xig
reverse is equal to one for positive
cases and zero for negative cases. So
for
negative cases
the equation uh simplifies a lot. So for
negative cases the logit of pi is equal
to theta i.
So theta i determines the probability
for a negative person
of being tested positively.
So that refers to the threshold used in
the study.
And so the variance in the ice refers to
uh the differences between studies in
the threshold that is used.
Alpha I. So which is a parameter for
study I
indicates to what extent the probability
for testing positively
changes when um a person in reality is
positive and not negative.
So it refers to the discrimination of
the test. So we hope that alpha i is as
high as possible.
So alpha i refers to the quality of the
test.
And what is the meaning of beta? So you
can see that in the graph. So in the
graph you can see uh look first at the
red and the blue curve. So the blue
curve is for a test that discriminates
not at all. So for a test with a quality
of zero. So alpha is equal to zero.
Whereas for the red curve alpha is equal
to two. You can see that um it's better
the the higher alpha the better the test
discriminates between the two uh groups
between true positives and true
negatives.
What's the meaning of beta? Well,
compare the red and the gray curve.
Well, the red curve is a symmetric curve
whereas the gray curve is an asymmetric
curve. So the beta um yeah describes or
expresses the asymmetry of the rock
curve.