In the search studies, in the selection
of the studies and in the interpretation
of the meta analytic results, you have
to be aware of the risk of bias.
This is what this screencast is about.
The problem is if you include only
papers that are published
then the results may be biased. There
can be different kinds of bias. outcome
reporting bias which refers to the the
idea that maybe researchers
will report the results only if the
results are going in a specific
direction.
So if you include in your meta analysis
only studies that you found in the
literature so that um results that were
reported by the researchers you can get
a biased view.
Another issue is publication bias which
refers to the problem that what is
published
may also
yeah give a biased view of um the
results maybe effects that are positive
and that are large are more likely to be
p to be published than uh smaller
effects or negative effects. So if you
look only at public published effects
then maybe you will overestimate the
size of the effect.
Another problem is citation bias.
So spectacular effects
very large effects are much likely much
more likely to be cited frequently.
And so if effects are cited frequently,
if studies are cited frequently, then it
is much more likely that you will find
that study and that you will include it
in your meta analysis.
If one study has not been cited yet or
has been cited only once for instance,
then the probability that you will find
that study will be smaller and maybe you
will miss that study in your math
analysis. So this will also
uh possibly um induce bias.
Another kind of bias is multiple
publication bias. You know that for
researchers it's important to publish as
much as possible and some researchers
when they do when they did a study they
try to make multiple publications out of
that study. And so as a metalist you
have to be very careful especially if
you see that um the same author or the
same authors published multiple papers
then you have to make clear
you have to make sure that these
multiple papers are publishing on
different data sets otherwise you can
include in your meta analysis only one
of these papers otherwise you will use
the same data multiple times in your
math analytic uh study, you will give a
larger weight to that study that has
been published multiple times.
There can also be a bias in keywords.
Um
so it's possible that a specific word
um a specific term is used more by
specific researchers or in specific
subdomains than in other domains. So if
you do not try to use um other keywords
um almost synonyms to search for
literature, it's possible that you miss
part of literature and that you miss
systematic
um that that your set of studies that
you will find is not representative
anymore for all studies that were done.
It's also possible that there is bias in
the sources that uh are used. So if you
um if you use only
uh journal articles then possibly so
that are again published uh papers then
again this can induce bias. So it's a
good idea to use not only journal
articles but maybe also look for books
also look for technical reports and so
on or conference proceedings and so on.
Um
also make sure that by defining the
criteria that you use to decide on
whether or not include uh individual
studies that you make sure that by
defining these criteria you do not
induce uh bias. For instance, if you if
one of your criteria is that you will
include only experimental studies, then
it's possible that specific studies or
specific uh questions
um will be or specific findings will be
underrepresented in your meta analysis.
There can also be geographical or
language bias. For instance, if you um
include only studies that were published
in English, then maybe you will miss a
lot of studies that were done, for
instance, in China, which are often
published in Chinese. Or you may miss a
lot of uh studies that were done in
France or in French-speaking countries
because they also have their own
journals in French language.
And it is possible that for instance in
China or in France or the French
speakaking countries results are
somewhat different than the results in
the English-speaking countries or the
countries in which a lot of studies were
published in English.
So there are several sources of bias.
Let's look at the issue of publication
or reporting bias.
There are a there is a lot of evidence
for this kind of bias. For instance,
here Edgar and Schmidt did a met
analysis
on studies
studying the
um yeah monotherapy calculating agent
versus a combination with chemotherapy
to treat advanced ovarian cancer.
and they did a meta analysis on
published trials on published uh
experimental studies and on average so
they calculated the survival ratio for
each study. So if the probability of
surviving is equally high for both kinds
of treatment
then the survival ratio will be equal to
one.
Now they did a meta analysis and they
based on the trials that were published
and they found that on average the
survival ratio is larger than one. It's
about 1
15 and if you look at the confidence
interval you can see that one is not
included in the confidence interval. So
this means that based on the published
data, their conclusion is well the
combination with chemotherapy is more
effective.
It's statistically more effective than
the monotherapy calculating agent only.
But they repeated this meta analysis
including all studies that were included
uh that were registered.
Um so note that some organizations if
they give fundings to do research they
require that the results are sent
regardless of what results are and these
results will be included in register the
research register.
So you can consider this register or the
published trials as a sub set of the
registered trials. And if you look at
all trials that were registered then you
see that on average the survival ratio
is only slightly slightly larger than
one and now the confidence interval
includes one. So based on all trials, so
published and unpublished trials, the
conclusion is no, we do not see really a
difference between the monotherapy
calculating agent versus combination
with chemotherapy.
Whereas if you look at the published
trials, you can see that difference. So
this could be an indication of
publication bias in the sense that more
spectacular results. Studies that found
a large difference between the two are
more likely to be published or
researchers are more likely to report
these results.
So this can be an indication of
reporting bias and publication wise.
Another example,
Krishnanovski Kanovska
uh
looked at the proportion of studies
that were published after five years
after a conference
conferences of the Society of Clinical
Oncology.
And I found that for studies that found
significant results, the probability
that these results will be published
after five years after the conference is
81%.
Whereas for the non-significant results,
only 68% of these studies were published
after 5 years. So again, this is an
indication of outcome
uh reporting bias or publication bias.
So it's possible that researchers did
not send non-significant results to
journals or if they sent it to journals
maybe these results were not published
because they were not significant.
some other indications. Well, um if
yeah, Finelli uh in 2012 looked at um a
set of papers a large set of papers in
psychology and psych psychiatry and they
found that in 95% of the test null
hypothesis
um
these null hypothesis were rejected.
Whereas if you look at the size of uh
the samples and if you look at what
reasonable estimate of population effect
size is then you see that the
statistical power is only about uh 35%.
So you would expect that um the
probability of rejecting a null
hypothesis is only about 35%.
But still in most of the studies that
are published the null hypothesis is
rejected.
Another
example is uh in the reproducibility
project they found that um
that yeah in a lot of large studies um
significant results were found but um it
was very hard to replicate these uh
significant results. So if other
research groups were trying to do
exactly the same study very often they
did not find a significant result
anymore. So it is possible that in
reality there was no significant
uh there is no effect but in a specific
study a significant effect was found and
this significant effect was uh
uh was submitted to a journal and was
published. Whereas in other studies
maybe no effect was found but these
results were not published or not sent
to a journal. These results
one explanation for these results is
that uh researchers fabricated or
falsified or modified the results in
order to make sure that the results are
statistically significant.
A somewhat less pessimistic
um explanation is that researchers
um are using B hacking which means that
well you know as a researcher you can
you have a lot of freedom in how you
analyze the data. You can include
coariantss or not include coariantss.
You can often do multiple tests. You can
uh uh you can for instance use an
analysis of variance, but you can also
use uh regression analysis.
And maybe the results or the conclusion
will depend slightly on what type of
analysis you did. And it is possible
that some researchers or it is practice
that some researchers are doing multiple
analysis and only report the results of
analysis that show significant results
and fail to send or report uh the
non-significant results to a journal. So
this is what is called P hacking. So
people are looking for significant
results by doing a lot of analysis and
only selecting significant results.
So to illustrate that this problem of
publication bias
is a real problem and to illustrate
where it could come from here. Um yeah
part of a letter that we received from
an editor of a chi scientific journal to
which we submitted a paper reporting on
a study we have done.
So when we do a study and we write a
paper, we send that paper to an editor
of a journal. That editor often reads
the paper and then decides um to send
that paper out to several experts
throughout the world uh to ask the
opinion of these experts on whether this
paper can be published or not. Very
often experts will give comments, will
give suggestions to improve the paper
and then uh the authors revise the paper
and submit it again after which maybe
the paper will be accepted for
publication. So, but here we sent our
paper to a journal and the editor mailed
back to us and he said, "Well, I have
decided not to send out your manuscript
for full review because the effects you
were you found are very small in
magnitude and so this could be
interpreted as relatively trivial by
readers.
We replied to the editor that this is
exactly the problem
or this is exactly the process that may
lead to publication buys. If only
spectacular effects will be published
and small effects are looked at or are
considered as trivial and therefore not
published. Then we get a biased view
because as we have seen in our
simulation study and in the other
studies you can expect that if there is
a population effect that sometimes your
observed effect will be smaller
sometimes it will be larger. So if we if
we if we submit and if we publish only
the largest effects then we we will get
an overestimate of our population effect
size when we calculate the mean effect
that we find in the literature. But of
course the editor did not reply anymore.
Um fortunately we sent it to another
journal and our paper was was published
in the other journal.
a very similar experience um which is
much more recent
um so again we submitted the paper to a
journal
and the editor said um yeah I'm not
going to publish this paper there are
some issues with that problem with that
paper but if your findings had been
particularly large or striking then
having only measured engagement once a
year might not have been a concern.
So again based on the size of the effect
the editor made a decision.
So again
this is
disappointing. This is um the underlying
process of publication bias.
So to summarize, there is no reason why
an effect size that is not statistically
significant is less interesting as an
effect that is not that is statistically
significant. On the contrary, if in
reality there is no effect, then I want
to know that there is no effect. There
is a problem that in the situation in
the scenario where there is no effect
but sometimes by coincidence a study
finds a an effect and only these studies
are published. In that way people will
think that there is an effect.
So it's equally important to publish
non-significant effects.
But of course if there is if you do not
find a significant effect this can also
be due to other reasons which may be
good reasons for not publishing your
results. For instance it's possible that
uh you have a very very underpowered
study. So you have a very small study
and therefore um your results are very
inaccurate. Your estimate is very
inaccurate imprecise.
uh the statistical power is very small
and therefore the probability of finding
a statistically significant effect is
very small.
It's also possible that you are looking
at an hypothesis that simply does not
make sense. For instance, if you would
do a study studying whether drinking one
glass of water water each morning after
two years will lead to larger ears.
Why would you expect such an uh such an
association? If you do not have reasons
to expect such an association, then it
also does not make sense to study this
association
and it may not be worthwhile to publish
these kinds of studies.
Or it's possible that your treatment
that you are study studying is not uh
implemented in a good way and that this
is the reason why you do not find an
effect of this treatment. So there can
be reasons why studies should not be
published
but there is a problem if a study of
high quality is not published because
the results are statistically not
significant.
to illustrate citation bias. Um well, we
have done um a meta analysis uh yeah
several years ago on the effects of
early prevention programs for families
with young children at risk for physical
child abuse and neglect.
As I look at the distribution of all the
observed effect sizes
so in bold we have our uh mean effect
size with confidence interval. You can
see that the mean effect size was
around30
um which is considered a small effect or
a moderate effect. But there was one
study with an observed effect size that
was very large about 1.2
and it was striking when we were looking
at the literature that that one single
study was cited a lot of times. So very
often it was said that prevention
programs
um are effective and then this single
study was cited.
So because in this single study a large
effect was found uh this study was uh
cited much more.
So again, readers of the literature can
get a biased view
because this is the study that receives
a lot of attention and therefore people
may think that the effect indeed is very
large. But the reality it seems that the
effect is much smaller than the effect
found in that single study. And probably
this
it may be due to coincidence that in
that study such a large effect was
found.
In coming videos we will see that there
are some techniques that can be used to
detect bias and to correct for bias.
Unfortunately these techniques do not
always work well. For instance the type
one erate may not be under control and
the power may be low.
Therefore, it is better to avoid bias.
To that end, you can try to find also
unpublished literature, also called gray
literature.
For instance, by making use of databases
that are exactly developed with that
goal.
You can also contact research groups
that are active in the domain to ask
whether they have done other studies
that were not published and if so, if
they're willing to share the results.
And of course, it's important that you
try to avoid bias in your own research.
Therefore, report all findings regarding
your research interest or questions
regardless of their significance.