In this video, I will show how you can
analyze a meta analytic data set using
R.
I will demonstrate the use of R for meta
analysis uh by this example. So we have
discussed this example during the
workshop. This is a data set that was
collected by Steve Rodenbush.
um a data set consisting of 19 studies
evaluating the teacher expectancy
effect.
In all these studies, the teacher was
told by the researcher that some
students were relatively strong students
and other students were relatively weak
students without there being a real
difference between these two groups of
students. And then after a certain
period of time it was assessed whether
the teacher gave higher scores to the
so-called strong students.
So in these studies um it was evaluated
whether the expectancies that teachers
have about their students affect their
uh scores their gradings of these
students.
In this table you can see the results of
these 19 studies. So the column G refers
to the standardized mean difference with
a positive G referring to an an effect
going in the direction that was
expected. So a positive G means that
students that were called strong
students indeed got higher grades than
uh students called weaker students. In
the last column, you can see the
standard error or the standard deviation
of a sampling distribution of the effect
size.
As rule of thumb, if G is at least twice
as large as its standard error, then
this means that this observed effect
size is statistically significant at the
0.05 05 significance level which is not
often case as you can see in this this
set this set of 19 studies.
Let's analyze this data.
You can install R and you can install R
studio on your own computer by
downloading uh these programs for free
uh from these websites. So we are going
to use R studio. If you installed RNR
studio and you open studio then you get
this window
on the left side in the the left upper
corner you can you get uh a script which
is empty for now. You can type in
commands in this script and save these
commands so that you can use these
commands afterwards in the next session.
If you type in a command and your cursor
is in that line and you push on controll
enter then this command will be
automatically copied to the window below
the so-called console
and this command will be executed and
you will see or sometimes you will see
output in this console.
I have already prepared an R script for
you with all the commands that we are
going to use to analyze the data set
crowd bush with a uh the 19 step.
You can open the R script. You can find
the R script on Toledo under course
documents software R.
So please um save this R script on your
own computer and then open it in R by
using file open file and so on.
Next
we are going to make use of the package
metaphor.
A lot of people prepared packages.
packages that are meant to do specific
analysis.
We are going to use the package
metaphor, a package that was developed
by Holang Vikpower from the University
of Mr. to perform meta analysis.
To use this or to install this package,
you click on packages, then you click on
install. You type in the name of the
package metaphor
and you install that package.
Once you have installed a package, you
have to tell R that you want to use this
package.
So you can do this um by typing the
command library
metaphor. You can see this command in uh
the R studio script Renbush.
So you go with your cursor on that line
and you push controll enter.
So in that way you will see that uh the
li the metaphor package is loaded. So it
is ready for use. Now
you have to install a package only once.
So once you have installed the package
you can use it in next sessions as well.
But for each session in which you want
to use the package metaphor, you have to
reload the package metaphor. So you have
to execute again the line library
metaphor.
Next, I also prepared a data set
including the data
um a data set called Renom Bush. It's an
an Excel file. You can find this Excel
file as well on Toledo under course
documents software R. So go to or or
save that uh Excel sheet on your own
computer and then import data set in R
studio by clicking on import data set
next from Excel and so on. You open the
data set. So you you import the data set
and by importing the data set you
immediately see how the data set set
looks like. So you have four columns. A
column with a study number, a column
with a weeks of prior contact. I will
talk more about that later. A column
with a standardized mean differences and
a column with the standard errors. Now
what we need to perform a meta analysis
using the metaphor package is at least
two columns. We need a column with the
effect sizes. So here column G. But we
also need a column with the sampling
variances. So the variance of the
sampling distribution of the effect
sizes. We do not have that column here.
But what we have instead here is the
standard error which is the square root
of the sampling variance. So in the next
step we are going to make a new variable
variable with a sampling variances and
this new variable should be equal to the
squared standard errors.
So this is what is done in the next
lines um included in the R script. So
routen bush dollar sign var refers to a
new variable to be created a variable
called var
which is part of the data set which will
be part of the data set bush
and this new variable is equal to and
you can see that in r we also uh
sometimes write um an arrow instead of
an equal sign. So the new variable var
in the data set Ren bush is equal to the
variable standard error from the data
set Ren bush squared. So the head two
means squared
by exe line you see that in the data set
automatically a new variable is added.
So now we are ready to analyze or met
analyze the data set.
Let's look at the first analysis. So I
use the command RMA which is a function
within the package metaphor.
The analysis should be done on the
dependent variable G. So that's a
variable including the um the v the the
effect sizes.
A var refers to the sampling variances.
The data can be found in a data set
called trrowen bush.
The method we are going to use in this
first analysis is the fixed effects
method.
So we are going to use a fixed effects
model assuming that the population
effect size is exactly the same in all
19 studies.
And this analysis
I am going to give a name to this
analysis. More specifically I'm going to
give it the name FEM fixed effects
model. So FEM is a name I gave myself to
this analysis.
By running this line, the analysis will
be done. But you will not immediately
see output. To see the output, you can
also execute the line summary and then
between parenthesis FM. If you do so,
you get uh for instance this output. You
can see that the estimate which refers
to the estimate of the overall
population effect size, the estimate is
equal to 0.06.
Think back of the guidelines of Cohen.
Cohen set well standardized mean
difference of 20 can be called a small
effect 50 a moderate effect and 80 a
large effect. So this means that on
average the effect seems to be very very
small. You also get the standard error
of these estimates. Dividing the
estimate by the standard error gives us
a value of 1.65.
You can can compare this value to a
standard normal distribution to assess
the statistical significance.
When testing the null hypothesis that
the effect is equal to zero, this ratio
of estimate divided by the standard
error will follow a standard normal
distribution. So you get a value of 1.65
which is not very very large. Um so you
have a probability of almost 10% to
obtain
a ZV valueue that is even farther away
from zero if the null hypothesis is
true. So we conclude this p value is not
very small. So this result is
statistically not significant. Um so on
average we do not have enough evidence
to say that there is a teacher
expectancy effect.
You also get a confidence interval a 95%
confidence interval with uh limits uh
equal to minus.01
and plus.13.
So you see that zero is included in the
confidence interval confirming again
that zero can be possibly uh the real
population value so that we doubt or or
that we do not have enough evidence to
reject the null hypothesis. So on
average we do not see really see
an effect a teacher expectancy effect
by typing forest and then between the
parentheses is the name of the analysis
you get a forest plot for this fixed
effects model analysis.
Um so you get for each of the 19 studies
a confidence interval around the
observed effect size. Um you can see
that in most of the studies zero is
included in the confidence interval. So
in most of the studies we do not really
have evidence for uh a teacher
expectancy effect if you take all
evidence together you get a mean effect
of 0.06 but with a confidence interval
that includes zero. So again this says
we do not have really convincing
evidence of a teacher expectancy if
but
as we have seen during the workshop very
often there are a lot of differences
between studies. There can be
differences in the kind of participants
in the study context in the outcome
variable in the way the independent
variable or the treatment is
operationalized
in the design and so on. So there can be
a lot of differences between studies.
Probably here there are as well some
differences between the 19 studies. And
it is maybe unlikely that none of these
differences
affect
the
size of the effect. So maybe the
assumption that we made when using a
fixed effects model, the assumption that
all population effect sizes for all 19
studies are exactly the same. Maybe this
assumption is not real.
Maybe each study has its own population
effect size. So maybe there is a a
distribution of population effect sizes.
So this would mean that now we say well
maybe there are two sources of
variation. On top of the sampling
variation, there is also variation
between the true effect sizes, between
the population effect sizes.
You can test this hypothesis. This
hypothesis that all population effect
sizes are exactly the same. So the
hypothesis of homogeneity.
The alternative hypothesis is that not
all population effect sizes are the
same. So that at least one population
effect size differs from at least at
least one other population effect size.
We have seen how we can test this. We
can use a Q statistic
which is a kind of weighted
uh sum of squares.
And if the null hypothesis is correct
then this Q statistic follows a k square
distribution with degrees of freedom
equal to uh the number of studies minus
one.
In fact, when we did the analysis in R,
um the result of this statistical
analysis is also included in the output.
You can see that the Q uh statistic is
has a value equal to 35.83
with uh 18 degrees of freedom. This
gives us a p value that is very small. P
value equal to 0.0074.
So based on this homogeneity test, yeah,
we are likely to going to reject the
null hypothesis and we are going to
conclude that there is systematic
heterogeneity that there is variance
between population effect sizes. So that
it is not a good idea to use a fixed
effects model.
Maybe it's a better idea to use a random
effects model. a random effects model
that assumes that population effect
sizes that can differ from each other
and more specifically that there is a
normal distribution of population effect
sizes.
So when using such a random effects
model we are going to estimate the mean
of this red distribution. So the mean
population effect size as well as the
variation between the population effect
sizes.
You can see that commands uh look very
similar as when using a fixed effects
model but instead now we say method is
equal to raml. Raml stands for
restricted maximum likelihood and that's
one way to estimate um the between study
variance.
Now in the output you can see that you
get uh somewhat similar output but on
top of that you also get an estimate of
the of to squared which refers to uh the
estimate of the variance between
population effect sizes.
So the variance between population
effect sizes is estimated to be equal to
0.019
with a standard error of 0.050.
You also get I squared. I squar refers
to the proportion of the variance of the
total variance
that is due to
variance between population effect
sizes.
So about 42% of the total variance and
the total variance is equal to the
population uh the variance in population
effect sizes plus the sampling variance.
So about 42% of this variance is
variance between population effect sizes
and so about 58% is sampling variance.
So this um yeah proportion is relatively
large. So again it's an indication that
yeah maybe it was not a good idea to use
a fixed effects model and it may be
better to use a random effects model.
But then if you look at the the results
or the estimate
uh which is the estimate of the mean
population effect size you can see that
this effect size is rather similar than
uh the estimate we have seen before. Now
it is 0.08 with a standard error of
0.05. Again the z value is not that
large. It is 1.62 which gives a p value
again close to 10.
So again the conclusion is we do not
have really enough evidence to conclude
that there is on average a teacher
expectancy effect.
So in this forest plot you can see that
that I made uh in Excel. You can see um
confidence intervals for each individual
study but also the result of the fixed
effects model and the results of the
analysis using a random effects model.
But there is an additional column in the
data set weeks of prior contact. In some
of the studies,
the teacher did not know the students
before the start of the study. And you
can imagine that in these studies,
maybe the induced teacher expectancy
effect better succeeded. So it it was
easier for researchers to convince
teachers that indeed some of these
students were stronger than some other
students.
Whereas if students were already known
for several weeks by the teacher
probably the effect that the that the
researcher has on the teacher expectancy
will be smaller. So the teacher will not
be convinced when the researcher is
saying these and these students are
strong students and these and these
students are weaker students.
So you could expect that if teachers are
influenced by their expecties
that this will be most um clearly
visible in studies in which there was no
prior contact between teachers and
students. So when the weeks of prior
contact was equal to zero rather than
one, two or three and by the way three
means three weeks or more than three
weeks of prior contact.
In this plot I ordered the effect sizes
according to the weeks of prior contact.
And indeed you can see that
by visual inspection that when there was
no prior contact the effect was not that
small. It was positive. With one week of
prior contact, the effect on in on
average is somewhat smaller. After two
weeks, it is still somewhat smaller and
after 3 weeks, it is about zero or even
slightly negative.
Let's do another meta analysis including
the weeks of prior contact as a
moderator variable. So in the first
model we use the weeks of prior contact
as a categorical moderator and we assume
that within categories so within
studies with zero weeks of prior contact
or within a category with one week of
prior contact and so on there are no
differences between population effect
sizes. So therefore we still call this
model a fixed effects model but this
time with a categorical moderator.
So within categories we assume that
population effect sizes are the same but
possibly there are differences between
the between the categories.
We can also fit a model a random effects
model with a categorical moderator. In
this situation, we say well there can be
differences between categories but on
top of that within categories there can
still be differences between population
effect sizes.
So now in fact we have three sources of
variation. We have the variation due to
the category.
We have variation due to differences
between population effect sizes within
categories. And a third source of
variation is the sampling variation.
Population effect size for a specific
study is not a exact not necessarily
um be equal to the observed effect size
in that study because in that study only
a sample was used. Take into account um
the number of weeks of prior contact.
There are no differences anymore. There
is no heterogenity.
when using random effects model. Well,
first look at the estimates. You get
exactly the same estimates as before.
Why is this? Well, this is because and
this you can see on top because the
estimated to squar is equal to zero.
So indeed there are no differences
anymore within categories. We explained
all variance between population effect
sizes and therefore the fixed effects
model with the categorical moderator
gives us exactly the same results as the
random effects model with a categorical
moderator.
By the way, this is not a very common
situation. Very often when we include a
moderator or even when we include
multiple moderators
we succeed in explaining part of the
variance but it is very unlikely that we
will explain all variance.
So typically to squar is still somewhat
larger than zero. We hope that we can
explain as much as possible but it is
seldomly the case that we explain
everything. So here everything is
explained R squar is equal to 100%.
As you can see in the output
we can also include uh weeks of prior
contact as a continuous moderator
variable. So the advantage so and
perform a kind of regression analysis.
The advantage is that now um yeah we
only have two parameters to estimate. we
have to estimate the intercept as well
as the slope of the regression line.
Whereas before
when we use weeks of prior contact as a
categorical variable, we had to estimate
four parameters. We had to estimate the
intercept. So the expected effect in the
reference category as well as um yeah
the contrast between the three other
categories compared to the reference
category. So this is a more yeah it's a
simpler model but a drawback of this
model is that maybe this model is not
very realistic. Maybe the trend is not a
linear trend but as you can see in this
scatter plot the trend looks indeed more
or less linear. So it's not such a bad
idea to use a regression model in this
sit.
The syntax looks very similar as before,
but this time we do not say that weeks
is a categorical variable. So we do not
say that it is a factor. We simply write
mods is equal to weeks.
You can see the intercept of 41
which is the expected standardized mean
difference if there was no prior
contact. So if the weeks of prior
contact is equal to zero. If there was
one week of prior contact the expected
effect is decreasing with 16. So after
one week the expected effect is 41 minus
16. After 2 weeks the expected effect is
41 minus 2 * 16 and so on.
So you have a negative slope.
You can al also use random effects model
with a continuous moderator. But now
again the the results are exactly the
same as before. And why is this? This is
because the to squar estimate is equal
to zero. So it seems that we explained
all variation between population effect
sizes by including weeks as a continuous
variable. So there is no residual
variance no population no variance
anymore between population effect sizes
after accounting for the weeks of prior
contact. So the random effects model
simplifies or reduces to a fixed effects
model.
So we have discussed six models.
Fixed effects models and random effects
models without moderators with weeks of
prior contact as a categorical moderator
or with weeks of prior contact as a
continuous moderator.
And in these analysis, yeah, we have
answered the basic or the
yeah the most common metalic questions.
Is there an overall effect? How large is
the effect? Is the effect the same in
all studies? So, is there an overall
effect? No, apparently not. We do not
have enough evidence that on average
there is an effect. How large is the
effect? We estimated size of the effect
when using random effects model. 08. Is
the effect the same in all studies? No,
apparently not. Our homogeneity test
concluded that there are systematic
differences between population effect
sizes. So it's not a good idea to use a
fixed effects model without moderators.
Uh so it's a better idea to use a random
effects model. But when using a random
effects model without moderators, you
simply can estimate the variance between
population effect sizes. But it's a good
idea to try to explain this variation.
By the way, we found and this is the
fourth question, we found that the
variation between studies was about
0.09.
And finally, when we try to explain this
variation, we found that um if we
include weeks of prior contacts as a
categorical variable or as a continuous
variable,
we found that this variable indeed
moderated the size of the effect. So the
size of the effect depends of the on the
weeks of prior contact. So the more
prior contact there was the smaller the
size of the effect that was found in the
studies
and we even uh yeah managed to um
explain 100% of the between study
heterogenity.
Final remark. As explained in one of the
videos, it is good idea to do some
checks to assess the credibility of your
results.
First, it is good to check whether there
is evidence for publication buys.
By typing funnel with the name of your
analysis, you get a funnel plot. The
plot suggests that there may be
publication buys.
Without publication buys, you would
expect a symmetric plot with on top of
the plot. This is for larger studies.
Less variation than at the bottom of the
plot. This is for smaller studies, but
with observed effect sizes varying
around the same value regardless of the
sample size.
Here however we see that for small
studies the observed effect sizes are
generally larger which indicates that
small studies with small effect sizes or
even negative effect sizes are missing
in our metalytic data set
on to you will also find the R codes for
making a period plot to calculate a rank
correlation perform a regression test
and apply the trim and fill method to
correct for bias.
In the same script, you can see how you
can make several plots to detect outline
and influential studies. For instance,
by replacing the dots by numbers in the
final plot, you see that studies four
and 10 are relatively outlying.
This is confirmed in plots with a
standardized residuals, the cook's
distances and the co-variance ratios.
Leaving out these two studies, study
four and study 10 also gives a somewhat
different results.
Also reflect on the assumptions that are
made. It is probably a good idea to make
a QQ plot as well. Here the distribution
looks reasonably normal.