network meta analysis.
When we talked about meta analysis of
standardized mean differences, we
assumed that all studies in our meta
analysis are comparing one treatment
with control condition.
Although it is possible that there are
small differences between studies in the
treatment and you can include treatment
characteristics as moderator variables
in your analysis.
We still assumed that there is one
general type of treatment that is uh
evaluated in all of the studies.
Sometimes however
the same problem can be treated in
multiple ways. For instance, in the
study of Linda, they distinguished 23
approaches to treat depression
and different studies can study or can
evaluate different treatments. It is
even possible that within the same study
different treatments are evaluated.
It is also possible that in some studies
a treatment is not immediately compared
with a control condition but that rather
treatments are directly compared to each
other.
In the study of Linda, they collected
the data of a lot of studies and
um you can see in the plot on the left
side of the of the slide
that uh the nodes refer to the 20 23
treatments of depression
and you can see that some of these nodes
are connected. This means that these um
nodes or these treatments are directly
compared. The thicker the connection,
the more that connection has been
studied.
So you see that some of the treatments
were uh immediately or were directly
compared to each other.
But uh most of the treatments are
compared to placebo condition or a usual
care uh condition.
Note that not all treatments are
immediately compared to each other.
It is indeed very often the case that
um studies compare a treatment with a
control condition or a placebo
condition. And this can make that if we
make a similar plot which is called a
network graph that we get a pattern like
the right hand side uh graph which is
called a starshaped network graph.
In this graph you can see that there are
multiple treatments but all of these
treatments are compared to one control
condition only. So the treatments are
never compared directly with each other.
These types of data can be combined in a
network meta analysis.
So in a network meta analysis we can
combine the results of multiple studies
that not necessarily uh studied the same
treatment.
So in total multiple treatments are
analyzed
possibly um within a primary study also
multiple treatments can be studied.
interesting in section network meta
analysis is that based on the results we
can rank the treatments from more
effective to less effective. And so in
that way we can compare treatments
even if these treatments were not or
were never uh studied uh or compared
directly in primary studies. So if you
have a starshaped
uh network plot even in that situation
you can rank as um treatments from less
to more effective.
How does it work? Well suppose that in
one study treatment A has been compared
to treatment B and suppose the
standardized mean difference is 04. So
this means that treatment A looks more
effective than treatment B.
In another study, treatment B was
compared to treatment C
and the observed standardized mean
difference was uh 0.3
which means that treatment B was found
more effective than treatment C.
So the uh the network graph would look
like this. So you have a treatment B
that has been compared to treatment A as
well as to treatment C. But A and C
never have has been or have been
compared directly. But still if you know
that treatment A was more effective than
treatment B and B is more effective than
treatment C then you can assume that
treatment A will be more effective than
treatment C.
So the difference between A and B is
0.4.
A is more effective than B. The
standardized mean difference is 04.
Standardized mean difference between uh
treatment C and B is.3.
So that means that the difference
between C and A is.7
or the estimated difference between C
and A is.7.
So the difference between the means
standardized by standard deviation is
equal to.7.
So you see that although
uh treatment A and C never has been
studied or compared directly based on
the results of these studies, we can
give an estimate of the standardized
mean difference or the the treatment
effectiveness. Um
we can compare the treatment
effectiveness of both treatments. Um at
least of course we have to make an
assumption. we make the assumption of
transitivity. So that if A is more
effective than B, B is more effective
than C, then we conclude that A is also
more effective than C.
And more specifically, the standardized
mean difference between A and C is equal
to the standardized mean difference
between A and B plus the standardized
mean difference between B and C.
If we have two independent studies, so
then the observed effect sizes are also
independent of each other. And therefore
the variance of the sum of the two
standardized mean differences is equal
to the sum of the two variances.
We have seen how we can calculate the
the sampling variance of a standardized
mean difference. So based on that
formula we can also calculate the
variance of the sum of these two
observed effect sizes.
So we call this indirect evidence.
But sometimes there are also studies
available that directly compare
treatment A and C. And so now we have a
closed
um closed loop. So A is connected to B,
B with C, but also A is connected with
C.
In this situation,
we have two kinds of evidence. We have
the indirect comparison of A and C uh by
combining the results of study one and
two. But we have also direct evidence uh
by looking at results of study three.
And so in the network meta analysis we
can combine the two types of evidence
direct and indirect evidence.
Why is this a good idea? Well,
if we would only look direct evidence
to say something about uh A versus C,
then we could use only the data from
study three.
If we also use the indirect evidence,
then we also use data or evidence from
study one and study two. So, by
combining the direct and the indirect
evidence, we use more data. As a result,
the precision of the estimate of the
effect or the difference between A and C
will be higher. So the standard error
will be smaller. So the confidence
interval will be smaller and the
statistical power will be higher.
A second advantage of using indirect
evidence as well is that in this way we
can also compare treatments that have
not been compared before in a direct
way. So look again at the graph uh on
this plot on on this slide. You can see
that yeah a lot of treatments have been
compared to a no treatment condition or
to an alarm condition but
uh now not a lot of pairs of treatments
have been compared directly. So if you
want to say something about whether
psychological therapy or the use of uh
the medication immina,
which of the two treatments of um
noctural and uras is more effective? We
only can use indirect evidence
now. So if we have an open network
like in the plot here, we can use the
results of a meta analysis on AB studies
and a meta analysis of BC studies to
obtain an indirect evidence of A versus
C.
Sometimes we have closed networks. So we
do not have only indirect evidence but
we also have direct evidence.
So we can calculate a weighted average
of the indirect estimate
from
um yeah comparing the results of the uh
meta analysis of AB studies and the meta
analysis of BC studies. We can compare
or we can combine that uh result with
direct estimates from a meta analysis of
the AC studies. So in that way we get an
estimate that is a mix of an in of
indirect and direct evidence and
therefore we also talk about a mixed
estimate.
Note that in the two cases we make the
assumption of transitivity.
Without that assumption of transitivity,
we cannot uh obtain an indirect estimate
and therefore also not a mixed estimate.
But does it make sense this transitivity
assumption? Well, the answer is
sometimes it does. In other situations
it does not. Look at this situation or
this example. Suppose in one specific
study a BMW was found to be much faster
than the Range Rover.
In a second study it was found that the
Range Rover is much faster than a
Porsche.
So can you then conclude
that the BMW is faster than a Porsche?
Well, I guess you can see that this is
that this does not make sense.
The issue is here that in the first
study a very old Range Rover was used.
So of course the BMW is much faster than
that that Range Rover.
In the second study in which the Range
Rover was the winner, the Range Rover
was a very new Range Rover and moreover
it was tested in very muddy conditions
in conditions in which a Porsche is not
expected to perform well.
So of course the Range Rover will win in
that situation.
So you can see that the it's it's yeah
the Range Rover in the first study was
completely different Range Rover than
Range Rover in the second study and it
was also tested in completely different
conditions.
So therefore we cannot use a
transitivity assumption. We cannot
predict that indeed a BMW will be much
faster than a Porsche on a highway for
instance.
So this transitivity assumption
assumes that treatment B
is doing equally good in the AB
comparison studies compared to the BC
comparison studies
which is definitely not the case in the
example on the previous slide. So, the
Range Rover
was not doing equally good when being
compared to the the Porsche than when
being compared to the BMW because it was
an older
um or or in comparison with the Porsche.
It was a newer version of Range Rover
and it was tested in a condition for
which a Range Rover was made.
So in general we can uh think about
effect modifiers that are all kinds of
characteristics of studies that can have
an influence on the performance of a
specific treatment. So for instance
participant characteristics, study
characteristics, treatment
characteristics
um
and so on. And so the assumption
underlying the transitivity assumption
is that these effect modifiers
are distributed similarly in studies in
which A is compared to B compared to
studies in which B is compared to C.
So I think the the example of the cars
is
straightforward but this can also happen
in meta analysis of drugs for instance.
So there would be a problem if a new
drug
um is studied
in studies uh with patients for which we
know that the traditional treatments uh
will probably not work. So if that new
drug is used on patients for which we
know okay there is no other choice that
the traditional treatment work does not
work so let's try out a new drug
and if in other studies the traditional
treatment is compared to uh another drug
but in these other studies traditional
treatments are also applied on patients
for which possibly these traditional
treatments work.
So in that situation, comparing the new
drug with um the other drug will not be
a fair comparison
because the transitivity assumption
cannot be made or I mean an indirect
comparison of the new drug and the other
drug is not fair.
An issue is that that assumption of
transitivity cannot be tested
statistically.
But what we can do is we can ask experts
to have a look at the different studies
and to evaluate whether these potential
effect modifiers are indeed equally
distributed across these different
designs or across these different types
of studies. studies comparing A with B
and studies comparing B with C.
So the idea is that these studies should
be comparable so that we can expect that
treatment B will perform equally good in
the first type of studies compared to
the second type type of studies.
The violation of the transitivity
assumption can however lead to
inconsistencies in the data.
I mean
if you have a closed loop so not uh in
the graph that I show here here we do
not have a closed loop. So A is compared
with B b with C but A and C are not
directly compared.
So we can uh get an estimate an indirect
estimate of the effect uh of A versus C
but there is no other evidence. So there
cannot be inconsistencies in the data.
But suppose we have a closed loop like
here. Then we can uh get an indirect
estimate of the effect of a versus c.
And we can compare that indirect uh
evidence with direct evidence of um a
versus c. And so we can look at whether
these two estimates are in line with
each other. This is also the case in
this graph. So A and C can be compared
indirectly via B but they can also be
compared indirectly via D. So we have
two different uh ways in which we can um
estimate an indirect
um treatment effect or we can indirectly
estimate the treatment effect of A
versus C. And we can compare these two
indirect estimates.
So if there would be a violation of the
assumption of transitivity then it is
possible that this is shown in
inconsistencies in the data. So that the
different estimates of the treatment
effect of A versus C are not in line
with each other. And we can also test
these inconsistencies.
So what is an inconsistency? Well, here
we have an example where we have three
studies. A is compared with B, B with C
leading to an indirect uh treatment
effect estimate of 7 and suppose that in
study three uh ASC are compared directly
and an observed effect size of.9 was
found. So we have a direct estimate and
an indirect estimate and we can compare
the two. So we can evaluate whether
these are more or less in line with each
other. Of course you can see here that
these two values are not exactly the
same. This does not necessarily mean
that there is inconsistency that the
transitivity assumption is not correct.
We know that there is always uh yeah
sampling variation within studies. So
the result that we obtain the observed
effect size we obtain in a specific
study is not necessarily exactly equal
to the population effect size. There's
the issue of sampling variation that we
have seen before. So that can be an
explanation why the 0.9 and 7 are not
exactly the same.
Another explanation is that different
studies
they
um often differ in a lot of aspects and
so there is heterogeneity between
studies in in uh in how studies are set
up and so on. And also these
effects or this heterogeneity can
possibly explain why. So again by
coincidence in study three a slightly
different estimate was obtained than uh
the indirect estimate.
A third reason is of course that there
is real inconsistency
that in studies in which A is compared
to C
that in these kinds of studies while
conditions are different compared to
conditions in which A is compared to B
or B is compared to C and that this
makes that transitivity assumption does
not make sense and that Um yeah there
are systematic differences between the
direct and the indirect
um estimates.
There can also be inconsistencies when
we have multiple indirect estimates. So
here for instance stud three and four
are comparing a with b d and d with c.
So based on that information we can get
an indirect estimate of a versus c.
So how can you check transitivity or
consistency? Well, a first way is to
check the distribution of the effect
modifiers over types of studies.
So we want to know whether in general
when BMWs and um Range Rovers are
compared to each other, the conditions
are different than when Range Rovers are
compared with Porsches.
We can also test an inconsistency
factor. So we can uh test the difference
between a direct and an indirect
estimate. So this was proposed by Bher.
The glazer and approach is somewhat more
complex. So it can be used to test
consistency when you have multiple
estimates. So it's possible that for
instance you have one direct estimate
and two indirect estimates.
But it's also possible to estimate and
test uh model inconsistency in general
across all types of um yeah across all
pairs of treatments.
For instance, look at the model of
lumly. So a model that can be used if
you have um standardized mean
differences that's the dependent
variable.
So the dependent variable is the the
mean difference standardized mean
difference um when treatment I is
compared with treatment J
in study K. Well, this mean difference
is defined to be equal to a difference
between the mean the expected value for
treatment I minus the expected value for
treatment J
plus random deviation
that is due to study heterogeneity and
that can have an effect on um yeah the
mean that is um
the the the mean for treatment I in that
study K or the mean the population the
expected value um for treatment J in
study K
and then and this is important there is
an additional term which is a kind of
interaction term for modeling the
inconsistency so it is the additional
effect on the standardized mean
difference when treatment I is compared
to treatment J
and then you have random deviation uh
due to sampling variance.
So in this way by estimating uh the
variance of that um interaction term
we well if there would be no
inconsistency then that variance of that
interaction term would be equal to zero.
And so in this way we can estimate the
amount of inconsistency and we can test
uh whether there is inconsistency.
It's also possible even to include
characteristics
to try to explain this variance in uh
this variance component. So to explain
this inconsistency.
So in practice suppose that you have
five different treatments. Well, you
could uh make use of four dummy
variables. A dummy variable for
treatment two for one for treatment
three, one for treatment four, one for
treatment five. And suppose that one
treatment two is compared to treatment
three. Then you have a one for the dummy
variable x2 and you have a minus one for
the dummy variable x3.
you have an additional column with the
mean differences and so on. And so based
on the use of this model that is shown
uh on the slide with these dummy
variables included, you can estimate um
yeah the means or the expected values
for each of the treatments.
Note that for one treatment you do not
estimate the mean because uh the
dependent variable are mean differences.
So the model would not be defined if you
would try to estimate the mean for each
of the treatments. There is one of the
treatments that should be used as a
reference category otherwise the model
is not identified.
a remark. So you can test inconsistency
by testing the variance component but
this test can be underpowered
for instance when you have a small
number of studies that give direct
evidence or when you have a large
heterogeneity a lot of heterogeneity.
So in these situations it is possible
that in fact there is inconsistency but
that based on your analysis you are not
able to confirm the existence of
inconsistency.
So you cannot consider a non-significant
test of inconsistency as a proof that
there is no inconsistency as a proof of
the transitivity assumption.
Now suppose that you found that there is
inconsistency.
How can can you continue? Well, if you
found inconsistency, so you know that
the transitivity assumption may not
work. So maybe in that situation, it is
safer to use the direct effect estimates
only
rather than uh also including indirect
estimates.
An alternative approach is to try to
explain inconsistency.
So you can look at effect modifiers
uh or you can include effect modifiers
in your model to try to correct for
these effect modifiers and to reduce the
variance um component referring to the
inconsistency.
or you can continue with um your effect
estimates. But then it is important to
take into account the variance referring
to that inconsistency
when um yeah when constructing
confidence intervals uh around the um
the treatment effects
or for testing the treatment effects
because this amount of inconsistency
adds to the uncertainty about the
treatment effects.
Then a final a few final remarks. So how
many treatments can you include in your
network?
So the broader you you make your
network. So the more treatments you
include in your network,
the more interesting your meta analysis
can become because then you compare more
treatments with each other and um yeah
it can be yeah you get more results, you
see better what treatments are more
effective than what other treatments but
at the same time
your analysis is becoming much more
complex and especially you are making
much more comparisons. So the number of
comparisons, the numbers, the number of
pairs of treatments that are compared is
increasing
to to a very large degree by including
additional treatments.
So this makes that you are estimating
much more parameters
and it is possible that at the end um
yeah you do not get stable estimates
anymore of the different treatment
effects.
The suggestion I also want to give is
well if you doubt whether to include an
additional uh treatment you can also do
a sensitivity analysis. We can look at
does the um effect that we estimate um
for comparing A with C does it change
when we do not include only A, B and C
as
treatments in our network but also a
treatment D.
So in that way you can see how stable
your network uh analysis
uh results are.
And if you can see that results are not
very stable, then it is important to be
transparent about it and also warn uh
the the reader of your paper that
results are not very stable or you can
simplify your model and exclude some of
the treatments to make the results more
stable.
A second remark is that well up to now I
assumed that all studies include only
one effect. So that um for instance uh
each study is comparing one treatment
with a control condition or one
treatment with another treatment. But
sometimes
um in one and the same study multiple
treatments are uh compared directly. So
in that u sense or in that in that
situation we talk about a multi-arm
study.
So such studies will give multiple
effect sizes will give multiple
standardized mean differences and so we
should take into account that these
multiple effect sizes are coming from
the same study and so in that sense that
there they are not independent of each
other or there is some overlap in
information. So we should take into
account that correlation between effect
sizes coming from the same study.
But I'm not going to give more details
about uh the techniques for network meta
analysis.