In the first part of the introduction,
we looked at the principles of meta
analysis. Let's look now at some
examples and alternatives.
First, we look at two examples.
First, an example in education. Let's
look at a meta analysis that was done
already in 1984 by Stephenbush. He did a
study on teacher expectancy effects. In
several experiments, 19 experiments in
total, teachers were told that part of
the students of their class were weak
students. Another part of the students
were called strong students without
there being a real difference between
these two groups of students.
After a while, the researchers looked at
the grades that were given by the
teachers to these students.
The researchers were interested in the
question whether teachers would give
higher grades to the so-called strong
students. If this is the case, this
would be an indication of the expectancy
that teachers had
sorry this would be this would indicate
that the expectancy that teachers had
regarding their students influenced
their scores. This is called a teacher
expectancy effect. In all these
experiments, we had two groups and based
on the data, we can calculate a
standardized mean difference which you
can see in the column called G here. A
positive G refers to an effect in a
direction that was expected in the sense
that teachers are given giving higher
grades to the so-called strong students.
A negative effect size, a negative G,
would mean that the opposite difference
is observed or specifically that
teachers give higher grades to the
so-called weak students, which is
definitely not what you would expect.
Now, if you look at the cheese, then you
can see that often these GS are
positive, but sometimes they're
negative. Further, you can see that in
general, these GS are relatively small.
Remember the guidelines of cone with
0.20 called a small effect, 050 a
moderate effect, and 0.80 a large
effect. Very often, the effect sizes
that were observed were even smaller
than 0.20.
In the last column, you can see the
standard error of these estimates. In
other words, the square root of the
sampling variance. We have seen that for
the standardized mean difference this
variance of the sampling distribution is
about 4 divided by n. There is another
column called weeks of prior contact.
In some studies, there was no prior
contact between teachers and students.
So teachers did not know the students
yet at the start of the study. In other
studies, teachers already knew their
students for one, two, or three weeks
before the study took place.
The value three refers to three weeks or
more than three weeks of prior contact.
Here the results of the meta analysis.
It was found that on average the
observed effect size is equal to 0.084.
Remember the guidelines. This effect can
be called a very small effect and the
corresponding p value is1.
Therefore the effect is statistically
not significant. Conclusion would be
that in general there is no teacher
expectancy effect. Maybe in some studies
the effect was positive and in other
studies negative. But on average the
effect is close to zero and it is
statistically not significantly
different from zero.
But performing a met analysis with a
regression model including the weeks of
prior contact as a predictor gives
interesting results.
The intercept can be interpreted as the
expected effect when there was no prior
contact. So when the prior contact was
equal to zero, the estimate of the
intercept is equal to 0.41.
So if there was no prior contact, this
is a moderate teacher expectancy effect.
Moreover, the p value is very small,
which means that we can conclude that
the effect is really there.
The estimated regression rate of the
number of weeks is minus 0.16.
Which means that with each additional
week of prior contact, the expected
effect decreases with 0.6.
A decrease that is also statistically
significant. This makes sense. It is
indeed hard to make a teacher believe
that one group is smarter than the other
group when there is no difference
between these two groups if the teacher
already knows the students.
A second example, an example from
medical research. Kieran and Chen
performed a meta analysis of some
randomized controlled trials, RCTs,
comparing long course and short course
antibiotic therapy for urinary tract
infections.
The measure that was used is the
relative risk or the risk ratio which is
the probability that the treatment does
not work if a short course antibiotic
therapy was given divided by the
probability that the treatment fails if
a long course antibiotic therapy was
given.
Suppose that the short course therapy is
equally effective
as the long course therapy. then the
probability that the treatment would
fail is equal in both conditions and
then the ratio of the two probabilities
will be more or less equal to one. So
here no effect means that the relative
risk is equal to one. If the ratio is
far from one then this is an indication
that one of the two lengths is more
effective.
An estimate of this relative risk in a
study is the observed risk ratio which
is the ratio of the proportions of
patients in both conditions for which
the treatment failed.
Here the results. Let's look first at
the observed effect sizes given with
dots in the confidence intervals. You
can see that the observed effect sizes
are typically larger than one. But
confidence intervals most often include
one. This means that in most of these
studies, no convincing EV uh difference
between the short course therapy and the
long course therapy was was observed.
And therefore, it was concluded that the
short course therapy is equally
effective as the long course therapy.
only in two out of the 12 studies a zero
was not included in the confidence
interval and therefore the null
hypothesis was rejected. Therefore, it
looks like there is no difference
between the two conditions.
But you get another conclusion if you
combine all these observed effect sizes
in a meta analysis. The weighted average
of all these effect sizes is 1.94,
which means that the risk of failure is
almost twice as large when using a short
course therapy. The 95% confidence
interval from 1.19 to 3.15 does not
include one anymore. So whereas in most
of the individual studies the conclusion
was that we do not see a difference
between the conditions
combining the data gives us convincing
evidence that the short course therapy
is less effective than the long course
therapy. What we see here in this data
set looks very similar to what we have
seen in the simulation. Individual
studies are small making confidence
intervals large and statistical power
small.
But by combining the data the interval
becomes much smaller and the power
higher.
Here are the conclusions of the
researchers. They remark that very often
in individual studies no statistically
significant difference between the two
treatments was found and therefore it
was concluded that the short course
therapy was equally effective.
But they also note that the fact there
was no statistical significance can be
due to the lack of statistical power. By
combining the results over all studies,
we get a risk ratio of 1.94, which means
that the probability that the treatment
will fail is 94% larger if you would use
short course therapy.
These were some examples of met
analysis. What are alternative
procedures?
One procedure that is very often used is
a so-called vote counting procedure. The
idea is very simple. You collect the
data of all studies that already were
done on a specific research question.
You count how many studies found no
effect, how many studies found a
negative effect, and how many studies
found a positive effect.
The category that is largest is the
winner. Therefore, if the majority of
studies did not find an effect, then the
conclusion would be that there is no
effect.
The advantage of this procedure is that
it is a relatively simple procedure.
Everybody can understand this procedure.
Yet, there are some drawbacks and these
drawbacks are clear from what we have
seen before. Think of the last example
we have seen, the example of the meta
analysis of Kieran Chen. It's possible
that the power in individual studies is
low and therefore we can expect that in
a lot of individual studies we will not
find an effect even if in reality there
is an effect. Therefore the power of the
vote counting procedure can be very low.
Moreover, the power will not increase if
you add more small studies to your data
set. On the contrary, it can become even
more unlikely that the majority of
studies will show a significant effect
and therefore the power of the vote
counting procedure can even decrease by
adding additional studies.
Another drawback is that in this
procedure all studies are given the same
weight whereas we have seen that smaller
studies will give less precise
information on the population effect
size and therefore it is better to give
a larger weight to larger studies.
A final drawback is that based on the
vote counting procedure we only give an
answer to the question whether there is
an effect in meta analysis. On the other
hand, we can answer much more questions.
We can also say something about how
large the effect is. We can test whether
the effect size is the same in all
studies. And we can investigate whether
the effect size depends on
characteristics of the studies.
Another alternative procedure is the
combination of p values. For instance,
look at the stufur method. What is the
idea? Well, suppose that the null
hypothesis is true in a specific primary
study. In that case, all one-sided p
values between 0ero and one are equally
likely. For instance, the probability
that we will find the p value smaller
than 0.05 is exactly equal to 0.05 or
the probability that our p value will be
larger than 050 is 50.
Indeed, when the null hypothesis is
true, the p values follow a norm a
uniform distribution with limits zero
and one.
We can normalize the p values by
calculating the z value from a standard
normal distribution that has a
cumulative density corresponding to that
p value.
For instance, suppose you find a p value
of 0.025.
Then you look for the ZV value in a
standard normal distribution for which a
probability that you will find the value
smaller than this value is. 025.
This ZV valueue is minus 1.96.
If the null hypothesis is true, the
resulting ZV values follow a standard
normal distribution.
Now suppose that we have multiple p
values from multiple studies and that in
all these individual studies the null
hypothesis is true. In that case all z
values would follow a standard normal
distribution. The mean z value this is
the sum divided by the number of studies
k therefore will follow a normal
distribution with zero mean and variance
1 over k.
Therefore,
if we divide the sum of the Z values by
the square root of K instead of by K, we
get a standard normal distribution.
If however there is a study or few
studies that show in effect in one
direction, the one-sided P values from
these studies will go in one direction
and hence also the Z values will go in
one direction and our test statistic
will go away from zero. We reject our
null hypothesis if our test statistic is
situated in the tail of the standard
normal distribution.
Again, this procedure has some
advantages and disadvantages.
One advantage is that we can use this
approach whenever we have p values from
multiple studies. Indeed, we can combine
P values even if the if these come from
different statistical tests.
Therefore, the procedure can be used for
instance if some of the P p values come
from non-parametric tests, some come
from analysis of variance and still
others come from t tests for the
difference between means and so on.
Another advantage is that we do not make
assumptions. Of course, maybe in an
individual study, assumptions were made
to obtain the p value from that study.
But when combining the p values, we do
not make additional assumptions anymore
about the distributions.
There are however also drawbacks.
One drawback is that the interpretation
of the results is not straightforward.
The null hypothesis is that in all
individual studies, the null hypothesis
is true.
The alternative hypothesis is that at
least in one of at least one of the null
hypothesis is not correct. If we reject
the null hypothesis, we cannot conclude
that on average there is an effect.
Instead, we have to conclude that in at
least one of the studies there is an
effect. But the procedure will not tell
us in what specific studies there is an
effect.
Moreover, again we cannot answer other
questions like how large is the effect?
Is the effect the same in all studies?
When does the effect show up? And is the
effect related to characteristics of the
studies.