In this screencast we will look at
metaanalytic structural equation
modeling MAM.
First I will give more details about
structural equation modeling SAM and
illustrate SAM with an example. Next I
will tell you more about its extension
to the modeling of data from multiple
studies and again we use an example to
illustrate such a mimm analysis.
First, structural equation modeling.
A SM model combines two kinds of models.
A structural model and a measurement
model. The structural model describes
the relationship between multiple
variables. These variables can be
observed variables like for instance the
length of a person. But it's also
possible to work with latent variables.
These are theoretical variables that
cannot be observed directly.
Examples of latent variables are
motivation or emotional intelligence.
Whereas motivation cannot be observed
directly, it can be derived from
observed behaviors. For instance,
indicators of the motivation of a
student are the number of questions the
student asks during a lecture or the
number of exercises the student makes at
home.
A measurement model is used to link
latent variables to observed variables.
In other words, to clarify based on
which manifest variables one gets
information on latent variables.
Let's look first at structural models or
the structural component of structural
equation models.
Various traditional models like multiple
regression models can be considered as
special cases of structural equation
models. Suppose two predictors X1 and X2
are used to predict the criterion
variable Y and that all three variables
are observed variables. In structural
equation modeling, it's common to
present a model in a graphical way using
a so-called path diagram. Observed
variables are presented with rectangular
boxes.
Here in regression model, the two
predictor variables can have an effect
on the criterion variable.
Single-headed arrows between boxes refer
to causal relationships or in the SAM
model to regression weights. Note that
by default, an intercept is estimated
but not shown in the output of a SAM
analysis.
A circular arrow refers to the variance
of a variable. Double-headed arrows
between boxes refer to covariances.
For the criterion variable Y, part of
the variance is explained by the
predictors. Part of the variance is not
explained. Also, the unexplained
variance therefore is a parameter that
should be estimated.
Structural equation modeling has two
purposes. Estimating the parameters.
here the betas the covariance between
predictors and the residual variance.
The second purpose is to test the fit of
the model. One can fit various models
for instance a multiple regression model
with two predictors and a model with
only one predictor and then compare the
model fit to evaluate whether the
inclusion of the second predictor is
significantly improving the predictions.
If you would standard, if you would use
standardized data, the variances of the
predictors become one. The co-variance
between the predictors then is the
correlation between them. The residual
variance is the proportion of the
variance that is not explained and the
regression weights are standardized
weights.
Another
example of a structural model is an
ANOVA model. The triangle stands for a
constant. Here a constant one. In this
plot, we have two groups with different
regression weights for the constant
referring to the expected values in the
two groups.
The variance of the outcome variable can
be group specific. Although it's also
possible to assume homogeneity which
means that only one variance is to be
estimated.
An advantage of using structural models
is that we can fit more complex models.
For instance, models with intervening or
mediating variables that at the same
time play the role of a predictor and
criterion variable.
In this way, you can fit for instance
models to investigate to what extent the
effect on of X on Y is a direct effect
or an indirect effect via the mediator
variable M.
Now let's look at the second component
of structural equation models, the
measurement model.
As an example of a measurement model,
look at the confirmatory factor analysis
model. Observed variables indicated with
rectangles are supposed to measure
latent factors indicated using ellipses.
The double-headed arrow between the two
factors indicates that the factors can
be correlated. The single-headed arrows
uh from the latent factors to the
observed variables represent regression
weights or factor loadings
to make the model identified. Typically
for each factor, one loading is
constrained to one.
In addition, there are the variance
parameters for the latent and observed
variables. For observed variables, the
variance refers to the variance that is
not explained by the latent factors.
Again, we could fit multiple models. For
instance, this model with two factors
and a model with only one general factor
on which all observed variables load and
compare the model fit in order to choose
the best fitting model.
Some models can combine both structural
and measurement models.
For example, a latent variable L3 can be
requested on two other latent variables
L1 and L2. This is a structural part of
the model.
All three latent variables may be
measured using a set of observed
variables which is modeled in the
measurement part of this SAM model.
An example
as input for a sum analysis you have to
specify a model. This implies that you
specify the measurement part. So you
specify what observed variables load on
what latent variables and you further
have to specify the structural relations
between the variables.
Further indicate what variables can be
correlated and clarify possible
constraints.
For instance, assume you want to do a
multiple regression analysis with two
observed predictor variables X1 and X2
that can be correlated and that are
assumed to have an impact on the
criterion variable Y.
An important remark is that in a SEM
analysis on data from a cross-sectional
observational study, this is a study in
which several variables are measured at
the same time and no variables are
experimentally manipulated.
We can estimate parameters of the model
and compare the model fit of various
models but we do not prove that the
assumed direction of the effects is
correct.
The same analysis can be done on raw
data but it's also possible to use a
coariance or a correlation matrix.
Suppose this is the correlation matrix
you obtained based on 120 observations.
Both predictors X1 and X2 correlate
positively with a criterion variable Y
and there is also a positive correlation
between the two predictors.
This will give the following output.
Note that you can replicate the results
using the R syntax prepared for this
screencast.
Here the output is given in a visual way
with estimates of the variances,
co-variances and regression weights.
Because here correlation matrix is used
as input, the variances of the
predictors are equal to one and the
residual variance refers to the
proportion of variance that is not
explained by the model.
You see that the two predictors explain
19% of the variance. Whereas the
observed variance of Y is equal to one.
The residual variance of Y appears to be
81.
Further you see that the correlation
between the predictors is equal to 50. A
correlation that was already given as
input and the regression weights are
equal to 030
and 0.20.
You can also look at the output in a
table format. If you look at the
standard errors and ZV values, you see
that both coefficients are statistically
significant at the 0.05 significance
level, which means that each predictor
improves the model even if the other
predictor was already included in the
model.
Note that in principle, you can also
test the model fit, but here you use six
values as input to estimate six
parameters. So there are no degrees of
freedom left for testing the model.
The six input var val values are the
three variances of one and the three
correlations. The six parameters that
are estimated are the two regression
weights, the correlation between the
predictors, the two variances equal to
one for the predictors and the residual
variance of y.
After this short introduction in SAM,
let us now look at a metanalytic sum
analysis and at metanalytic sum analysis
or mayam analysis.
In a metalytic sum, we estimate the sum
model parameters using combined
information from multiple studies.
This can be done in two steps. In the
first step, we combine the data from
multiple studies to estimate an overall
correlation matrix. And in the second
step, we do the sum analysis based on
this combined correlation matrix.
Alternatively, a MSM analysis can be
done in one step.
Am analysis combines advantages from met
analysis and from structural equation
modeling. By combining data from
multiple studies like in other meta
analysis, you can increase the
statistical power when testing
hypothesis and the precision when
estimating the parameters of interest.
It also allows estimating and testing
moderating effects of study
characteristics.
MSM also has a flexibility of SAM in
general. You can estimate various kinds
of models with latent and observed
variables.
Here
we will look only at two-stage mason
analysis. In the first stage, we combine
the correlations from multiple studies
to obtain an overall correlation matrix.
Note that studies can differ in the size
of the sample used and hence in the
precision of their estimates and
therefore observed correlations should
be weighted in the meta analysis.
Note that it is not required that all
studies report on all correlations. If
you want to fit a multiple regression
model with two predictors, you need
estimates of three correlations, but
also studies that report on only one or
two of these correlations can contribute
information to the meta analysis.
As a result, not all pulled correlations
will have the same precision, which
should be accounted for in the second
stage.
It's also important to note that we will
not do separate univariat math analysis
for the different correlations
because in that way we would not account
for the dependence of correlations from
the same study.
For instance, if in a study the sample
has some atypical values for the
variable X, this will affect both the
correlation between X and Y and the
correlation between X and Z.
Therefore, we do a multivariate meta
analysis and we can use robust variance
estimation or RVE to fully account for
the dependence.
The first stage will result in a
correlation matrix across studies
together with a sampling variance or the
squared standard error of each bullet
correlation.
The sampling variance gives us an idea
of the precision of the estimates but
also the sampling coariances are
estimated which gives us an idea of the
association between correlations within
studies.
In the second stage, the matrix with a
pulled correlations is then used to
estimate the SM model. But in contrast
to an ordinary SE analysis, we are now
also accounting for the matrix with the
corresponding variances and co-variances
of the pulled correlations.
An example of a Mason analysis.
There is discussion in the literature on
whether dehumanizing a group, for
instance, calling a group cockroaches or
rats, can contribute to violence against
that group.
Some people suggest that dehumanization
is strongly related to disliking the
other group and that it is the dislike
that contributes to violence rather than
the dehumanization.
In a recent study, we did a meta
analysis on studies that studied
violence, deumanization, and dislike to
investigate whether there is still an
association between deumanization and
violence after correcting for dislike.
The model we fitted was a multiple
regression model. Violence is regressed
on dislike and dehumanization.
Two predictors that can be correlated.
The regression weights of the two
predictors represent the effect of the
predictor on violence after correcting
for the other predictor.
In the first stage, we did a multivaried
meta analysis applying RVE.
Again the data and R syntax are made
available so that you can replicate this
analysis.
This first stage resulted in a first
matrix with a pulled correlations across
studies. We found that overall violence
is more strongly correlated with
deumanization than with dislike.
We also found as expected that dislike
and deumanization are positively
correlated.
A second matrix is a coariance matrix
because there are three correlations. We
have in the coariance matrix 3 * 3
cells. On the diagonal we have the
sampling variances. You see that the
correlation between dislike and violence
is estimated with less precision than
the two other correlations.
Off the diagonal you have the sampling
covariances. For instance, the positive
uh sampling coariance between the
deumanization violence correlation and
the dislike violence correlation means
that in studies in which a relatively
large deumanization violence correlation
is observed in general also a large a
relatively large dislike violence
correlation is found.
In the second stage, the correlations
are used to fit the same model
parameters.
We found that after correcting for the
effect of dislike,
the effect of dehumanization is still
statistically significant.
To test this coefficient, we calculated
the 95% confidence interval and we
compared the model fit of this model
with a model that constrained the
coefficient of dehumanization to zero.
The opposite is not true. If we account
for the effect of dehumanization, there
is no statistically significant
additional effect of dislike anymore.
Together, the two predictors explain
about 19% of of the variance in the
amount of violence.
We also did a series of sensitivity
analysis in which we corrected for a few
additional predictors.
But we found that results are robust for
all these additional models. We found
that dehumanization is statistically
significantly related to violence even
after accounting for the effect of
dislike.
To conclude,
an important strength of MSAM is its
flexibility. Messa models can include
observed but also latent variables. They
can include multiple levels, multiple
predictors, multiple outcome variables,
mediators, moderators and so on. In
fact, all met analytic models that we
have seen so far can be considered as
special cases of a Mason model. Yet,
Mason is a recently developed approach
that is not fully developed yet. More
research is needed on the possibilities
and the performance of the approach.
Finally, here's some references to the
work of March Chung and Susanna Yak on
Mason.