In this final video, let us look at some
tools that can help you while doing a
meta analysis or systematic review.
Let's first look at some checklists and
guidelines.
We have already seen that there are
various checklists that can be used to
assess the quality of primary studies.
But there are also checklists to
evaluate the quality of systematic
reviews and meta analysis.
These checklists may also help you to
make sure that your review or meta
analysis is of good quality.
Here
is selection from the CASP tool for
assessing the quality of a systematic
review of RCTs.
Questions are asked and for each
question some hints are given.
Another tool is a robes tool related to
the risk of bias tools for primary
studies. This tool is meant to assess
the risk of bias in systematic reviews.
Other checklists were developed to make
sure that your report is complete and
clear. Probably the best known checklist
for reporting is a Prisma checklist. The
checklist includes 27 items regarding
the different parts of the systematic
review report.
Here you see the first 14 items
that can be checked if reported.
And here the remaining 13 items.
Another kind of tools is software for
managing references.
Probably the most commonly used tools
are endnot.
These tools allow you to import the hits
from the database searches. They can
also be used to remove duplicates. You
can also add notes, for instance, on why
you did or did not include this study in
the review. You can also attach files,
for instance, the PDF of the paper, and
you can use the tool for making a
reference list for your report.
There's also software that is
specifically developed for systematic
reviews.
One such tool is a EPI reviewer. This
web based tool can also be used to
manage
the references, but it's also a very
helpful tool for organizing the data
extraction with multiple coders. You can
create codes, divide the papers over
multiple coders, let each coder code the
papers in a web- based form, calculate
intracoder agreement, and so on and so
forth.
Tools like rind and confidence go a step
further by including AI techniques. For
instance, they can be used to highlight
words or text that are likely related to
the components of the PCO model and
hence can make it easier for reviewers
to find the information needed to decide
on inclusion.
Ryan
even can gradually learn the relevance
of studies based on previous decisions
reviewer made about in or exclusion.
The tool elicit even aims to make the
whole screening and data extraction
process automatic which can save huge
amounts of time for the reviewer.
Also, other generative AI tools that are
not specifically developed for
systematic reviews may be helpful.
Complexity AI can give answers to
questions like CHBT but with clear
references to the sources that were
used.
Consensus AI does the same but looks
only in peerreed scientific literature.
It can also judge how much consensus
there is among studies.
Semantic scholar is a tool that can be
used to discover and summarize academic
papers.
The use of AI in systematic reviews and
meta analysis is a very recent field of
research.
First results look promising, but we can
expect that tools and techniques will
evolve quickly in the coming years.
This was the final video. I hope that
what you learned will prove helpful to
you. I wish you good luck and take care.