In this session, we will look at the
effect size calculation.
The calculation of effect sizes is one
of the most important and one of the
most difficult steps in the in the
execution of a meta analysis.
Very often we are combining the results
of several studies that are reported in
the literature and very often the raw
data are not reported.
Instead we calculate effect sizes effect
sizes that summarize uh the results of
these individual studies.
In our meta analysis effect sizes are
the dependent variable. For instance, if
you are doing an analysis of variance or
regression analysis in your meta
analysis, you are going to predict uh
the size of the effect. So the effect
size is a dependent variable in our meta
analysis.
Very often we use a standardized effect
size
because we want to compare the results
over studies.
There are a lot of effect size measures.
We already used before the standardized
mean difference. We also looked already
at the risk ratio. But there are many
other effect size indices.
For instance, the correlation
coefficient, odds ratio, the loss ratio
and so on.
Before we can combine effect sizes in a
meta analysis, we have to make sure that
the same effect size is used for all
studies. So we have to convert the data
or the results to one common measure.
Why do we use effect sizes?
Look at this example. So suppose in a
specific study one tests the difference
in the size of tumors in an experimental
and a control group.
If people see that the p value that is
testing this difference is equal to.11
a lot of persons would conclude no there
is no there is no difference uh in the
size of tumors.
This is however not a correct
conclusion.
So the p value
states so the the relatively large p
value states that there is not enough
evidence against the null hypothesis
to conclude that the null hypothesis is
not true
but this does not mean that the null
hypothesis is true and one um one common
problem in studies is a lack of power.
So it is possible that the p value is
not very small. Not because there is no
effect and maybe the effect that was
observed in the study was also not very
small but rather because
the study was a relatively small study
and so the confidence interval is
relatively large and the confidence
interval therefore includes zero.
So concluding
if we cannot reject the null hypothesis,
concluding that the null hypothesis is
correct is not a good conclusion.
And what about this p value? So suppose
that the p value is very small, smaller
than 0.001.
Very often researchers conclude
there is a large differences difference
in the size of tumors between an
experimental and a control group. Also
this conclusion is not the correct
conclusion.
Suppose that you have a very large study
so that you have two very large groups
large experimental and a large control
group. In that situation, the confidence
interval will be very small. And even if
the difference between uh the the sizes
of the tumors or the mean size and
tumors
is relatively small, still this
difference can be highly significant if
the two experimental and control groups
are very large.
So a very small p value does not
necessarily mean that there is a large
difference in the size of tumors. It can
also mean that we simply have a very
large uh study and therefore we are
highly convinced that there is a
difference
but this does not necessarily mean that
the difference is large.
So these are the two uh misconceptions.
So a failure to reject the null
hypothesis implies that there is no
effect that the null hypothesis is true.
Another common misconception is that a
statistically significant p value
implies a large effect and the larger
the p value the larger the effect.
As I tried to make clear already,
this is not true because the test or the
results of a significance test also
depends on the size of the study.
So look at this formula or this um
this equation presented by Rosenal. He
said well a test statistic is function
of the size of the effect and the size
of the study. To make this more um
concrete,
look at the t value from a two sample t
test.
So the t statistic is calculated by um
calculating the difference between the
sample means. We divide it by the pool
standard deviation multiplied by the
square root of 1 / n + 1 / n c. So, NE
and 1 C uh and C are the sample sizes of
the two groups.
We already looked at the observed effect
size, the observed standardized mean
difference which is defined as a
difference between the sample means
divided by the pulled standard
deviation. So it is clear that there is
a
a strong relationship between the t
statistic and the standardized mean
difference. More specifically the t
statistic is equal to effect
the effect size times 1 / the square
root of 1 / n + 1 / n c. So indeed this
is an illustration of the formula of
rotal. So the t statistic depends on the
effect size as well as on uh the size of
the study.
The larger the study, the larger t, the
larger the effect size, the larger t.
And so this makes that if we have a very
large study, then even for small
standardized mean differences, the t
value can be large. the other way
around. It's possible that um even for
very large effects, observed effect
sizes, the t statistic will not be large
and so the p value will not be uh very
small in case of small sample sizes.
I do not want to say that test
statistics are not important or that
they're not valuable. On the contrary,
they are very valuable. But at the same
time, we do not only want to say
something about whether there is an
effect, but we also want to estimate the
size of the effect. And therefore, more
and more uh journals, but also for
instance the APA publication manual
stresses the importance of also
mentioning reporting effect size
measures.
So the effect size to summarize
expresses the magnitude of the effect or
the relationship between variables and
independently
of the size of the study.
A remark regarding the name effect
sizes.
Effect sizes sometimes express the size
of the effect in experimental and quasy
experimental studies. So in studies in
which u an independent variable a
treatment variable is manipulated.
So for instance in a group comparison
design with an experimental control and
a experimental group and a control group
in which um the treatment is given in
the experimental group and no treatment
or placebo is given in the control group
or in within subject design
in which um one group of subjects
receives multiple treatments. So first
for instance is uh the group is measured
without the treatment and then the
treatment starts and the group is
measured again.
So in these situations it makes sense to
express or to talk about effect sizes
because in this situation it is clear
that if we find a correlation or an
association between the condition
and the outcome variable
then it makes sense to assume that this
association is due to the treatment.
However, the term effect sizes is also
used to refer to assessation measures in
non-experimental studies. For instance,
to compare existing groups.
For instance, we already looked at the
difference between male and female
students in the performance on a
mathematics exam.
An
alternative scenario is where you
express the association between
continuous variable variables. For
instance, you can uh use a correlation
coefficient to express the relationship
between school size and the performance.
Also in this situation, these
association
measures are often called effect sizes.
But here we have to be very prudent.
I mean suppose that um we find that
correlation between school size and
performance is negative in the sense
that in smaller schools students perform
worse
or that's a positive correlation.
Can we talk about an effect? We have to
be very prudent in interpreting this
correlation. It is possible that
it's not because the school is small
that students perform worse. It is
possible for instance that smaller
schools often are found in rural areas
in which um parents have a lower
educational level. It's also possible
that in the these rural areas um there
is
a much less offer of cultural activities
and all these factors can make that
students perform worse. So it's maybe
not due to the fact that the school is
small that students perform worse. It's
possible that uh students perform worse
because the school size is associated
with other variables and that are these
other variables that affect the
performance.
So if we observe a correlation,
we have to make sure that we interpret
this correlation correctly that we do
not immediately interpret this
correlation as an effect. But still in a
metalytic literature very often
correlations and and other measures of
association are called effect sizes.
So pay attention with the term effect
sizes. It's okay to use the term effect
sizes, but keep in mind that this does
not necessarily mean that there is
indeed in an effect of one variable on
the other variable.
Sometimes in a meta analysis we are
combining for instance chromebox alphas.
So these are measures that express um to
what extent um a test is reliable to
what extent different items of a of an
instrument are related to each other. So
here it does not make sense to talk
about an effect but still in metaic
literature we uh often chromach alphas
are called effect sizes as well and in
some analysis we even do not look at the
association between two variables. For
instance suppose that you are interested
in the prevalence rate of dyslexia.
So maybe this has or probably this has
been studied in multiple studies and you
can combine all these prevalence rates
and you can study whether um there is
heterogeneity in rates and if there is
heterogeneity you can study you can
explore whether you can find
characteristics of the studies that are
related to the prevalence rates. So you
can again do a meta analysis on these
metrics
in much the same way as we um can do a
meta analysis on correlations or
standardized mean differences. But here
the metric is a characteristic or is a a
statistic regarding
one single variable and not the
association between variables.
So again this is very important
association is not the same as a causal
relationship.
So before you conclude based on
correlation coefficient for instance
based on an observed association that
there is one variable that is
influencing the other variable you have
to check clearly the internal validity
of your design. You have to make sure
that there are no compounding variables
that can explain the association.
How can you interpret effect sizes?
Well, sometimes
unstandardized effect sizes are used
because sometimes interpretation of
effect sizes is clear from the
beginning. Suppose for instance um
you start a campaign um a campaign to
try to reduce um the smoking in uh in
youngsters.
You can express the effect of that
campaign by looking at the number of
cigarettes that are were smoked before
the campaign and the number of
cigarettes per person that were smoked
after the campaign. You do not have to
standardize this mean difference. It's
clear immediately for all readers of
your report what you mean by this mean
difference.
And if in multiple studies exactly the
same measure is used. So in in multiple
studies they look at the mean difference
in the number of cigarettes smoked. then
you do not have to standardize this in
effect size before combining them in a
meta analysis.
Some people still find it hard to
interpret a standardized mean
difference.
If you look at this website, if you go
to this website, you can see how you can
uh interpret a standardized mean
difference of for instance two.
One interpretation is well suppose that
you have two normal distributions, two
normal population distributions.
If the difference the standardized mean
difference is equal to two, then this
means that 98%
about 98%
of the scores of the light blue
distribution is larger than the mean of
the dark blue distribution.
Another interpretation is there is about
32% of overlap between the two
population distributions.
A third interpretation is suppose that
you would take randomly one person from
the control condition and randomly one
person from the treatment condition.
Then there is a probability of about 92%
that the person from the treatment
condition will have a higher score than
the person from the control condition.
And then the final interpretation is
that
suppose that you consider the 20%
highest scores of the control condition
as
scores that are okay. So that you use a
specific cutoff score above which 20% of
the control condition is situated.
Then
you have to treat
148 people from that control condition
to have an expected number of persons
above that uh above that cutoff equal to
100. So if you want to bring 100 persons
above that cut cutoff then you have to
treat
148 of these of uh people from the
control condition.
also for the correlation coefficient. Um
this site can be used to look at how you
can interpret correlations.
Thanks to the fact that these that
effect sizes are standardized, we can
use rules of temp. So Cohen for instance
uh suggested several rules of terms by
looking at um how effect sizes were
interpreted by researchers in a lot of
studies in the behavioral sciences. And
he found that if the the standardized
mean difference is about 20 that very
often authors called u the observed
effect relatively small. If the effect
size was equal to 0 50 then this effect
is often called medium and if the effect
size is equal to 80 then often
researchers call uh the mean difference
a large difference.
You can also see um correlations and uh
the proportions of variance explained.
Um so R and R squared and you can see um
what values correspond to small effects,
medium effects and large effects,
at least in behavioral sciences.
Note that sometimes small effects can
still be impressive
and I recommend you to read the paper of
Brenta Miller because it's uh yeah it's
a very interesting paper. So they argue
that sometimes small effects are indeed
impressive and they give some
um examples.
For instance, they give an example of an
experiment experiment in which um
students sitting in a library. Some
students are given a cookie. Other
students are not given a cookie. And
then afterwards when these students come
out of the library, there is an old
woman who wants to cross the street and
and apparently has problems in uh in
crossing the street. And it was found
that students who got before one simple
cookie, they were more willing to help
that old lady than students who were not
given a cookie.
The effect was not huge, but
apprentice and Miller conclude that this
effect is impressive. It's impressive
that by giving a very small cookie to
persons, these persons are more willing
to help other people. So you would not
expect that there is an effect, but
still there is an effect. It's a small
effect, but because you do not expect
it, it's still impressive.
Another
example, they also give the example of
um of an of experiments or an experiment
in which um
members of a jury in a trial in court
seems to be affected by the physical
attractiveness of the defendants. So
it's an experiment. Um so it was not it
was a fake trial but of course the
people from the jury did not know that
it was a fake trial and in one group um
the defendant was a very physical
attractive women woman in another group
the defendant was not attractive at all
and it was found that the jury members
uh judged differently so were apparently
affected by the physical attraction
effectiveness of the defendant. Again,
the effect was not very large, but still
it is uh it is an impressive effect
because again, you would not expect that
there is an effect. You would expect
that people are doing their best um the
best they can to remain objective and
and probably they did their best to be
objective, but still they were affected
by the physical attractiveness of the
defendants.
So note that the size of the effect is
not equal to the practical significance.
So we have seen that you have the
statistical significance. This is not
the same as the size of the effect the
effect size because uh the statistical
significance also depends on the size of
the study.
But very often in the literature people
say well you have statistical
significance and you have practical
significance which is which is expressed
uh in a measure of effect size but the
size of the effect still is not the same
as a practical significance because the
practical significance also depends on
for instance the cost of the treatment.
So suppose that by washing hands
you can
you can have a small effect
um or or you can by washing your hands
you can have a large effect on uh the
number of cases with flu
versus
by vaccination you can have the same
effect.
So the size of the effect can be the
same in the two situations for the two
treatments. But still the practical
significance of washing your hands is
larger because it's it's a very easy
measure to take. It's it does not cost
money. Everybody can do it.
So the practical significance of this
treatment is larger.
Another example severity of the problem
under investigation.
Suppose that by washing your hands you
can
avoid having flu
or um um being affected by the corona
virus on one hand or by washing your
hands you can avoid common colds.
Suppose that the effect is the same. The
size of the effect is the same.
In that case, the practical significance
is larger for corona virus because this
problem is a larger problem is is more
severe.
The same is true for the extent of the
problem. If we can tackle
um a very extensive problem, a problem
that is uh that is everywhere with a
simple solution. The practical
significance of this solution or this
treatment is larger than if you can uh
help um um solving a problem that is not
very common.
Calculation of effect sizes. Um, there
are a lot of effect sizes. We already
have seen a few effect sizes,
but I tried to make an overview of some
effect sizes of commonly used effect
sizes, but this is not um an exhaustive
overview. There are much more effect
sizes than the ones I mentioned here.
So I try to to categorize effect sizes
according to uh the measurement level of
the dependent variable and the
measurement level of the independent
variable.
Let's look first at a situation where
you have two dichotomus variables.
So suppose for instance you want to
predict using a test whether somebody
will fail or succeed in the final exam
at university.
and you collect data. Suppose that these
are the data
then you hope that based on your
predictive test you can predict as good
as possible the final exam score. So you
can predict whether the person will uh
fail or not. So suppose that one stands
for success and zero stands for a
failure. Same for the predictive test.
Is there an association between the two
tests? Or in other words, can you
predict whether somebody will fail or
succeed on the final exam based on the
result of the predictive test?
If you look at the data, then apparently
this is the case. If one you can see
that 150 persons uh succeeded on the
predictive test and the majority of them
also succeeded on the final exam. So 130
people from these 150 people uh
succeeded
from the 50 people who failed the
predictive test also a majority but a
small majority succeeded on the final
exam. So there seems to be an
association between the two. This is
more easy
uh to see this if you calculate uh
proportions. So you can see that from
all people who succeeded on the
predictive test, 87%
succeeded on the final exam. Whereas
this is only the case for 60% of the
people who uh failed on the predictive
test. So how can we calculate a measure
that expresses the size of association
between the two variables? One possible
way is to calculate the difference in
risks. Uh so the difference in the
probability of succeeding the final exam
for the two uh conditions for uh people
who did not fail and people who failed
on the predictive test. And you can see
that the probability
is 27%
higher uh for people who succeeded on
the predictive test. So this is the
difference between the risks. An
alternative measure that is also very
often used and that we already uh have
seen before in the first session is the
relative risk or the risk ratio. So it
is 87 uh 87% divided by 60%. Which gives
us a value ratio of 1.45.
So this means that if one succeeded on
the uh predictive test then the
probability is 1.4. 45 times higher that
the person will also succeed on the
final exam compared to people who did
not succeed on the predictive test.
Note that these are two measures for
exactly the same data but the values are
completely different 27 and 1.45.
Still another measure that is very often
used is a fi coefficient.
five coefficient giving a value of 29
again another value.
Another measure that is very often used
is odds ratio.
This odds ratio gives a value of 4.33
and also very often used is the lo odds
ratio which is a natural logarithm of
the odds ratio giving a value of 1.47.
So you see for the same situation for
the same kinds of data you can calculate
multiple metrics
and it's important to note here that
these different measures also give
different values.
So you cannot simply say that the effect
size for this data is for instance 1.45.
You have to mention what type of effect
size you calculated or what measure of
effect size, what measure of assessation
you calculated.
If you would have um from multiple
studies effect size metrics for these
kinds of data for 2x two tables, then
you have to make sure that the effect
size metric that is used in all these
studies is exactly the same. Otherwise
it does not make sense to combine these
effect sizes over studies.
Another situation suppose you have an
ordinal or an interval dependent
variable and a dichomous independent
variable. So suppose you have two groups
and you compare these two you compare
the scores on an ordinal or interval
variable in these two groups.
We already have seen the standardized
mean difference calculated as the
difference between the sample means
divided by the pulled standard
deviation.
Pooling standard deviations make sense
if we can assume that there is a common
population standard deviation so that in
both uh conditions the standard
deviation
of the population is exactly the same.
If this is not the case and and this for
instance suppose that the treatment has
an effect has has not the same effect on
all persons then this could make that in
the treatment condition the variation
between persons in the performance on
the outcome variable is larger than in
the control condition. In that situation
it does not make sense to use pulled
standard deviation to calculate a
standardized mean difference.
An alternative that was proposed by
class is uh to standardize uh the mean
difference by dividing by the standard
deviation from the control group only.
Still another situation suppose that you
have one group that is measured before
and after a treatment. What is sometimes
used is a standardized mean difference
uh based on gain scores.
So the the mean gain for for each person
the gain or the difference is calculated
between um the score after a treatment
and the score before the treatment. And
then a mean difference score is
calculated and this is divided by the
standard deviation of these different
scores.
An alternative measure is a standardized
mean difference in which you calculate
the difference between the post mean and
the pre-mean and you divide it by the
standard deviation of the precores.
Sometimes you have a combination of
these two two designs. You have two
groups an experimental group and a
control group. But the experimental
group and the control group is measured
before sorry in the beginning of the
experiment and after the treatment
uh started.
So here in this situation you can
calculate this uh standardized mean
difference.
So in fact you calculate uh for both
conditions first standardized mean
difference and then you calculate the
difference between these two
standardized mean differences.
Still other measures are nonparametric
and robust measures. For instance,
sometimes uh or some people proposed to
use the the difference between medians
rather than the difference between means
because medians are more robust against
uh outlying values.
Still another measure is a point by
serial correlation coefficient. So it's
it's a correlation coefficient
calculated between
um a dichomous variable 01 variable on
one side and um the scores on
uh the dependent or the yeah a
continuous variable on the other side.
Another group of measures um can be used
in in a situation where you have a
nominal dependent variable and a nominal
independent variable. So again there are
multiple measures that can be
calculated. I'm not going to uh to give
details on these measures.
But what I want to say is suppose that
you have a table like this.
So you have two nominal uh or
categorical variables
and based on this table this frequency
table it looks like the experimental
condition performs better. So the
treatments seems to have a positive
effect in the sense that a lot of people
um have less symptoms of the illness in
the uh experimental condition whereas in
the control condition uh for a lot of
people the amount of uh symptoms remain
the same during the experiment.
So in this table
it seems that there is a positive effect
of the treatment. You can calculate uh a
couple of measures measures that were
included in the table that I've shown on
the previous slide.
But look at this situation
here. I changed control. I switched the
labels of control and experimental. So
based on this data, the conclusion would
be no, the experimental condition or the
treatment is making the situation worse
compared to the control condition.
But if you would calculate the measures
that were given on the previous slide,
then for the two tables, you would
obtain exactly the same values. So this
is a real problem um especially for met
analysis. If you would uh use measures
of effect for uh expressing the size of
assessation between two categorical
variables. These measures do not give a
direction. They do not say in what
direction the effect is observed. And
here in the third table again you would
get exactly the same values uh for the
the matrix whereas again the situation
is different. Here I switched um
uh the labels better and same. So again
the interpretation of the
effect size is different but the value
for the effect size is exactly the same.
So this is problematic for math
analysis. Suppose that you would uh uh
find in one study the first table in the
second study the second table. So in the
two studies you would find the same
effect size measure. Um so if you would
in your meta analysis calculate the mean
effect then the mean effect would be
equal to um yeah the the effect size
that you found in the two studies. But
because the effect is going in the two
in two different directions in the two
studies, the conclusion should rather be
that there is no effect at all on
average.
What if you have a nominal or
categorical independent variable and an
ordinal or interval variable
uh as a dependent variable? Well, in
this, so for instance, what if you would
uh have an analysis of variance in a
specific study? Well, what you could do
is you could calculate multiple
standardized mean differences.
So for each pair of groups, for each
pair of categories, you can calculate uh
the mean difference and you can
standardize it by dividing this stand
this mean difference by a pulled
standard deviation or you can look at
the proportion of variance that is um
that is explained by the categorical uh
independent variable.
What if you have uh two interval
variables? In that situation again you
can calculate multiple measures uh for
instance correlation coefficient of
Pearson. But if you have ordinal uh
variables then it's better to use a
Spearman correlation and so on.
What effect size can you use in case uh
regression analysis was done?
Look first at a simple linear regression
analysis. So with Y being regressed on a
predictor X.
In this situation, the regression weight
of X can be estimated as the correlation
between X and Y multiplied by the ratio
of the standard deviations.
So note that if X and Y would be
standardized
then the standard deviations would
become one and then B would become equal
to the correlation.
So a correlation coefficient which is
very often used as a measure of
association or measure of effect is in
fact a regression coefficient. it's a
standardized regression coefficient.
But if there is no need to standardize
the data, then also uh regression
coefficients can be considered as effect
size measures.
Suppose that X the predictor variable is
not continuous but dichomous
with zero for instance for the control
condition, one for the experimental
condition. then the estimate of B is
equal to the difference between the
sample means. So again you can see that
a mean difference which is often used as
a measure of effect is in fact a
regression coefficient
and a standardized mean difference
therefore is equal to a standardized
regression coefficient. If your
dependent variable would be uh divided
by uh the standard deviation of E, so
the residual standard deviation, then
your regression rate uh of X would be a
standardized mean difference.
Suppose that your dependent variable is
a dichotomus variable. In that case, you
can use logistic regression analysis.
So your dependent variable now is the
logit of the probability that y is equal
to 1. So the logit which is equal to the
natural logarithm of the odds
odds which is equal to b the probability
that y is equal to 1 divided by the
probability that y is equal to zero.
So the lo odds is equal uh in our model
to a + b x. What is now b? b is in fact
a lo odds ratio. So b is the difference
between um the lo odds for the
experimental condition and the control
condition. And the difference between
two logarithms is a logarithm of the
ratio.
Um so the difference between lo odds is
equal to the log of the ratio of the two
odds. So it's it's the lo odds ratio. So
the lo odds ratio which is very often
used especially in biomedical sciences
is also regression coefficient.
Now the sampling distribution of effect
sizes. Why is this important for a meta
analysis? Well, it's important to know
what a sampling distribution is of an
effect size measure for multiple
reasons. First reason is that typical
metalytic uh techniques assume that the
effect size uh that is used follows a
normal distribution so that the sampling
distribution is a normal distribution.
A second reason is that we need to have
an idea of what the precision is of the
effect size measure before we combine
effect size measures in a math analysis.
Because a precision is used to weight
effect sizes in the meta analysis and
it's also used to calculate the
precision of our uh final mean estimate.
Look at the standardized mean
difference. Indeed, a standardized mean
difference follows a normal or the
sampling distribution of the
standardized mean difference is a normal
distribution with mean equal to the
population standardized mean difference
and with a variance. A variance that can
be estimated.
Variance is equal to
the ratio between um of necid
* nc plus
the delta squared. So the population
effect size divided by two times the
total sample size. Of course we cannot
calculate this sampling variance but
because we do not know delta. But what
is very often done in meta analysis is
you replace delta uh by G. So you
replace the population effect size by
the observed effect size and then you
get a rather good estimate of the
sampling variance of G of an observed
effect size.
So if the group sizes are equal and if
the group sizes are relatively large
compared to the standardized mean
difference itself then the sampling
variance is more or less equal to 4
divided by the total sample size.
What about correlation coefficient? Well
also the correlation coefficient has a
sampling distribution that is more or
less normal. The mean of the sampling
distribution is the population
correlation coefficient and the variance
is equal to 1 minus r row squared
squared divided by the total sample
size.
Now there are several problems however
with this uh uh association measure.
The first problem is that sampling
distribution is only approximate
approximately normal especially if row
is close to zero uh uh close to minus
one or + one. Suppose that the
population correlation coefficient is
95.
In that situation, observed correlation
coefficients cannot be much larger than
the population correlation because u
correlation coefficients cannot be
larger by definition than one. But
observed correlations can be much
smaller than the population correlation
of 95.
So the sampling distribution will become
skewed especially if you have small
samples.
So the sampling distribution is only
approximately normal. A second problem
is there is some bias. The expected
value of um the observed correlation is
not exactly equal to the population
correlation.
And the third problem is the bias but
also the sampling variance depends
strongly on the
um the population correlation.
So here again to estimate the sampling
variance we could replace row by r. But
here this a small deviation of R from
the population correlation can result in
a in a large difference in the estimate
of the sampling variance.
A solution is to calculate a Fiser Z
transformation
transformed value.
and fishery set is equal to.5 * the
natural logarithm of 1 + the observed
correlation divided by one minus the
correlation. So the advantage is that
the sampling distribution of the fisher
z value is more or less equal to a
normal distribution. Another another
advantage is that the sampling variance
now is
can be easily estimated. it is equal to
1 divided by the sample size minus 3.
Note that now the sampling variance does
not depend anymore on the size of the
effect.
So what is very often done if uh in
multiple studies correlations were
observed and we want to combine these
correlations. Well, we first uh perform
um or we use a fisher set transformation
to convert these correlations to the
fisher z scores. We perform a met
analysis on the fisher z values. So you
calculate the the mean fisher z for
instance and then afterwards you and and
you also calculate an a confidence
interval around uh the fisher z the mean
fisher z value and then afterwards you
back transform these values. So you back
transform the confidence limits and you
back transform the mean fisher set
towards the r scale.
A third measure that is very often used
is the odds ratio. So odds ratio that
can be calculated if you have a 2x2
table. So um suppose that you that the
cells are a b c and d then the odds
ratio is equal to a * d divided by b *
c.
Again we have the problem that odds
ratio has a asymmetric distribution.
So suppose that um suppose that there is
no association at all in the population.
So in that situation um the odds ratio
in the population will be equal to one.
But the observed odds ratios can be
smaller than one and can be larger than
one. But obser cannot be smaller than
zero.
So about half of the observed effect
sizes would be uh values between zero
and one whereas the other half would be
values between one and plus infinity. So
again you have a skewed distribution.
Another drawback is that the standard
error formula is also a complex uh
formula.
solution is here again to perform a
transformation. More specifically, very
often the natural logarithm is taken of
the odds ratio. The advantage is that
the sampling distribution now becomes
more or less normal. So symmetric and
normal and that the sampling variance is
uh easily be estimated more
specifically. It's equal to 1 / a plus 1
/ b + 1 / c plus 1 / d.
choosing a measure. So we have seen that
there are a lot of measures. I did not
ex um explain all the measures from the
table and on top of that there are much
more additional measures. How do you
choose a measure? So first of course the
measure you use depends on the design.
For instance if you have two uh and on
the measurement level for instance if
you have two continuous variables then
you can use correlation coefficient. If
you have two dichoamous variables, you
can use a loss ratio.
Secondly, it's often a good idea to use
a standardized measure to make sure that
you can compare the values over multiple
studies.
Third, you have to be aware that
sometimes assumptions are made. We
already looked at the standardized mean
difference um in which the
standardization was done by dividing by
a pulled standard deviation. This only
makes sense if the assumption that the
two population standard deviations are
the same is reasonable
otherwise it may be better to use
classes delta. So dividing the mean
difference by uh the standard deviation
from from the control condition.
A fourth criterion is a popularity.
So standardized mean differences loss
ratios correlation coefficients are very
often used.
People are familiar with these values
with these measures. So it can be a good
idea to use these measures in your meta
analysis.
Fifth, simplicity of a measure.
The lost for instance is somewhat hard
to interpret. The risk difference is
much easier to understand. So that could
be an argument to choose for a risk
difference.
Another criterion is
that it is a good idea to use a
directional effect size. So if um if for
instance you are looking at two
continuous variables then it's a good
idea to use R but it's not a good idea
to use R squar R R squar would uh give
an idea of what the proportion of
variance would be if you would predict
one of the variables based on the other
variables based on the other variable.
But a drawback of R squar is that it is
not directional. So it's possible that
in one study a negative correlation was
found. In another study a positive
correlation was found. So on average
there is no correlation. There's no
association. But if you would use R
squar then in both studies uh you would
get a positive value and the mean of
these R squared would be positive of
course as well suggesting that there is
on average an effect
and then seventh the simplicity of the
sampling distribution. We look for
measures that have a normal sampling
distribution with um if possible a
sampling variance that can be easily
estimated.
A remark on the comparability of effect
size measures.
I already said that in the same
situation for the same types of data you
sometimes can calculate multiple
measures and sometimes these measures
are comparable but sometimes they are
not comparable. For instance, look at um
um the standardized mean difference for
independent groups and the standardized
mean difference uh uh based on gain
scores.
So for independent groups, the
standardized mean difference is the
difference between the two population
means divided by the common standard
deviation
or at least we assume that there is a
common population standard deviation.
The G for gain scores is equal to the
mean difference score divided by the
standard deviation of the different
scores. So it is
equal to the mean of the post- test
scores minus the mean of the pre-est
scores
divided by so the standard deviation of
the difference scores is equal to the
square root of the variance of the post-
test scores plus the variance of the
pre-est scores minus 2 * the correlation
uh between pre and post test um times
the standard deviation of the pre-EST
scores times the standard deviation of
the post- test scores.
If we can assume that the treatment does
not have an effect or that that the
treatment has the same effect on all
persons.
In that situation the variance um um of
the post- test scores will be the same
as the variance of the post pre-est
scores. So in that situation this
variance can be
um
the variance is equal to sigma squared.
We can put sigma in front of the square
root and so we have the difference
between the uh the means divided by
sigma times the square root of 2 * 1
minus row.
And assuming
that the mean of the post- test scores
is the same as the mean that would have
been observed in a group that was
measured only after a treatment.
And assuming that the mean of the
pre-est scores
is the same as the mean of a control
group of control condition in that
situation you can use the formula that
you see at the bottom of this slide to
convert or to express the relationship
between the um the effect size for gain
scores and the effect size for
independent groups.
So why
do I why did I explain this derivation?
I explained this derivation to make
clear that sometimes we can express the
relationship
um between two measures and this
relationship can be used to convert one
measure to the other measure.
But it's also important to see based on
this derivation that for deriving this
conversion formula we made some
assumptions. We made the assumption that
the means of uh the um
the the post- test and the pre-est are
comparable to the means of uh an
experimental uh group and a control
group. And we also made the assumption
that the treatment effect is the same
for all persons. So that the variance of
the post- test scores is the same as the
variance of the pre-est scores. So based
on these assumptions, you can derive
this uh conversion formula.
And so if you would uh have an observed
effect size um
from independent groups and for another
study you would have an observed effect
size from gain scores where you can
convert one observed effect size to the
other type of effect size before you
combine them in a meta analysis.
Sometimes such a conversion is not pos
is not needed. So for instance, if you
look at the observed effect size
um the difference between effect sizes
sorry the difference between sample
means divided by a pulled standard
deviation that can be used in the
situation where uh the standard
deviation of the populations can be
assumed to be the same. But in the same
situation, it's also possible to
calculate classes delta.
And classes delta estimates exactly the
same population value. Classes delta is
the mean is the difference between the
sample means divided by the standard
deviation of the control group. So also
the standard deviation of the control
group is estimating the standard
deviation the common standard deviation
of the two populations.
So these two effect sizes in fact are
estimating the same population effect
size.
So they can be combined in the same meta
analysis. You do not have to convert one
measure to the other measure. But what
is important here to note is that
glasses delta is slightly less precise
because you are estimating the common
standard deviation sigma by using only
the standard deviation of the control
group. So this estimate is less precise
and therefore that estimate of the
population standard deviation sorry the
estimate of the population standardized
mean difference is also somewhat uh more
uh somewhat less precise.
So this means that
standardized mean differences in which
the mean
uh difference or the difference between
the sample means is divided by the
bullet standard deviation should be
given a somewhat larger weight than
classes deltas in a met analysis.
How can you calculate effect sizes?
Well, we have seen that several that
that you can derive conversion formulas.
Um, I'm going very fast over the next
slides. So, that were slides that I uh
retrieved uh from a website of David
Wilson.
So David Wilson said well to calculate
an effect size value and here if they
talk about if he talks about the effect
size value he refers to the standardized
mean difference. So if you would
calculate would like to calculate the
standardized mean difference then there
are several ways or several approaches
that can be followed.
Some of these approaches are very good
approaches, others are less good and
some approaches are
poor approaches.
So a great approach is
the direct calculation. So if you would
have the sample means and if you would
have the standard deviations and the
sample sizes, then you can calculate the
standardized mean difference using this
formula.
We also have seen that there is a clear
relationship between the G the
standardized mean difference and the t
statistic from uh a two sample t test.
Um so you can derive exactly um the
standardized mean difference from the t
statistic at least if you have um the
sample sizes.
Note that if you if an analysis of
variance is used uh to compare two
groups the f statistic that you obtain
is equal to the square of t. So if you
take the square root of f then you get
the t value and so again you can derive
the standardized mean difference from
this f value.
Suppose that you have for a specific
study a correlation coefficient, but for
other studies you have standardized mean
differences. You can convert the
correlation coefficient to that
standardized main difference using this
formula.
There are also some ways that are fine.
For instance, if you have uh results of
an analysis of variance with more than
two groups
and you have the means of the different
categories, but you do not have the
standard deviations of each um uh
category. In that situation, you can use
you can calculate the standardized mean
difference for a pair of means by
dividing the difference between the
means by a pulled standard deviation um
being equal to the square root of the
mean squared error that is very often
reported uh in such an analysis of
variance.
Note that this mean squared error is
based on uh the deviations in each of
the three groups and not only in these
two groups. So it's not exactly um the
value that you would obtain um when
calculating a standardized mean
difference if you would have the
standard deviations of each of the
categories separately. But probably the
value you obtain will be very close.
What if you have a twoway factorial
ANOVA? You can see the formula here
or if you have anova.
So these were fine or good ways.
Somewhat less good is approximations
based on dichoamous data.
Have a formula here. I'm not going to
explain it in detail
or this formula to convert a loss ratio
to a standardized mean difference
or this formula to convert a k square
value from a 2x2 contingency table to a
standardized mean difference or to
convert convert the f coefficient to a
standardized mean
So to do these calculations you can make
use of the website of David Wilson. Uh
I've put the link on this slide. You can
also use um the package
ESC
from R that is um in in which the same
formulas are implemented as in the
online tool of David Wilson. You can
also use a metaphor package that we will
use later in the practical session.
Other software can be used as well. For
instance, CMA which stands for
comprehensive meta analysis or uh you
can also use Excel. But in that case,
you will have to yeah to write uh the
formulas or implement the formulas
yourself.
In the handbook that is online on
Toledo, you can also find a lot of
formulas that can be used to convert one
metric to another metric.
Some threats of effect size measures.
The first threat is of course if you
have bad data, if you do not have uh
data of a good quality, then of course
your effect size metric can also be
wrong. For instance, what is very often
the case is that small typing errors are
made in data sets and
um or also typing errors in research
reports um such as in P values or in D
values or test statistics
or in effect size uh effect sizes that
are reported. So if you use these
statistics or draw data to calculate an
effect size measure then of course you
will get a bad effect size metric if the
data you started from were not correct.
Another problem is measurement error.
So suppose your dependent variable in an
experimental design is not measured in a
very accurate way. In this situation,
the standard deviation that you obtain
will be larger. And so think about the
standardized mean difference. So if the
standard deviation will be larger
because of measurement error, then the
observed effect size will become
smaller. So you can get biased results
by having an imprecise measurement of
your dependent variable.
By dichotomizing continuous variables,
often the effect size becomes smaller.
It's also possible that your variable is
not measured that that you are not
really measuring exactly what you want
to measure. So that your outcome
variable or your independent variable is
somewhat biased in the sense that you
may that you measure something slightly
different.
So this can increase the association
between the two variables or it can
decrease the association depending on
what exactly you are measuring.
It's also possible that there is bias in
your estimator. For instance, I said
that the standardized mean difference is
more or less unbiased. So that the mean
of the sampling distribution of the
standardized mean difference is the
population standardized mean difference.
This is not exactly the case. This is
not exactly true. So Hatches proposed
um a correction factor to correct for
small sample bias. So instead of using
G, it's better to multiply G by 1 minus
3 / 4
times the sample size - 9. You can see
that if N is large, so if you have a
large study, then that correction factor
will be more or less equal to one. So in
that situation the correction factor
does not correct a lot or or uh the
corrected G is almost equal to the
original G. So this correction factor is
especially important uh to be used. It's
important to use this correction factor
especially if your sample size is small.
Another threat is range restriction.
I'm going to explain this on the next
slide. So more information on these
threads is given in the book of Hunan
Schmidt. So they discuss in detail each
of these threads and they also discuss
in detail how you can correct your
effect sizes for these threads.
What about range restriction?
So I have here a scatter plot between
two continuous variables. In fact, these
are the scores on two exams from a large
group of students. And it's clear that
there is a high correlation between the
two variables, a high positive
correlation. So students who performed
well on the first exam also performed
well on the second exam in general and
the other way around. But suppose that I
restrict the range that I only
uh keep students who performed between
five and 15 on the first exam.
I made a new scatter plot based on only
these students.
And if you look at this scatter plot,
you can see that the association between
the two variables disappeared largely.
So maybe there is still a correlation a
positive correlation but this
correlation will be very small. So this
is an illustration that the range
restriction typically reduces the size
of association between two variables. So
again this can induce bias.