In this screencast, I will introduce the
principles of meta analysis.
To do so, I will start from a simulation
to explain the problem of failures to
replicate and to show how meta analysis
can help us out. Next, we will look at
more complex scenarios than the one from
the simulation. And finally, I will give
an overview of questions that are often
studied in met analysis and of the steps
that are typically involved.
First, the problem of failures to
replicate.
Suppose there is an association between
gender and the scores on the mathematics
exam in the sense that female students
perform better than male students.
Suppose that both uh for female and male
students the scores follow a normal
distribution with a common standard
deviation but that female students
perform on average half a point better
than male students.
A measure that we can use to express a
size of the association between gender
and met is the difference between the
means which here is 050.
A drawback of this measure, however, is
that its size depends on the way the
variable is measured. Suppose that the
exam is not measured. It's not an exam
with scores on a scale from 0 to 10, but
rather with scores on a scale from 0 to
100. Then maybe on average, female
students will perform 85 and male
students 80.
Therefore, the difference would be five
points instead of half a point.
In other words, talking about the
difference between the means to express
a size of the association only makes
sense if you know on what scale the
variable is measured.
To solve that problem, very often a
standardized mean difference is
calculated.
The difference between the means is
standardized by dividing this difference
by the standard deviation.
In this example, the standardized mean
difference is a difference of 050
divided by the standard deviation of
1.5.
Therefore, the standardized mean
difference is equal to 0.33.
This measure was already introduced in
1969 by con. Note that we are talking
here about the population of female and
me and male students. That's also why I
use Greek symbols to refer to the means
and to the standard deviation and why I
use the Greek symbol delta to refer to
the standardized mean difference.
Now suppose that in a study samples are
drawn from these populations
based on the scores
you observe in these samples. You can
also calculate a standardized mean
difference. More specifically, you can
calculate a difference in sample means
and standardize this difference by
dividing it by a kind of pulled or
averaged standard deviation which I will
explain later in this course.
We will call the statistic calculated
based on the sample data an observed
standardized mean difference or an
observed effect size. And this observed
standardized mean difference can be used
to estimate the population standardized
mean difference also called the true
standardized mean difference. In other
words, G is used as an estimate of
delta.
Note that thanks to the standardizing it
becomes possible to say something about
whether a specific value can be
considered as high or small because this
does not depend on the scale anymore.
Cohen gave us guidelines for
interpreting standardized mean
differences in the behavioral sciences
by calculating standardized mean
differences for a large number of
studies and looking at the
interpretation the authors of these
studies gave to the effects they found
based on the guidelines of con a
standardized mean difference of 0.20 20
is considered a small effect.
A standardized mean difference of 050 a
moderate effect and 0.80 is considered a
large effect.
Now back to the example we have seen
that in the that the population
standardized mean difference is 0.33.
Of course in reality we often do not
know the population means and standard
deviation.
What we have instead in a typical study
is a sample of scores from both
populations.
Still, we can use these two samples to
say something about the standardized
mean difference from the population. I
simulated this process by asking the
computer to give me a sample of 20
scores from a normal distribution with
mean 8 and standard deviation 1.5
and to give me also a random sample of
20 scores from the female population
with a normal distribution with mean 8.5
and standard deviation 1.5.
Here you see the results for the fe for
the male students. The average score is
somewhat higher than the population
mean. We obtained the sample mean of
8.10 whereas the population mean was
equal to 8.
That on average the scores were a little
bit higher than the mean of the
population is due to coincidence.
In a sample of 20 scores for female
students, I obtained an average score of
9.34.
This is much higher than the mean of the
female population 8.5.
In the two samples, the standard
deviations were exactly equal to each
other 1.55.
It is again due to coincidence that
these standard deviations were slightly
larger than the population standard
deviation of 1.5 and that they are
exactly the same in both samples.
Now suppose that the values I have drawn
were the values observed in a real
study. In that case probably the
researchers would perform a t test to
test whether on average there is a
difference between male and female
students. Based on the simulated data we
get a relatively small p value a p value
of 0.015.
If we would use a significance level of
5% then we would reject the null
hypothesis. The null hypothesis saying
that the two population means are equal.
In other words, we would conclude that
there is a difference between male and
female students in the sense that female
students perform better than male
students.
In this example, this is indeed the
correct conclusion. Female students
indeed perform better than male
students.
I also calculated the observed
standardized mean difference. This gives
a value of 0.80.
In other words, if these were the data
of a real study, in this study, the
standardized mean difference of the
population would have been
overestimated.
In reality, the population standardized
mean difference is equal to 0.33.
Whereas based on our sample data, our
estimate is 0.80.
In some if these were the data of real
study, we would overestimate the
difference between male and female
students, but we would come to the
correct conclusion that female students
perform better than male students.
I've done this simulation a second time.
In a new sample of 20 male students, the
mean is 7.60, 60 which is somewhat too
smaller than population mean of eight.
The sample mean for the female students
now is 7.59 which is much too small
and it is even slightly smaller than the
sample mean for the male students. Now
the two standard deviations are
different and are slightly smaller than
the population standard deviation.
You can see that the two sample means
are very similar. Using a t test to test
the difference between the population
means therefore results in a large p
value. The p value is equal to 98.
Based on these data, the conclusion
would be that there is no difference
between male and female students, which
is an incorrect conclusion.
If we then estimate the size of the
effect, we get a standardized mean
difference very close to zero because
the two sample means are very close to
each other.
You can also see that the standardized
mean difference now is negative because
now our sample of female students
perform on average slightly worse than
our sample of male students.
In some if this were the data of real
study, the conclusion of the researchers
would be wrong. They would conclude that
there is no difference between male and
female students. Moreover, the estimate
of the standardized mean difference
would be completely wrong. our estimate
is almost equal to zero and even
slightly negative whereas in reality
there is a positive effect in the sense
that female students perform better.
I've done this simulation another eight
times. Therefore in total I simulated 10
data sets. Now look at the p values.
You can see that very often the p value
is not very small. Often the p value is
larger than 0.05. of five. This means
that often the null hypothesis that
there is no difference between male and
female students. So the null hypothesis
that there is no association between
gender and mathematics is not rejected.
Therefore often an incorrect conclusion
is drawn. Only in two out of the 10
times the correct conclusion was drawn
that female students perform better than
male students.
Now look at the standardized mean
differences. Remember that in reality
the population standardized mean
difference is equal to 0.33.
But now we see that our estimates
sometimes sometimes are much larger like
in the first simulated data set. But
sometimes our estimates are much smaller
like in the second simulated data set.
Sometimes the standardized mean
difference is negative. Sometimes it's
positive. In general, you can see that
these observed standardized mean
differences are varying around the
population standardized mean difference.
And indeed, it can be shown
mathematically that the observed
standardized mean difference is normally
distributed around the population
standardized mean difference. In other
words, if you would draw a very large or
an infinite number of samples and each
time calculate the observed standardized
mean difference, at the end you would
observe a normal distribution of values
around the true population effect size.
This distribution is called the sampling
distribution of the standardized mean
difference.
It can also be shown that the variance
of this sampling distribution called the
sampling variance is more or less equal
to four divided by the total size of the
study.
Remember that in our example we
simulated samples of size 20. Therefore
in total the study sample size was equal
to 40. Therefore the sampling variance
of G is equal to 4 / 40. This is equal
to 0.10. 10.
If we know that G follows a normal
distribution with mean delta and a
variance that we can calculate, we can
use this to construct confidence
intervals.
For instance, to calculate a 95%
confidence interval, we can subtract and
add 1.96*
the square root of 0.10
to G.
We can now say with 95 com 95%
confidence that the population effect
size studied in this study is situated
within this interval.
I have constructed confidence intervals
for each of the 10 observed effect sizes
from the 10 simulated data sets.
Remember
that population effect size was equal to
0.33.
You can see in this plot that sometimes
the simulated effect size was somewhat
too high and sometimes it was somewhat
too low. But the observed effect sizes
clearly vary around the population
effect size of 0.33.
Only in the fourth simulated data set,
the observed effect size was very close
to the population effect size.
Further note that zero is included in
almost all of these confidence intervals
for eight out of the 10 simulated data
sets. Zero is included in the confidence
interval, which means that the null
hypothesis that the population effect
size is equal to zero is not rejected.
Only in two data sets in the first and
in the sixth data set zero is not
included in the confidence interval.
Only in these two cases the significance
test reveals that the population effect
sizes are different from zero. But as
you can see exactly in these two studies
the size of the effects is highly
overestimated.
Now suppose that these 10 simulated data
sets came from 10 real studies. You can
see the issue of failures to replicate.
By coincidence, studies can come to very
different estimates and even different
conclusions.
So what can we conclude about the
population effect size? Well, we have
seen that the observed effect sizes vary
around the population effect size. So
sometimes of observed effect sizes will
be too large, sometimes they will be too
small.
Therefore, if you want to say something
about the population effect size, we can
calculate an average of all these
observed effect sizes to get a more
precise estimate of the population
effect size.
In other words, we sum all the effect
sizes and divide this sum by the number
of studies, which in metanalytic
literature is very often referred to
with a symbol K. We can now use this
mean as an estimate of the population
effect size. In our example, the mean
effect size is equal to 0.25,
which is not too far from the real um
value of 0.33.
If you would have the data from 10 other
studies, probably we would get a
different mean effect size. Again, it
can be shown that the mean effect size
fluctuates around the population effect
size. So sometimes our mean will be
smaller, sometimes it will be larger
than the population effect size. This
sampling distribution is again a normal
distribution around the population
effect size.
But importantly, the sampling variance
now is k times smaller. The sampling
variance now is not sigma squared
anymore, but it's sigma squar divided by
k. In our example, we had 10 effect
sizes. And for each of the effect sizes,
the sampling variance was equal to 0.10.
The sampling variance of the mean effect
size now is not 0.10 anymore. It's
0.010.
In some if we use a mean effect size
rather than an individual effect size,
our estimate becomes more precise. In
other words, the estimate is more likely
to be close to the population value.
I calculated confidence interval for the
mean of the 10 simulated effect sizes
given in red in the graph. You can
observe several things. First, you can
see that the individual observed effect
sizes vary a lot around the population
effect size, but the mean is relatively
close to the population effect size. A
second observation is that the
confidence interval now is smaller than
for the individual studies.
For the individual studies, we had large
confidence intervals which also had
resulted in the fact that only in two
out of the 10 studies we simulated a
zero was not included in the confidence
interval. Therefore, only in two out of
the 10 studies, the conclusion was
correct. More specifically, that female
students perform better than male
students. This illustrates that in the
individual studies, the statistical
power is relatively small. But if you
combine the results of several studies,
you can see that the confidence interval
becomes much smaller and now zero is not
included in the confidence interval
anymore. So based on the combination of
the data from the 10 data sets, we
conclude that there is a difference
between male and female students. So
that female students perform better than
male students.
Based on the combination of the data, we
draw the correct conclusion. there is an
association between gender and met.
This illustrates that the statistical
power or the probability that we will
reject a null hypothesis increases by
combining the data of several studies.
To summarize, observed effect sizes in
individual studies may vary a lot,
whereas the combined effect size is
often close to the population effect
size.
we are indeed averaging out the noise.
Negative and positive deviations are
canceled out.
A second observation is that for the
individual studies, confidence intervals
were relatively uh large.
Whereas for our combined
confidence interval, the confidence
interval was relatively small,
illustrating that the accuracy or the
precision is higher. we can better
estimate what the population effect size
is.
Third, zero was often included in the
confidence intervals for the individual
studies.
Whereas, if we combine the results, zero
was not included in the confidence
interval, illustrating that by combining
the results of several studies, we can
increase the statistical power.
If you want to try out out this
simulation yourself, you can make use of
the Excel file simulation MA which you
can find on to. This file contains
several sheets. The first sheet called
raw data includes a data of 10 studies.
Data that are randomly drawn from normal
distributions. For each study, random
samples of 20 scores are drawn from two
normal distributions.
If you click on the function key F9, all
these values are replaced by new
randomly drawn values from these normal
distributions.
The second sheet called study one, you
can see the means, standard deviations,
sample sizes, the observed standardized
mean difference, the t and the p value
for the first study. The values are
calculated based on the data from the
first study from the previous sheet.
Again, if you click on F9, new random
data will be sampled and these values
will change. In the third sheet called K
studies, you get an overview of all the
means, standard deviations, sample
sizes, standardized mean differences,
TMP values for all 10 studies. And in
the final sheet called meta analysis,
you can see the calculation of the mean
effect size. You can also see a plot
with a confidence interval for the
individual studies as well as for the
mean effect size. I suggest you to click
a few times on F9. Each time data for a
new data for a new set of 10 studies
will be simulated and all means,
standard deviations and so on will be
adapted. In that way you will see that
the observed effect sizes will indeed
vary a lot around the population effect
size. But we'll also see that the mean
of the observed effect sizes will in
general be very close to the population
effect size which illustrates the
increase of precision.
You can also see that very often zero
um will be included in the conference
interval if we look at the individual
studies, but it will often be not
included in the conference interval when
we look at the combined results which
illustrates that combining effect sizes
increases the statistical power.
In fact, what we have done here is a
meta analysis. Jean Glass introduced
this term meta analysis to refer to the
analysis of analysis or the analysis of
the results of multiple studies.
But of course in reality meta analysis
often are much more complex.
A first complexity is that very often
studies have samples of different sizes.
We have seen that the sampling
distribution of G is a normal
distribution with a mean of delta with a
sampling variance more or less equal to
four divided by the size of the study.
This means that if you take small
samples for instance samples of size 20
observed effect sizes fluctuate a lot
and can deviate a lot from the
population effect size.
But if instead we would take large
samples, the sampling distribution would
become much smaller. If for instance we
have two groups of size 100, the
sampling variance becomes becomes 4
divided by 200. This means that our
sampling distribution is much smaller.
In other words, that the observed effect
sizes are in general closer to the
population effect size.
Now suppose that you have access to
several observed effect sizes, some from
small studies and some from large
studies. You know that all these effect
sizes tell us something about the
population effect size. But as you can
see on this slide, effect sizes from
large studies probably are close to the
population effect size. Whereas for
small studies, observed effect sizes can
be far away from the population effect
size. Therefore, if you want to estimate
the population effect size, we are going
to look especially at the larger
studies.
Therefore, instead of calculating an
ordinary average, it is better to
calculate a weighted average of the
observed effect sizes. As weights, we
can use the size of the study or even
better we can use the precision which is
equal to one over the sampling variance.
If we have an observed effect size from
a large study, the sampling variance of
this effect size will be small.
Therefore, the precision of the effect
size will be high and a large weight
will be given to that study.
Note that if all studies would be of the
same size, the precision would be the
same for all these studies and the
weighted average of the observed effect
sizes would be exactly the same as the
ordinary average effect size.
A second complication is the following.
In our simulation, we assumed that
population effect sizes were exactly the
same in all 10 studies. Delta 1 is equal
to delta 2 is equal to delta 3 and so
on. Of course, even if the population
effect size is the same for all studies,
there can be differences between
observed effect sizes because in each
study only a sample of scores is taken.
In other words, observed effect sizes
can vary due to sampling variation and
the amount of sampling variation depends
on the size of the study.
Yet, it's also possible that the
assumption that the population effect
size is the same for all studies is not
true.
If a similar research question has been
studied multiple times, this is
typically not done in exactly the same
way. There can be a lot of differences
between studies. For instance, it's
possible that the kind of participants
is not the same in all studies. Maybe in
some studies children are studied
whereas in other studies adults are
studied. It's also possible that the
context of the study is not exactly the
same in all studies.
Also the outcome variables or the way in
which they are measured can vary across
studies.
Also the kind of and dose of treatment
can differ between studies. Another
study characteristic that can vary
between studies is a study design. Maybe
some studies may use an experimental
designs whereas other studies may use a
correlational design.
In some there can be a lot of
differences between studies. And
importantly, these differences can make
it unlikely that the population effect
size that is studied is exactly the same
in all studies.
So maybe there are also differences
between the population effect sizes. In
this scenario, there are two sources of
variation.
We have variation between the population
effect sizes from studies. So, variation
between the deltas
in metanalytic literature. This
variation in population effect sizes is
often called the true variation or the
systematic variation. On top of that, we
still have the sampling variation. For
instance, in study five, you can see
that population effect size delta 5 is
relatively small.
Yet, the observed effect size can be
different. It can by coincidence be even
smaller than the population effect size
or it can be larger than the population
effect size from that study.
Finally, we will look at the questions
and steps that can be distinguished in a
typical meta analysis.
In a meta analysis, we typically try to
answer multiple questions. First
question is, is there on average an
effect?
Secondly, if overall there is an effect,
how large is this effect? So we want to
test whether there is an effect and we
want to estimate the size of the effect.
Another question that is very often
answered in a meta analysis is can we
consider population effect sizes to be
the same in all studies. If not, we talk
about heterogeneity.
We do not only want to test whether
there is heterogeneity, we also want to
estimate the size of heterogeneity.
Next, if there is heterogeneity,
a challenge is to try to explain this
between study varants. In what kind of
studies is the effect larger than in
what other kind of studies?
Another question that is sometimes but
not often answered in a meta analysis is
what is the effect in specific
individual studies? Based on the results
of a meta analysis, we can indeed make
improved estimates of the effect sizes
for specific studies.
The coming sessions, we will look at how
we can answer these different questions.
In a typical meta analysis, multiple
steps are taken. The first step is a
formulation of research question.
Afterwards, a search is done for
studies. Often there will be a lot of
hits, a lot of potentially relevant
studies, but these may not all be
relevant for our research interest or
research question.
In the third step, therefore, we will
select the relevant studies.
After selecting the relevant studies, we
will extract the data that we need for
doing our meta analysis.
Next, we convert the data to a common
effect size measure.
In a statistical analysis, we combine
and compare these effect sizes. We also
typically look for moderator variables.
These are study characteristics that are
related to the size of the effect and
therefore explain the heterogenity.
Finally, we report the results and draw
conclusions.
These steps define the structure of this
course.