Dear students, welcome in this course on
ma analysis. I'm inviata. I am a
professor of statistics and methodology
at the faculty of psychology and
educational sciences of the Kuven.
Long time ago, I did a PhD study on the
use of multi-level models also called
mix models for doing meta analysis.
Nowadays, I have two research lines.
First, I'm doing methodological research
on meta analytic techniques and models
and I'm involved in applied meta
analysis.
Second, I'm doing research on learning
analytics, which is the collection of
data when students use technology as
well as the analysis of these data in
order to optimize and personalize the
learning environment.
I also teach statistical courses,
especially introductory courses at the
faculty of psychology and educational
sciences at K Louven, mainly at the
compass in Cort, which is about 100
kilometers west of Luven. I hope you
will enjoy this course and you will
learn a lot. Good luck.