applications and extensions.
A first application is discussed in
another PowerPoint presentation. Here I
would like to focus on a second
application of meta analysis, the meta
analysis of single case experimental
studies.
Marion and others investigated
whether they could stimulate the
response behavior of students by working
with response cards. Current practice is
that students raise their hand after the
teacher asks a question and that only
one or maximally two or three students
get a chance to give an answer
by working with response cards. So these
are cards on which students
can write their answer.
In principle, all students can formulate
an answer.
Here you see the results for one
student, a student from the fourth year
of primary education as presented by the
researchers.
Let us look at the black dots. In
several time intervals, it was counted
how many times the student gave an
answer.
Observations were done during four
phases. The first phase is a baseline
phase in which the traditional approach
was used.
In the second phase, a treatment phase,
response cards were used. The third
phase is again a baseline phase, so
without response cards. Whereas the
fourth the final phase is again a
response card phase. So on the xaxis you
see the sessions the time intervals on
the yaxis you see the number of academic
responses.
This design is called an abab design.
You can see that in the A phases, so the
baseline phases with a traditional
approach, the student regularly raised
his hand but could not often give an
answer. Whereas in the B phases, the
student more frequently formulated an
answer.
The graph suggests that there is indeed
an effect of using response cards on the
number of responses given. But you may
wonder whether the effect we observed is
statistically significant. Moreover, we
could be interested in an estimate of
the size of the effect.
In single case studies, not often effect
sizes are calculated.
It is even not common practice to
perform statistical significance tests.
So that typically no test statistics are
available that could be used to
calculate effect sizes.
Instead, results are often presented in
a graph like the one I showed earlier.
Yet, this tradition means an advantage
for the meta analyst since it becomes
possible to retrieve the raw data, which
is usually not the case for group
comparison studies.
One way to get insight in the size and
significance of the effect is to use a
regression analysis. Response variable
for the student is described
using a regression equation with one
predictor, more specifically a treatment
dummy indicator with value zero for the
baseline faces and one for the treatment
phases.
For the baseline phases, the treatment
variable is equal to zero and therefore
the expected number of answers equals
beta 0.
In the response card condition, the
treatment variable is equal to one and
therefore the expected number of answers
equals beta 0 plus beta 1.
Beta 1 therefore indicates how much the
expected number of answers increases or
decreases if response cards are used.
Beta 1 therefore can be regarded as a
measure of the effect
in our regression analysis. We therefore
can estimate and test the size of the
effect of the treatment.
The model is a peace-wise regression
model. Between phases, the regression
line is interrupted.
In baseline conditions, the curve is a
horizontal line with beta 0 as hat. In
the response card condition, this is a
line with beta 0 plus beta 1 as eight.
To express the size of the effect, we
could therefore use the regression
coefficient beta one. A problem of this
measure, however, is that it depends on
the scale that is used. If for instance
intervals are made 10 times as large,
the expected means in both phases will
be 10 times as large. And also the
coefficient beta 1 will be 10 times
larger.
Therefore, it may be a good idea to
standardize the measure. For instance,
by dividing the mean difference by the
within phase standard deviation.
It is also possible to divide scores
directly by the root of the pulled uh
variance.
This standardized mean difference can be
estimated by dividing the difference in
the observed phase means by the square
root of the pulled within phase
variance.
This measure is very similar to the
standardized mean difference used in
group comparison studies.
Note that the serious drawback of a
single case study is that it gives
primarily information about one single
case, but it that it does not give a lot
of information about the population of
cases. While this could be especially
interesting for most of us,
an obvious solution to this problem is a
replication of the study. This may be a
direct replication. This is a
replication of the study in exactly the
same conditions only with another
subject.
But it's also possible to do a
systematic replication. This is a
replication of the study but varying one
or more characteristics of for instance
the treatment to look for factors that
may moderate the treatment effect.
Sometimes the experiment
is replicated in the study itself. for
instance using a multiple baseline
design or it is replicated in another
study.
This raises the question of how to
combined results
of several cases in a quantitative way
in the experiment of Narion. In total,
six subjects participated.
We could perform a peace-wise regression
analysis for each of these subjects. You
can see that the pattern is very similar
for all subjects, but not equal. If you
compare, for instance, student one with
student five, you can see that the first
student gives less answers in the
baseline phase, but more in response
card condition.
Beta zero of student one therefore is
smaller but but beta one or the effect
is larger.
We could summarize the regression
equations of all students in one single
equation by adding an index J for the
case. The expected number of responses
for student J on moment I equals the
beta zero of that student J plus if the
observation at moment I falls in the
response card condition the beta 1 of
that student.
The index J therefore indicates that
both the baseline and the effect size
can vary over cases.
This variation over students
can be described using additional
regression equations. For instance,
simple equations with only an intercept
and a student specific residual.
Gamma 0 therefore refers to the average
level of performance during the baseline
phases over all cases. Whereas gamma 1 0
is the size of the mean effect
over all cases. The variances of U0 and
U1 indicate the between student variance
in initial level and in the effect
respectively.
You recognize in this model a
multi-level model. A multi-level model
consists of regression equations at
several levels typically assuming a
normal distribution for the residuals at
each of the levels. The parameters that
are estimated in a multi-level model in
a multi-level anal an analysis are the
regression coefficients at the highest
level as well as the variances and
co-variances of the residuals at each of
the levels.
We used the restricted maximum
likelihood procedure implemented in
susprom mixed to estimate the parameters
of the model.
Here are the results. You can see that
the mean baseline level equals about
one. Which means that in a baseline
condition, students answered on average
about one time per interval.
In the response card condition, the mean
number of answers per interval is about
14 points higher. Between parenthesis,
you can see the standard error of the
estimate. Note that the ratio of the
estimate over the standard error is
approximately standard normally
distributed.
Therefore, we can see that the effect of
using response cards is statistically
significant for commonly used
significance levels.
Further, you can see that there are no
differences between students in the
baseline level, but that there is a
tendency that the effect varies over
students.
Comparing the ratio of estimates over
the standard error to a standard normal
distribution, you can see that this
tendency is statistically not
significant at the 0.05 significance
level. Also, when using a more
appropriate likelihood tracio test, this
variance appears to be statistically
nonsignificant.
Finally, you can see that the response
behavior clearly varies more over time
intervals within a student than over
students. We want to note that the
number of cases in fact is too low to
perform a multi-level analysis
and especially to have powerful
statistical tests. But the example was
used for illustrative purposes.
A second example, Shogran and colleagues
did a meta analysis on 13 single case
studies including in total 30 cases.
Investigating whether giving the pro
possibility to make choices in their
tasks or in the order of the tasks can
reduce the amount of problem behavior in
the classroom.
The authors used relatively simple
metalytic procedures. For instance, by
calculating means of a simple effect
size measure,
we did replicate the meta analysis using
a multi-level model. Since in most of
the studies more than one case was
investigated, we used a three-level
model. At the first level, the variation
within case J over of study K over
measurement occasions is described.
The amount of problem behavior was
requested on a dummy variable indicating
whether on moment I the child was given
the choice between several tasks or not.
Both the expected amount in the baseline
condition as the expected effect of
being given the choice is allowed to
vary. You can see that beta 1 jk varies
over cases around a mean effect for
study k. This is theta
10 k and that the study specific effects
vary around an overall treatment effect
gamma 10.
Note that there were differences between
studies in the scales.
Therefore, we first performed a separate
regression analysis for each case and
calculated the root mean squared error.
So, it's a standard deviation of the
residual of the first level equation.
Next, we divided the scores for each
case by this root mean square error.
Here you can see the results of the
multi-level analysis. You can see that
under the baseline condition, the
expected amount of problem behavior was
about three standard deviations above
zero.
In the treatment condition, so when the
child was given the choice, the amount
of problem behavior was 1.84 standard
deviations smaller,
a mean effect that is statistically
significant.
standard the parameter estimate divided
by the standard error of 46 gives a ZV
value of four corresponding to a very
small p value when comparing this value
to a standard normal distribution.
You can see that there is no significant
variation between studies in both the
baseline performance and in the effect,
but that there are substantial
differences between cases
at level two.
To explain differences between cases and
studies, characteristics of the cases or
characteristics of the studies can be
included in the equations describing the
variation over groups.
If you would substitute beta 1 jk from
the level one equation by the level two
equation, you could see that theta 111
is a coefficient of an interaction term
interaction term of the case
characteristic set and the choice dummy
variable. In other words, if data 1 one
is different from zero, this means that
the size of the effect depends on Z and
therefore Z is a moderator variable.
Similarly, gamma 101 refers to the
moderator effect of a stud
characteristic W.
To illustrate the exploration of
possible moderating effects, we included
a case characteristic, more specifically
gender, and a study characteristic, more
specifically, whether the student could
choose the task or merely the order of
the tasks.
You can see that the interaction of both
characteristics with a choice variable
was statistically not significant
indicating the effect of having choice
on problem behavior does not depend on
these case and study characteristics.
Note that beta 1 again can be regarded
as an effect effect size measure since
we already standardized the response
variable. Beta 1 is already a
standardized mean difference.
Sometimes it may be difficult to
retrieve all raw data.
While it still might be possible to
calculate a standardized mean difference
as an alternative to the analysis of the
raw data, we could also first calculate
a standardized mean difference for each
case and combine this with a tree level
model.
The first level equation now becomes the
following. The observed effect size G
equals the population effect size
beta 1 plus random residual.
At the second and the third level, the
equations for the variation of the
effect over cases or over studies remain
the same, but the equations for
describing the variation of the baseline
performance are dropped because they are
not of importance anymore.
In the left column, you can see the
results of the analysis on road data for
the model we discussed before. In the
right column, you can see the results
for the analysis of the effect size
measures. You can see that the estimates
are very similar and that the
conclusions are the same. This analysis
illustrates that we do not need draw
data. Combining effect sizes gives the
same results.
If you would have very large data sets,
analyzing effect sizes can go faster and
there may be a higher probability that
the estimation procedure converges.
But combining draw data on the other
hand has the advantage that it is
possible to adapt the first level
equation for instance to include
additional level one variables.
The flexibility of the multi-level model
allows for several extensions.
First extension is to allow for more
complex variance uh coariance structures
at one of the levels. For instance, it
may be a too strong assumption to assume
that scores from a case are independent
from each other. And it may be more
prudent to allow for a possible
outcreoration.
To take into account that measurements
that are close to each other in time are
more similar than measurements that are
farther apart in time.
Secondly,
other coariantss can be included also at
the first level. For instance, an
additional dummy variable at the first
level to compare a second treatment with
the baseline.
Thirdly, linear trends can be taken into
account by including a time variable t
in the first level model with a main
effect and an interaction effect with a
treatment dummy called D in this
equation.
The interpretation of this equation
becomes more clear when we restructure
the terms. Intercept of the equation is
equal to beta 1 and beta 0 plus beta 1
times the treatment dummy variable D. In
the baseline phase, the treatment dummy
variable is equal to zero. So the
intercept is equal to beta 0. In the
treatment phase, the intercept is equal
to beta 0 plus beta 1.
Note that the intercept is the expected
value at time zero. By centering the
time variable around the value at the
end of the baseline phase, beta 0 can be
interpreted as a level of the outcome at
the end of the baseline phase.
Beta 1 can be interpreted as the
immediate effect of the treatment.
Similarly, the trend over time is equal
to beta 2 in the baseline phase and beta
2 plus beta 3 in the treatment phase.
Beta 3 therefore can be interpreted as
the difference between the slope in the
treatment condition
and the slope in the baseline condition.
Note that now we have two effect sizes
for each case. Beta one which expresses
the size of the effect on or the
immediate treatment effect the effect on
the level and beta 3 which expresses the
effect on the slope respectively.